<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra Pound</persName>, <date when="1914-11-03"
               >03 November 1914</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref=""> <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here --> </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="drr">Danielle Richards</persName>
               <persName ref="fo">Felix Oke</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427338414$8i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc><p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "(Ezra)" in pencil at the top of first page. The top of the first page also reads "COPY" and "<placeName key="brookline">Brookline Mass.</placeName>."Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography --> </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            &personography;
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
            <div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1914-11-03">November 3rd. 1914</date></dateline>
               <salute>My dear Mr. <persName key="ezra_pound">Pound</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am exceedingly sorry for this advertisement. It is, of course, quite ridiculous and the fact that I 
            am put down as <quote>"foremost member"</quote> was undoubtedly due to an underling’s error in the office. I told <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> 
            last spring that the inclusion of these two names was foolish, as neither <persName key="wb_yeats">Yeats</persName> nor <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>
            were <orgName key="imagists">Imagists</orgName>, and I supposed that the matter was settled. Imagine my feelings when I came home and found these names
            printed on the jackets. But indeed you have lived so long out of <placeName key="unitedStates">America</placeName> that you seem to have forgotten
            American methods of advertising. The names were simply put in to boom the <title key="some_imagist_poets">book</title>, a thing which is constantly done over
            here and would not in any way surprise anyone in this country. The ludicrous thing is that in my preface I have carefully said that I do not belong to any school.
            Undoubtedly the advertisement that you have pasted at the top of your paper was put in at the same time as the ones in <title key="poetry">"Poetry."</title>
            I fear that it may even appear in the <date when="1914-11">November</date> magazine, although I tried to stop it in time, but those things are printed so long
            in advance that I think it may have been impossible. The new advertisements in the daily papers contain quotations from the reviews.</p> 
            <p>I can do no more and I think it would have been more gentlemanly for you to have realized from my cable to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>
               that I was doing all I could and that things would be adjusted as soon as possible.</p> 
            <p>As to my being put down as an Imagiste, you yourself are responsible for that. If you publish an <title key="anthologyDesImagistes">"Anthology des Imagistes"</title>
               and include a person’s work in it, naturally the publishers consider that that person belongs to that group. You will remember that I wrote you <date when="1913">last winter</date>
               and told you that 
            <pb n="2">
            if yours was to be an Imagiste anthology I did not think I belonged in it. You never took the trouble to answer my letter, and the next thing I knew was
            that I saw my name in the advance advertisement which appeared in the <title key="newYorkTimes">New York Times</title>. Having been given the name of
               Imagiste I shall certainly not repudiate it. One of the foremost members I certainly am, for the amount that I have published and the attention it has
               attracted I think warrants my being considered in that category. You have only yourself to thank for including me in the group, and it is not agreeable
               to feel that you only wished the inclusion as long as I could be kept obscure and insignificant.</p> 
            <p>This is not a generous attitude and I regret that you saw fit to take it. As to the names of the other members of the group not being included
               in the advertisement, let me point out to you that the publishers were anxious to sell the book and to do so they naturally wanted to use names
               which were of world-wide reputation. The names of the rest of the group will appear when our anthology is printed, in which I am in no way
               treated differently from the others and, by the alphabetical position of my name, the last person in the book. Far from wishing to keep other members
               of the group insignificant and unknown I have given a very handsome tribute to Richard and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> in an article I
               wrote from <placeName key="london">London</placeName> to <title key="littleReview">"The Little Review"</title>.</p> <!--the T here seems to be doubletyped, it appears due to a typewriter error-->
            <p>As to your suggestion that the publishers be sued for libel, you have of course no suit, as even in cement and soap you would have to get out a patent
               in order to sue anyone. So <subst>fa<del type="strikethrough">s</del><add place="above">r</add></subst> as I know you have not copyrighted the name <quote>"Imagiste,"</quote> 
               I have never heard of a school of poetry being copyrighted,
               I doubt if it could be done. But if you should feel inclined to sue, I should be exceedingly delighted as then they would put new jackets on the book
               which I should greatly prefer. Also, it would be a good advertisement. And, in the third place, you would be obliged to prove my inclusion in your group
               as a libel, and it would be interesting to see whether that could be done.</p> 
            <pb n="3">
            <p>I do think it is a mistake to take such an unimportant thing so seriously, and I think it is a wrong attitude to take towards me when I had already expressed
               my regret and have been doing all in my power to suppress the advertisement which I object to as much as you do.</p> 
            <closer>Very sincerely yours,</closer>
      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
