<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-05-29"
                    >May 29, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$102i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of four sheets of paper with typing on each side of the first three and on one
                        side of the last. On the top of each sheet (every other page), excluding the first, there is a page
                        number in the center. There are a few areas where things are crossed out and typewriting or
                        handwriting is added to make changes.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-05-29">May 29, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I think I have at last discovered the mystery of the books not having been received by
                <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName>. The sheets were shipped on the “Anglian” on the 16th of April. <persName key="roger_scaife">Mr. Scaife</persName>, who is
                business manager of <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin’s</orgName>, has ascertained from the Company that the “<placeName key="anglian">Anglian</placeName>”
                reached <placeName key="liverpool">Liverpool</placeName> safely, in fact that she was due back here yesterday. But Mr. Scaife tells me
                that he fears the delay occurred on the docks in Liverpool, as he understands that merchandise is
                piled up all over the docks there, and delivery is dreadfully delayed.</p>
            <p>He sent a weekend cable last Friday to Constable, requesting <persName key="michael_sadleir">Sadler</persName> to look the matter up
                and, if necessary, to send someone to Liverpool to ferret out the sheets. He says that, if we send
                any more, they will probably be delayed in the same way, and will certainly not reach Constable
                so quickly as the original sheets would do. Houghton Mifflin are just as annoyed as you are
                about it. They realize perfectly the fact that the copyright is lost, and that the delay will occasion
                a lull in the interest about the book. It is most unfortunate, but I do not believe we can blame the
                publishers here. It would seem to be a case of conditions in the freight service occasioned by the
                war. But the bad thing is that Constable, with the exception of Sadler, do not seem to know
                anything about this business. I think myself that they are the worst firm for selling things in the
                world.</p>
            <p>I am writing a letter to Sadler now, requesting him to do everything in his power to get
                our book properly on the market. I do not suppose it will be as well put on as it is here, for here I
                am paying for a lot of separate advertising myself; and that, of course, I cannot do in England as
                Constable bought their copies of the book outright, and I no longer own them. The venture,
                therefore, is entirely theirs as far as the English edition is concerned.</p>
            <p>The interest here is enormous, as you will see by the clippings I am sending you. The
                reviews are uniformly bad; but as they are written by people entirely unfitted for the task, both
                from education and predilection, (the ordinary cheap, hack reviewer in fact,) that does not make
                much difference. Everybody seems to be talking about it a good deal; but our sale is not any too
                brilliant, ten copies more however since I last wrote, making 470 in all. Mr. Scaife thinks that the
                way <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> made a mistake in the first figures was that somehow he counted the figures
                for the rest of the series. The edition was 750. I think we stand a chance of selling the edition out
                before the year is over.</p>
            <p>I am sending you a beastly slam that we had in “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>,” by a man named
                <persName key="conrad_aiken">Conrad Aiken</persName>. He was in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> last summer, 
                I believe, and fraternized with <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>. He writes
                very poor poetry: old-fashioned and fearfully inverted. I cannot help wondering how much his
                acquaintance with Ezra has influenced him in jumping on us. It is not a review – merely an
                article out of a blue sky, and I do not believe will do us much harm. <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> is answering for
                it for “The New Republic.” The excuse they gave for publishing an article of that kind, when
                they purport to be my friends, is that they wanted to open a discussion. As Aiken accuses us of
                interpuffing I did not think that any of us could write the answer. Ferris’s tongue is tied, because
                he publishes the book, so Braithwaite seemed the only thing, and as he is heart and soul with us
                and was most anxious to do it, I had to take him <u><foreign xml:lang="fr">faute de mieux</foreign></u><anchor xml:id="n1"/><!-- Is this the right order of operations to show that this French phrase is underlined?? -->.</p>
            <p>I took “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>” in to Roger Scaife the other day, rather hoping that he might think
                well of distributing it; but he was just as much against the plan as Ferris was, although he thinks
                that, if <persName key="may_sinclair">May Sinclair</persName> has really written a good article on us in the next “Egoist,” it might be well
                to distribute that; so you had better send me <measure quantity="50" unit="copies">50 copies</measure> anyway, possibly more. I had a scheme
                that the two numbers might be distributed together, and if I can persuade the publishers that that
                is a wise thing to do, I will send out this May number at the same time with the June.</p>
            <p><persName key="remy_gourmont">Remy de Gourmont’s</persName> little notice will do us a lot of good here, slight though it is. I have
                already translated it, and portions of it are going into an advertisement; and Braithwaite will
                quote it in his defenses for “The New Republic.” The real difficulty here is that there are no
                prose writers who are interested enough to defend us.</p>
            <p>Where is <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>? Has he lost interest in us, or have you and he fought, or has he given
                up writing in the “<title key="outlook" level="j">Outlook</title>?” It is an awful hard row to hoe, Richard, but I think we are getting
                on. Certainly, we do not lack publicity now. I only long for people to get away from the freak
                attitude toward us, and take us for the serious and earnest poets that we are.</p>
            <p>A man named <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Kreymborg</persName>, who used to edit “<title key="glebe" level="j">The Glebe</title>,” is getting up a little magazine
                called “<title key="others" level="j">Others</title>.” He has written to ask both <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> and me for contributions. He tells me that
                “Pound, <persName key="john_rodker">Rodker</persName>, <persName key="skipwith_cannell">Cannell</persName>, <persName key="horace_holley">Holley</persName>, 
                <persName key="wc_williams">Williams</persName>, and <persName key="orrick_johns">Johns</persName>” have responded to his request. Ezra
                undoubtedly is going to try to run this paper in his own way; so Fletcher and I thought it was just
                as well to send him contributions at once, so as to <del rend="strikethrough">give</del> <add place="above">show</add> 
                Ezra <del rend="strikethrough">a notion</del> that he could not keep
                us out of it, so we have sent things to him. I do not know whether he has written to you yet, but if
                I were you, I should send him some of yours and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> things. His address is: Alfred
                Kreymborg, Grantwood, New Jersey.</p>
            <p>You wrote and asked me about <persName key="guido_bruno">Bruno</persName>. They tell me that he is a little Jew, who is frankly
                out for the money. The <persName key="albert_boni" key="charles_boni">Bonis</persName> <!-- Can I have two keys? "Bonis" refers to Albert and Charles Boni -->
                in New York told me that his <title key="brunosWeekly" level="j">paper</title> was very poor; and I saw some
                quotations the other day from it, which were beneath contempt; but I have never seen it myself,
                and I do not know anything about the man. He seems to be just a fellow who thinks the other
                young men are making some money out of the new movements, and he wants to try. If I can find
                out anything more about him, I will let you know.</p>
            <p>Do not forget to send me any clippings that come out about us, although I suppose we
                cannot expect any until the book is issued in England.</p>
            <p><persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> is still going on, she writes me, though on what I cannot imagine. I
                have an article on <placeName key="poetryBookshop">The Poetry Bookshop</placeName> in the current number,<anchor xml:id="n2"/> which was written to make up
                for <add place="margin">my</add> having unwittingly hurt <persName key="harold_monro">Monro’s</persName> feelings 
                in my “<title key="letterFromLondon" level="a">London Letter</title>.” I tried very hard not to
                appear to praise him unduly; but I really think he deserves credit for having tried to do something
                for poetry. His limitations are congenital, and in no way due to a commercial or narrow-minded
                spirit, I am convinced. I am glad it did not come out until after his review, or people might have
                thought I was trying to curry favor with him.</p>
            <p>I quite agree with you that quiet, unsurperlative speech is the proper way to criticise; but
                you know what Fletcher is: always extreme, one way or the other, and I cannot get him to write
                judicially, because it is not his nature.</p>
            <p>I am delighted to think that you will defend me in the next number of “The Egoist”
                because, as I have repeatedly told you, I think your criticism is excellent, honest, and just. Your
                article on Ezra was a little masterpiece of discrimination.</p>
            <closer>Lots of love to Hilda,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">French, meaning for want of a better alternative.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb"><persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName>, "The Poetry Bookshop," <title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title> Vol. 2, No. 3 (May, 1915).</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
