<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-03-25"
                    >March 25, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$190i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of three sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. At the
                        top of each page except the first there is “R.A.” and the page number in the left corner and the
                        date in the right corner. There is a watermark on the paper that reads “Berkshire Linen U.S.A.”
                        Following the document of the letter are three delivery receipts. Each is the size of 1/3 sheet of
                        paper. The first is perforated at the top and bottom, the second is torn at the top with a jagged
                        edge, and the third has a jagged edge on both the top and bottom. The first receipt is for Letter
                        Parcel number 14833. “Fenway Station” is stamped on the P.O. (post office) line. The writing on
                        the receipt, in pencil, is difficult to read, but it appears to say that it was received for registration
                        by “Lowell, Heath St.” The “addressed to” says Richard Aldington, Paracombe [illegible]
                        Devon, Engl. The signature over “To addressee or order” is illegible. The second receipt is for
                        Letter Parcel 15688, also from Fenway Station. The recipient is, again, Lowell, Heath St., with a
                        word after “St.” that starts with B. The addressee is Richard Aldington, Esq, North Devonshire,
                        Eng, Garcombe. The third receipt does not have a legible number, though it ends with “203.”
                        The date appears to be April 20th (4-20). The recipient is “A. Lowell, Heath St.”
                        The addressee is R. Aldington, Paracombe Engl.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-03-25">March 25, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I am sorry to say that <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName> did not pay up on the 15th, as he agreed to do. As I told
                him that I should put the matter into the hands of a lawyer if he did not pay on that day, I put
                it into the hands of my <persName key="william_putnam">brother-in-law</persName>, with the very unsatisfactory result that he reports, after
                investigation, that Brown’s business is mortgaged, so that it is almost impossible to get
                anything out of him, and the property cannot be attached on this account, apparently. We
                have forced him to engage a lawyer to defend himself, which is something; but, of course,
                there is no use carrying it into court, as it would merely run him into bankruptcy – which
                would be only a name, as he has nothing to lose by going bankrupt – and he could start
                business again under another name. Will does not at all advise suing him, therefore, but
                thinks that we shall get the thirty dollars that he owes you before very long, as Brown’s
                lawyer says he has some assets which will come in shortly.</p>
            <p>I am enclosing a power of attorney which Will has given me, because whatever I do
                or say, Brown replies that he has had other instructions from you; and, of course, for two
                people to do business with any results at this distance is impossible. If I am to consider
                myself your agent in regard to your American affairs, I must be able to make myself obeyed
                by the publishers, and I cannot do that legally without a power of attorney. If, on the other
                hand, you do not wish to sign this power of attorney (which, it seems to me,
                you very possibly may not), I think it would be best for you to do all your business yourself by letter.
                But I appreciate the almost impossibility of doing this at such a distance, and with the mail in
                such a condition as it is between here and <placeName key="England">England</placeName>; and I shall be perfectly delighted to act as
                your agent in every instance that you desire, but I must have this power of attorney.</p>
            <p>Here is another instance: when you wrote to <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> that if we had withdrawn our
                poems from <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Kreymborg’s</persName> <title key="othersAnthology">Anthology</title> you would like to have yours withdrawn also, Fletcher
                and I talked it over together and decided that it would be better for me to write to
                Kreymborg, rather than for him to do so. I therefore wrote to Kreymborg, saying that you had
                sent instructions that if we had withdrawn our poems you wished to have yours withdrawn
                also. I have just seen a review of Kreymborg’s Anthology in which they speak of a poem of
                yours. I feel sure that Mr. Kreymborg would have obeyed my orders had he not received a
                later letter from you giving him different ones, - a letter which you presumably wrote without
                knowing what we had done about the matter. If I knew whether you had written or not, I
                could take some steps in the matter. If I had this power of attorney I could prevent the
                publication of that Anthology until a new edition could be got out without your poems. As it
                is, I can do nothing without knowing how you have acted in the matter. It is a fearful
                business running anybody else’s affairs! I try to do the best possible thing I can, and
                what I think you would like to have me do; and, of course, I very often don’t succeed.</p>
            <p>Brown has certainly been an awful mess; but <title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">the book</title> is out.<anchor xml:id="n1"/> I have a copy here, and I
                suppose he sent you one. I will try and find out whether he has or not, and if not, get you one
                and send it. It is not as attractive as the English edition, but it is not at all bad, and I am
                delighted to have it on the market, as long as we can not stop its publication. And I don’t
                really know that if we stopped the publication it would be of any advantage. You may sell a
                few copies here, even through Brown, although I believe his financial affairs are such that his
                publications are not handled generally by booksellers.</p>
            <p>I am most sincerely sorry that I got you in for all this, but nobody spoke of Brown as
                dishonest at the time I suggested his writing to you about our book, and now everybody
                speaks of him as dishonest; and there you are!</p>
            <p>I think in working for your interests here (if you decide to entrust them to me), it
                would be better to leave them entirely in my hands, and not write some of your instructions
                to Fletcher. It is quite impossible to say how long Fletcher will remain in this part of the
                country, although I am delighted to say I think he is quite settled down here and seems to
                enjoy himself. But even as it is, he acts on his part, and I act on mine, and you act on yours,
                and the situation is quite impossible, from a business point of view. Fletcher is not very
                practical, although full of enthusiasm and energy, and I often have to act as a go-between
                between him and editors here – or, rather, I have to straighten out unfortunate situations
                which his impetuosities create for him.</p>
            <p>Now, as I said before, if you prefer to run all your own affairs, do not hesitate to tell
                me. I cannot say that I think I have made a brilliant success of your affairs so far, but you can
                be quite sure that that is not from want of trying. Only, I should like some definite
                instructions from you as to whether I am to consider myself your legal agent, with power of
                attorney, or not. If the former, I should, of course, have the power to sign contracts and
                manage your affairs as I should my own, - collect your royalties and transmit the money to
                you as I do on the “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="s">Imagist Anthology</title>”. If I am not to be your agent, I think it would be
                better to have all this work sent direct to England, with the exception, of course, of the
                “Imagist Anthology”, as I am the holder of the contract for that work, and it is in my name. I
                think the method that has hitherto pertained should be adhered to under all circumstances.</p>
            <p>Fletcher tells me that he wrote you in regard to the little notice of courtesy which we
                have been obliged to put in the “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>” for <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>. Miss Monroe was very
                much upset last year at not being specially referred to in our Preface. She considers that she
                gave the movement its first start – and I think we must admit that she did. I have just been in
                <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, lecturing, and I saw Miss Monroe and told her that we were, none of us, 
                overpleased with the way she was treating us now; that we did not consider that she
                published us enough, nor did we consider that she mentioned us enough in her editorials. I
                think I made some little impression, but not as much as I could wish. Talking to Harriet is a
                good deal like trying to dent a Scotch mist.</p>
            <p>Last year, when she wrote to us, she was in an especially annoyed frame of mind; and
                in order to appease her wrath, which <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> seemed to think was extremely worth
                appeasing, he strongly advised me to promise to put some notice of her into the Preface of
                this “Anthology”. I should have told you at the time, but I am afraid it slipped my mind. This
                Preface being all written, Fletcher and I decided that it would be impossible to put the notice
                in the Preface. We therefore have incorporated a short paragraph among the
                acknowledgements. As I told you, the book had to go to press, and there was not time to
                consult you when I remembered it, and the matter was so trifling, I did not think that you
                would mind very much. But I certainly will try to be more business-like in future, and not
                commit my fellow-Imagists to anything without their consent.</p>
            <p>My lecture in Chicago was called “The New Poetry, With a Special Reference to
                Imagism”, and was given in <persName key="maurice_browne">Maurice Brown’s</persName> [sic] <orgName key="littleTheatre">Little Theatre</orgName>. 
                He is <persName key="harold_monro">Harold Munro’s</persName> [sic] brother-in-law. The auditorium is small, but it was crammed to overflowing, with people in
                the aisles, in defiance of the police regulations; and, as it was, they had to turn a hundred
                away from the door, as there were no seats for them. The interest aroused was really quite
                extraordinary. I read selections from all of us, and I think it should distinctly help the sale of
                the new “Anthology” and of your book.</p>
            <p>I am sending you a rather amusing <title key="andOtherPoets" level="m">book</title> of <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer’s</persName>, in which appear a
                number of parodies. They come out in the <title key="newYorkTribune" level="j">New York Tribune</title>, and, I think, will amuse you. I
                am sorry that none of you appear in the parodies, but at the time he wrote them I did not
                know him, and so was not able to read you and read you to him and impress upon him that
                we should be represented in any book of the sort. I think he only took me because of my
                Polyphonic Prose, which it amused him to do. In fact, we made acquaintance originally over
                this parody, which he sent to me with an apology. It is an extremely clever book, and, I am
                sure, will amuse you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>.</p>
            <p>Please give a great deal of love to Hilda, and please write soon. I miss your letters
                very much, and I have not heard from either you or Hilda for a long time.</p>
            <p>I returned from Chicago this morning, and Fletcher tells me he understands our
                “Anthology” is not to be out until the 13th of April. They have certainly sent me no proofs
                yet, which is most annoying.</p>
            <closer>With a great deal of love to you both,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington ultimately publishes his book, Images, Old and New (1916), with Edmund R. Brown's press, Four Seas.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>