<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-01-31"
                    >Jan. 31, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$177i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of two sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. At the
                        bottom of the first page there is some handwriting, intended to be inserted into the letter. On the
                        top of the second page in the left corner is “R.A.–2” to mark the page number, and in the right
                        corner is the date. There are a few places where words are scratched out and exchanged with
                        written words in pencil.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-01-31">Jan. 31, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>This is the Preface. I believe <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> has written to you about it already. It consists of the
                very best that Fletcher and I can do. It has been written, and written, and rewritten, and we have
                thought it out very carefully and verified all our illustrations. I think that it explains our position
                a little better than anything we have had so far, for the great difficulty now, I think, is
                misunderstanding. People are beginning to accept us, but they are still a little bit at sea as to what
                it all means, and I think the best thing we can do now is to explain ourselves, our position, and
                the rules by which we do our work. We have tried to make this as clear as possible. I took it in
                and read it to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> the other day, and he thinks it the best thing that has been written
                on the subject. He was so much taken with it that he wants to issue it as a separate circular, as he
                thinks it will do everything to help the sale of the book.</p>
            <p>Of course, you are at liberty to change it if you see fit, but I rather hope you won’t change
                it, as I think a thing gone over too many times loses its unity, and I am sure there is nothing here
                that we cannot all subscribe to, and as you people did not offer a preface this year, we thought
                we had better offer you one. I would suggest that, if you can, you leave it exactly as it is,
                and then you on your side can write next year’s preface if you want to.</p>
            <p>If you like it as it is, I wish you would cable “Yes.” My cable address is “<placeName key="sevenels">Sevenels, Boston</placeName>.” 
                There is no need of putting any name on, and if you will just cable: “Sevenels, Boston,
                Yes” I shall understand. <add place="margin">I don’t know whether you are allowed to use [unreadable] addresses now[.]</add> 
                And then if you will tell me the price of the cable, I will send it over to you at once. The time is
                so short that Ferris Greenslet feels we must start to print as quickly as possible. As it is now, we
                shall come out later than any of the rest of the series.</p>
            <p>I received this morning your letter of January 16th. You see how long it takes letters to
                come. You will by this time have got my letter saying I received all your poems safely. Your
                contribution is entirely decided upon, including “<title key="whitechapel" level="a">Whitechapel</title>,” but I am still waiting to hear
                what <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> is going to do after she receives my letter, what <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> is going to do in regard to
                substituting something for “<title key="evil" level="a">Evil</title>,” and what you wish to do in regard to our poems. You say in
                this letter to do exactly what I like about my poems, which looks to me as if you did not like any
                of them very much. I wish you would write a little more fully, as I want to please you, and so
                does Fletcher, but of course we must have some definite word to go on. If I only knew these
                things, we could start printing the poems and print the Preface later, but as it is we are
                completely hung up until we hear from you more fully, so I hope you will answer right straight
                away. I hope, in fact, that you will have answered long before you got this letter. It takes so long
                for letters to come and go now. You seem to be constantly surprised that you have not had
                answers from me, when I have written immediately on receiving your letters. It is awfully
                discouraging about the length of time it takes, and makes doing business between <placeName key="england">England</placeName> and
                America fearfully hard. I dread your next letters, I am afraid that you will be hurt at something I
                may have said. In explaining things flat-footedly and just as they are, one is apt to make them
                sound more severe than they are intended; but surely, we have worked so long together now; and
                have got along so well that even in cases where we may disagree or where we may have some
                reason to <del rend="strikethrough">want proof of</del> <add place="above">reprove</add> the other fellow’s actions, we can at least realize that the same
                remarks made in conversation would have quite a different sound; and I am sure that you must
                realize by this time that I am so loyal as though I were English by immediate birth and not
                merely a couple of hundred years ago, and that under those circumstances you will take anything
                I may say, as I shall always take anything you may say, as friendship in disagreement, if we do
                disagree, but always in friendship. I feel very strongly about this, for there are no people to
                whom I cling more closely than I do to you and Hilda, and although you did hurt me about
                Flint’s <title key="frenchPoetsReview" level="a">review</title>, and I did feel it necessary to write as I did, still none of those things interfere
                with the main current, and that you must always believe.</p>
            <p>I had a very nice letter from <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> some days ago. If he was sore at one time, he is
                entirely over it now, and everything is all right in that quarter. I am having rather a bad time here,
                as I am the subject of a couple of nasty attacks: one in “<title key="reedysMirror" level="j">Reedy’s Mirror</title>,” and one in the 
                “<title key="newYorkTimes" level="j">New York Times</title>.” But Fletcher has answered the “Mirror,” and <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> writes me that he
                intends to defend me in the “<title key="chicagoEveningPost" level="j">Chicago Evening Post</title>.” There is no doubt about it, that poetry is a
                vital issue over here now, and people get as excited about it as they do over politics.</p>
            <p>I think I wrote you that Fletcher and I had taken our poems away from the <title key="othersAnthology" level="m">“Others”
                Anthology,</title> which I am sure is a good move. I suppose we shall all appear in <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet’s</persName>
                <title key="newPoetryAnthology" level="m"></title>Anthology, and I do not think that the “Others” Anthology has a chance. Fletcher saw a letter
                from <persName key="ts_eliot">Eliot</persName> yesterday, written from <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, 
                in which he says that <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra’s</persName> <title key="catholicAnthology" level="m">Catholic Anthology</title> is
                not selling well at all. They tell me it is out here, but there have been no advertisements and no
                reviews that I have seen, so if it came out, it must have come out singularly quietly. On the other
                hand, none of us can do anything without creating a stir which shows interest, and I think
                everything is going really very well, and I think this new <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> will clinch it. I think on the
                whole it is better than last year’s. But I do hope you can see your way to leaving the Preface as it
                is, as I am quite convinced that the public over here, with whom we have our largest sale, need
                just this Preface and will appreciate it.</p>
            <p>If you have not already written definitely about Fletcher’s and my poems, please do so,
                and do not forget to cable, as soon as you get this, about the Preface, because we ought to
                start on the printing at once. Also please tell Hilda to answer about her poems, because I cannot do
                anything until I get all these things settled.</p>
            <p>I am sending this off in a hurry to catch the steamer, the censor business does take so
                long with letters.</p>
            <closer>Love to both of you.</closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>