<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-01-13"
                    >Jan. 13, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$162i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of three sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. The
                        final page has only a little bit of writing at the top and is mostly empty. The edges of the pages
                        have some bent areas, and there are a few areas where someone has handwritten edits or
                        scratched out words.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-01-13">Jan. 13, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I feel very badly indeed to have raised your hopes to the pitch evidenced by your letter of
                December 28th. I sent you a cable yesterday to disabuse your mind of their being any immediate
                prospect of our having a paper here. In my letter of December 15th, I wrote you saying that I
                would try to raise the money, if you cared to consider the job of editorship, and I told you that I
                had only got one subscriber then. I do not know what <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> may have written you, but you
                should know by this time that he is very enthusiastic and utopian, and not to be taken
                <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="fr">au pied de la lettre</foreign></hi>. 
                I fear he must have given you the idea that there was more immediate chance 
                of our being able to raise the money for the paper than there was.</p>
            <p>Since I wrote to you, I have been feeling round a little; and since receiving your letter I
                have asked for some subscriptions, always <del rend="strikethrough">somehow</del> <add place="above">however</add>
                with the same disheartening result. Nobody feels like giving anything just now, and I do not know 
                whether they will after the War, but I am bound to confess that the prospects are not bright.</p>
            <p>There has been a multiplication of little papers devoted to poetry since <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> started
                here. Another one, called “<title key="contemporaryVerse" level="j">Contemporary Verse</title>,” has issued its first number since I wrote to you.
                It is very poor, but all these things have tended to make people skeptical <del rend="strikethrough">on</del> 
                <add place="above">with</add> the advisability of helping small magazines. And the big ones, 
                which have much greater expenses, are failing right and left. You seem somehow to have got an 
                inflated idea of my intentions in regard to this paper. To run such a paper as you suggest, on 
                such lines as you suggest, would take an amount of money which I could never hope to command. 
                “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>” is endowed with 
                <measure type="currency" num="50,000">$50,000</measure> a year, and then I understand it does not pay, although 
                they have <measure quantity="10,000" commodity="subscribers">10,000 subscribers</measure>. Everything is on a larger scale here than in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. The country
                not having any one particular centre, magazines printed in one part of it are frequently not to be 
                found on the news-stands of another.It is impossible to get “<title key="reedysMirror" level="j">Reedy’s Mirror</title>” of <placeName key="stLouis">St. Louis</placeName> on any 
                news-stand in the East, or the <placeName key="sanFrancisco">San Francisco</placeName> “<title key="argonaut" level="j">Argonaut</title>” or the 
                “<title key="bellman" level="j">Bellman</title>.” All this makes the proposition 
                a much more difficult one. I have been looking into it a little more since I wrote you, and I am very sorry 
                indeed that I did not look into it more carefully before I even hinted to you that such an idea had entered my
                head. It seems quite impossible for us to attempt such a thing, even if we could raise the money.
                It never occurred to me that you would have an idea of branching out into an office, and a
                stenographer, and an office boy. Of course, I knew those things to be out of the question. No
                stenographer could be got for less than <measure type="currency" num="65.00">$65.00</measure> a month, which you will easily see would be
                utterly beyond our capacity to pay. I supposed that you would be willing to do the clerical work
                and send out the magazine once a month, as you do the <title key="poetsTranslationSeries" level="s">Poet’s Translation Series</title>, and it seemed
                to me that your salary should be determined with a view to that. In this, it seems, I was
                mistaken. I can perfectly understand our point of view, but I can equally see the impossibility of
                anything of the sort.</p>
            <p>Another thing is your desire to be the editor-in-chief, the court of final appeal. That, of
                course, you can see would not be possible. If we succeeded in raising any money, the people who
                gave it to us would give it on the guarantee of my character and my point of view. They do not
                know you, and your name would carry no weight over here at first. I should therefore be
                responsible to the people who gave us the money; and under those circumstances, it would be
                absolutely imperative that I should have the final say, and assume, in fact, the full responsibility.
                I should not expect to interfere with you any more than was absolutely necessary; but I should
                certainly direct the policy of the paper, and I am afraid I should not direct it upon strictly
                Imagistic lines. We could not have any paper if we did, because there are not enough Imagists to
                write for it. I suppose, really, it would be only exchanging <persName key="harriet_weaver">Miss Weaver</persName> for me, and although I
                imagine that you would not have such difficulty with me as you have with Miss Weaver, still it
                would be working in a subordinate position, although I do not think that you would feel that very
                much.</p>
            <p>Another point you mention is the running of propaganda for the Allies in the paper. That
                would be quite out of the question. In the first place, I do not think there ought to be any political
                articles of any kind in the paper. A great many papers and magazines are already devoted to
                matters of international and national import. We are in no way fitted to write upon political
                subjects. We should do it amateurishly and badly and make ourselves ridiculous. And there
                is another difficulty, and that is that although a great many people here are, as you know, in
                favour of the Allies, there are also a vast quantity in America who are pro-German. Just here in
                Boston, most of the people one knows are pro-Ally, and you know how pro-Ally I am myself.
                But what Europeans very rarely realize is that, in spite of individual opinions, the country as a
                whole is neutral, really neutral, in the sense that each side neutralizes the other. I do not myself
                believe it is possible for us to go to war on either side, because I think there are enough
                sympathizers on the other side in Congress to prevent our declaring war. Under these
                circumstances, we are obliged to maintain a certain elasticity and courtesy in our daily life. I
                personally have given up sending any poems of mine to “<title key="international" level="">The International</title>,” because 
                <persName key="george_viereck">Mr. Viereck</persName> is so violently pro-German, and his other paper, 
                “<title key="fatherland" level="">The Fatherland</title>,” is the official paper
                for hyphenated Americans. He has been peculiarly blatant and offensive. But there are many
                other papers which are distinctly Germanistic in leaning, although they wisely refrain from
                polemics in which my poems appear and those of other people. If you come to this country, you
                will find yourself constantly thrown with Germans and German sympathizers, and it will be
                necessary to treat them as calmly and as pleasantly as if there were no war. We could not
                possibly antagonize all the German sympathizers by running any propaganda whatever. I think
                we should remain completely out of the field of politics. This is not difficult here. We have had
                much practice. One of my most intimate friends is German, and he sympathizes with the German
                cause; he dines with me frequently, and although we avoid speaking of the War as much as
                possible, when we do, we do it quite naturally and without heat. <orgName key="americanPoetrySociety">The Poetry Society of America</orgName>,
                at whose meetings the poems are read aloud, have pro-Ally and pro-German poems follow each
                other, and the poems are discussed on their merits and not at all upon their political bearings. So
                you see how really neutral the country at large is. The war is also comparatively far from here,
                and it is really quite easy to avoid it. But the idea of <del rend="strikethrough">writing</del>
                <add place="above">running</add> any political propaganda in a literary and artistic paper is one 
                I should not consent to for a moment.</p>
            <p>Another objection is that you could not possibly put on your passport that you were
                coming over here to edit such a paper. I do not think you would be allowed to land. I do not think
                that the Government would allow such an obviously partisan movement. In the second place,
                there is a law in this country, called the Contract Labour Law or some such name, by which
                people are not allowed to be engaged for a job before they leave their country. It is of course
                aimed at day labourers and factory hands, but I think I am right in saying that it holds good for
                everybody. The way it is got round is that people do not announce their engagements upon
                stepping ashore. But if you had it in your passort, I think that it would dish you completely.
                Also the idea of having anything so grave attached to so simple a little sheet as ours, would
                <del rend="strikethrough">be would</del> cause a burst of amusement from all the newspapers in the country, and we should be
                black-eyed before we started.</p>
            <p>I have now answered your remarks at length, and I am afraid I have given you the
                impression that it is very little use for us to try to run a paper, even if we had the money. As a
                matter of fact, we have not the money, and I do not believe we can get it, so it is really
                unnecessary to discuss these minor details until we have. I only put them in, in order that you
                might realize exactly what the situation was, and what it would be, before you took a jump in the
                dark. It would be the greatest pleasure to have you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> here, and I think we should have a
                heavenly time with all of us in <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> together, but the rebuffs I have received at the suggestion
                that anybody should give any money for such a paper, have considerably dampened my ardour.
                People are always very anxious to pat you on the back and tell you how sympathetic they are
                until you suggest touching their pocket-books, and then it is extraordinary what a number of
                reasons they have against their being subscribers. I am afraid we shall all just have to put it out
                of our minds for the moment, which is quite as much of a disappointment to Fletcher and me as it
                is to you. I am awfully sorry if what either Fletcher or I said led you to think the scheme was
                more than a vague outline based entirely upon hope. If I am ever able to raise the money, at some
                future date, I trust that the scheme as I have outlined it more fully will appeal to you, because I
                think the thing should be put down in legal black and white <add place="above">before we start</add>, so there should be no
                misunderstandings at any rate. I did not go into all these details before, as the whole thing
                seemed so up in the air; but since you have raised the questions, I thought I had better answer
                them at length. I am just as sorry as I can be that people are so close-fisted. But what can we do?</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>