<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-01-19"
                    >Jan. 19, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$168i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of 5 sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of the first four
                        and on one side of the fifth. Each new sheet (every other page) has “R.A.” and a page number in
                        the upper left corner and the date in the upper right corner. The paper appears to have a very faint
                        watermark, though it is not legible. In several places there are words crossed out and new words
                        written above them in pen.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-01-19">Jan. 19, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I got your letter of January 5th this morning, about <title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">your book</title>,<anchor xml:id="n1"/> and immediately got hold
                of <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>. He is considerably hurt at your attitude, and I must say I think you go a little far in
                forbidding him to publish the book. The book will be out in a few days. I have corrected the final
                proofs. Brown is not crooked, I do not care what they tell you there. He is unbusinesslike, and
                procrastinating, and very poor. The only reason they can pay at all on the “<title key="poetryJournal" level="j">Poetry Journal</title>” is
                because <persName key="blanche_wagstaff">Mrs. Blanch Schumaker Wagstaff</persName> [sic] gives them a little sum of money each month to pay
                contributors. They paid me three dollars for a poem I sent them, and I enclose a draft for five
                dollars, which they are paying you. I have also persuaded Brown to accept <persName key="fs_flint">Flint’s</persName> 
                “<title key="chalfontSaintGiles" level="a">Chalfont Saint Giles</title>,” also for three dollars, and he has agreed to pay the money in to me before the end of
                the month. They never pay until the poems are printed. He says he sent you five copies of the
                “Poetry Journal” which contained your poems, and I have no doubt he did, and you must put
                down not receiving them to the mails. I will see if I have a copy and send it to you at once; but he
                has also promised to send out to the Press and get some copies and send them to you.</p>
            <p>His little series has some quite good people in it, and I think you will do as well to leave
                your book with him as anywhere else. If you take it away from him now, you should reimburse
                him for setting it up and for the various corrections on the proof. He had corrected one set before
                I saw it, and I have corrected two since. All of this means that he has to pay the printer.
                He does not demand this; on the contrary, I think he is quixotically fair, and as you will see by his letter to
                you, he is willing to give you back the book and himself pay for all the trouble and expense he
                has been in in regard to it – at least, so I understand his last paragraph, but I should not think that
                you would want to put him to any such expense. He is undoubtedly procrastinating, and I think it
                is even difficult for him to find the next dollar, but he is enthusiastic about your work, and will
                push it as far as his means allow.</p>
            <p>I enclose the proof-sheets of his catalogue, containing an announcement of your book, and I sent him
                <del rend="strikethrough">in</del> <persName key="teignmouth_shore">Teignmouth Shore’s</persName> quotation about you from 
                “<title key="colour" level="j">Colour</title>” to fill in the part of a page which on this proof is blank.</p>
            <p>I have not peremptorily forbidden the publication of the book, as you have asked me to do, as
                I felt sure that when you received this cheque from him and got his letter, you would not
                want it suppressed. I do not want to hurt your feelings, but I do not think there will be any great
                sale for the book here, no matter who publishes it. It is not very easy to get our things sold in
                quantity, for the three hundred copies, which seems to make such an impression on you, would
                be a very small amount for America, and you must not forget that the price is exceedingly cheap.
                Booksellers over here do not care to handle such cheap books, as their percentages are not
                enough to make them worth while. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> was doubtful when he got up the 
                <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">New Poetry Series</title> whether he could get them handled at seventy-five cents, retail price. Before I suggested
                your book to Brown, I had offered it to <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>, <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName>, 
                <orgName key="mitchell_kennerley">Mitchell Kennerly</orgName>, and <orgName key="a_and_c_boni">Boni</orgName>,
                and they all refused it. Brown alone was willing to take the risk, and although in most of
                this series Brown has been helped out by the author’s paying part of the publication price, in
                your case he is taking the risk himself. There is no doubt whatever that he is treating you fairly,
                even if he has not answered your letters. He has accepted your contract as amended by you, and
                that was fair. I do not think you have any cause to complain of his treatment, although I admit
                that he is late in getting out the book; but most of the rest of his series is already published, and
                yours will be by week after next at the farthest, possibly next week.</p>
            <p>If I have done wrong in this, I hope you will excuse me. Perhaps I should have followed
                your letter absolutely and taken the book away from him. I did not do so because I did not think
                it was to your interest. I am sure there will be no difficulty whatever in collecting what is due to
                you. I am right on the spot, and I have told Brown that I shall be after him to pay you what he
                owes you, when he owes it to you, and my position here is such that no one would dare cheat,
                because they know I could easily go for a lawyer and call for an accounting. At the same time I 
                am not particularly crazy to handle the job, if you do not like the way I am handling it; and if you
                prefer to take the matter entirely into your own hands and deal with Brown directly, taking your
                book away or leaving it with him as you think fit, I am perfectly willing, and shall not be in the
                least offended. The position of go-between is always unpleasant, but I am not usually considered
                a bad business woman, and I have done everything I can for your interests, and you may be sure
                I always shall. You told me to make what contract I saw fit with Brown, and you would abide by
                my ruling, and apparently now you wish to take matters into your own hands. I must tell you
                frankly that, if you take this book away from Brown now, I think you will be treating him
                unfairly, and I think your suspicions are unfounded. I know him, and the father of the girl to
                whom he is engaged is an intimate friend of my brother <persName key="percival_lowell">Percy’s</persName>. He is an astronomer, and they
                are good people, and you are in no sense in the hands of a charlatan in dealing with him,
                although of course you cannot expect the same businesslike methods and satisfactory procedure
                that you would with a larger firm. At the same time Brown accepted your book, it was a question
                of having him publish it, or not having it published, and it seemed to me it was better to have him
                publish it than nobody.</p>
            <p>Now I have something to complain of in my turn, something much more serious than you
                have, for you and Flint together put me into a very awkward position. Sometime ago Flint sent
                me his very nice review of “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">Six French Poets</title>,” 
                telling me he had sent it to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>, but that if
                Harriet could not print it in her paper, would I send it to any American review that would take it,
                as he could not possibly get it into anything in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, 
                “<title key="poetryDrama" level="j">Poetry and Drama</title>” having shut down, and you taking care of it in 
                “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>.” Harriet had already given the book to <persName key="agnes_lee">Mrs. Otto Freer</persName>
                for review. It was being reviewed in “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic”</title> by <persName key="elizabeth_sergeant">Elizabeth Sergeant</persName>, and the only
                other paper with which I have any permanent connection is “<title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>.” I had that
                morning received a letter from <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName>, asking me to tell her of some one whom
                I thought would know enough to review it. I immediately sent her Flint’s review, with the request
                that she print it.</p>
            <p>Now, having sent the review to me, Flint should certainly not have printed it anywhere
                else until he heard from me, as no editor likes to print a thing which has already appeared
                somewhere else. In spite of this, and I suppose with the kindest intentions in the world, you
                printed it in the January “Egoist.” Now that is particularly awkward, as I had already taken some
                of the sentence of that review and incorporated them in a folder which Macmillan is getting out
                about my book, giving Flint’s name and saying that they appeared in “The Little Review.” The
                folder has not yet been issued, but is in type, and unfortunately you saw it fit to leave out these
                very sentences in the “Egoist” copy. In view of this, I have had to write and apologize to
                Margaret Anderson, and at the same time beg her to swallow her pride and put in the review as
                she received it, otherwise I must suppress those folders. You see that Brown is not the only
                unbusinesslike person in the world.</p>
            <p>Now here is another thing – I should like to know why you were so anxious to suppress
                the few extremely nice sentences which Flint put in his review. You did the same thing in
                <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> review of me last year. Now it is quite possible that Flint was willing to have these
                sentences taken out, but it was hardly courteous, after having sent me the review, to send in an
                expurgated copy in which all the sentences which were uncomplimentary were left in, and many
                that were <add place="above">complimentary</add>, were taken out. I understand your critical faculty and your desire
                always to <del rend="strikethrough">do</del> <add place="above">say</add> exactly what you think, and not something else; but when this theory is carried
                so far as to make it necessary for you to impose your opinions upon other people’s articles on my
                work, I resent it extremely. In fact, you have hurt me to the quick. I was annoyed the first time
                you did this, but I am far more annoyed now. I have done everything I can to get yours, and
                <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName>, and Flint’s work printed over here, and I have referred to it in almost every lecture I
                have given, and I have given a great many. It is owing to my pushing and advertising that the
                <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Imagist Anthology </title>has gone as well as it has. It is owing to the interest in the Imagist Anthology
                that your books sell so much better than you or <persName key="harold_monro">Monro</persName> expected. I have stinted myself in neither
                time nor energy to push the group along. That I have not succeeded in getting your poems more
                generally accepted in magazines is not my fault. I cannot force editors to take what they do not
                want, although I have forced Brown to take Flint’s “Chalfont Saint Giles” by telling him how
                highly I thought of the poem. You know how much I admire all your work; but of course there
                are things in it that I do not admire, but I do not go out of my way to tell them to people, and I
                certainly <del rend="strikethrough">will</del> <add place="above">would</add> not delete anything 
                complimentary to you, if I were running a magazine and anybody asked me to print anything of the sort.
                I have as high a moral sense in regard to criticism as you have, and it is for that reason that my 
                article on you was not wholly complimentary. But it is one thing to write one’s self, and another to use 
                the blue pencil upon complimentary remarks when they are said by somebody else.</p>
            <p>I understood that you were going to write a review of my book yourself for the February
                number, and I suppose that you ran Flint’s in in January out of the kindness of your heart; but it
                would have been kind and more tactful if you had left in the things which he said which were
                especially agreeable, and more businesslike if you had ascertained, or Flint had ascertained,
                whether or not I had disposed of the review to any paper here, before printing it.</p>
            <p>Now here is one thing which I must beg you to do, or rather not to do – please do not
                refer in “The Egoist” to <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> “<title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Anthology of Magazine Verse</title>.” I know very well what
                you think about it, and of course in many ways I agree with you, in some ways I do not. But
                Braithwaite has been a good friend to us, and whatever we may think of his taste, it is not our
                business to knock him. Without him we could not have got nearly as far as we have. He would
                not have put in Hilda’s poem, had I not pointed it out to him, and dinned, and dinned, and dinned
                at him to make him see the beauties of her work, which is far beyond him. The Anthology has a
                wide circulation, is bought by all the schools, and as the public as a rule is inferior in knowledge,
                even to Braithwaite, to be in it or out of it makes some difference to one’s standing as a poet. If
                you come out with a review saying disagreeable things about his book, he will be seriously hurt.
                He will think I have not played fair, and he will be down upon all of us from now on. There is no
                reason for you to review this book, it is an American publication and is not issued in England,
                and I shall be very grateful to you if you will not mention it at all in the columns of “The Egoist."
                You have seen what effect <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra’s</persName> jumping on the people who do not agree with him has. It has
                landed him nowhere. In trying to make people understand a new form of art, it is far better to
                persuade them than to hammer them; and you must have seen by the amount of space which we
                were accorded in the papers and magazines that my method is having an effect which Ezra’s
                never had. Remember another thing - I have given up a great deal of my time, which I have
                wanted for production, to pushing us as a group, and these lectures which I have been giving
                have taken an amount of time and energy which is incredible. I do not grudge it, and every
                lecture pushes us all, as I have been extremely careful to boost us all in them, but I should have
                done very little of this work on my own account, because it is no longer necessary. I am now
                preparing my second edition of my “Six French Poets,” which came out in November. The
                second edition is not called for yet, but the publishers tell me that there is no doubt that it will be
                very shortly, and they wish to prepare for the second edition now. It is a <measure type="currency" num="2.50">$2.50 </measure> book, and you can
                see what that means.</p>
            <p>Now it is the greatest satisfaction to me to feel that we are really getting ahead, as I know
                we are. But I do want you to leave Braithwaite alone, and I do want you to feel that I have not
                been neglectful of your interests in regard to Brown. There will be no difficulty whatever in
                getting the copyright away from him, if at any time any other publisher wants it; or if you wish to
                re-acquire this, the expense will not be great. But with all my loyalty to you, I do not wish to get
                in wrong here with the various people who are inclined to be our friends, and you must allow my
                judgment in the matter of silence about Braithwaite’s book, at least, to stand. You will do as you
                please about Brown, but I sincerely think that you had better leave the matter as it stands now.</p>
            <p>As the book is coming out so late, your first payment will be in August. If your payment
                is not forthcoming, or if there seems any reasonable doubt as to the payment’s being fair, I will
                insist upon seeing his books, if you wish me to do so. You have worked with me long enough
                now to know my honesty and fairness, and I think you can trust to it in all matters for the future,
                and whatever does not go right, you may be sure I will make right as far as it is in any one’s
                power to do so.</p>
            <p>I wrote to Flint yesterday, and told him it was impossible that we should print “<title key="evil" level="a">Evil</title>.”
                Ferris Greenslet thinks it most inadvisable that it should appear in our volume, and my opinion
                about it has not materially changed since he expurgated it. The poem is unpleasant in the
                extreme, my chief reason against it being that it is very reminiscent of certain things in “<title key="others" level="j">Others</title>,”
                and that, although of course I understand from what a different point of view Flint wrote it, the
                public is not so discerning. We will accept “<title key="whitechapel" level="a">Whitechapel</title>,” as I wrote you, but under no
                circumstances will I agree to “Evil;” and even if you think it is a prejudice, I trust you will bow
                to it, as I have to your decision in regard to “<title key="turnpike" level="a">Off the Turnpike</title>."</p>
            <p>I wish we could meet. All these things would be straightened out in five minutes if we
                did, but even with a few differences of opinion and little advices going back and forth, you must
                never suppose for a moment that anything I could do, or say, or think, means anything but
                extreme interest in us as a group. And as to friendship – what is the use of talking about a thing
                which is as self-evident to me as the air I breathe?</p>
            <p>I dined with my brother <persName key="lawrence_lowell">Lawrence</persName> last night, and my sister, <persName key="katherine_bowlker">Mrs. Bowlker</persName>, was there. Her son-in-law
                is in Flanders fighting, and she has just come back from England, where she has been,
                taking her grandchildren over to bid their father good-bye before he went to the front. It would
                have done your heart good to hear the pro-Ally, fire-eating talk that went on there. The little
                group of people, of whom I am one, and which consists of all the best educated and cultivated
                people in our part of the country – I might almost say in America  – are so strongly in favour of
                the Allies that one would think we are still a colony. I think my whole family would walk to the
                front with guns on their shoulders, if they could. So, you see, my remarks in my last letter were
                not personal, and I hope you understand that they merely referred to the public attitude necessary
                in dealing with people of different opinion.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately,</closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>I am returning <persName key="edward_storer">Storer’s</persName> book, which I have just got back from Brown. He does not
                    want to publish it, and I thought it safer to get it and send it myself, rather than trust to his
                    remembering to send it.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington ultimately publishes his book, Images, Old and New (1916), with Edmund R. Brown's press, Four Seas.; ¶7 F.S. Flint's review of Six French Poets appeared in The Egoist, Vol. 3, No. 1 (January, 1916), pp. 9-10, as well as in The Little Review, Vol. 2, No. 10 (January-February, 1916), pp. 16-17.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>