<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document
will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
    <!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                        key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date
                        when="1920-09-25"
                    >September 25, 1920</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="drr">Danielle Nasenbeny
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">
                            https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$323i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter consists of three typed pages on carbon paper. The upper lefthand corner of the first page consists of an address heading. The righthand consists of a dateline. Above the dateline after the first page is a heading (Mr. Aldington - [Page #]). There are some tears on the right edges of the third page, and folds on the upper right corners of the first and second pages.
                    </p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement>LOCATION OF LETTER WRITING</settlement>
                    <date>DATE OF LETTER WRITING</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><date when="1920-09-25">September 25, 1920</date></dateline>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
                    <p>I have not had any luck with your things, except the one I sold to <persName key="elizabeth_cutting">Miss Cutting</persName>
                    and which I am dreadfully afraid you had already sold to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Miss Monroe</persName>. You sent
                    it to me before this second batch in which you had a list of the people to whom
                    you had sold things. I have warned Miss Cutting, as the “<title key="northAmericanReview" level="j">North American</title>” will
                    publish nothing which has appeared before. In sending me things to place, it is
                    usually quite useless to send me anything which has appeared anywhere, even in
                    <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, but nothing which has appeared in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>, and none of the better
                    established magazines will take anything which has been printed anywhere.</p>
                    <p><persName key="stewart_mitchell">Stewart Mitchell</persName> wrote and asked me to send him all your poems which I had, but
                    I am sorry to say that he has returned them all to me, and also your “<title key="influenceJamesJoyce" level="a">Influence
                    of Mr. James Joyce</title>.” I may be able to place the poems, I am not sure. The best
                    ones you have already sold. There is not the slightest use of my thinking I can
                    place this article on <persName key="james_joyce">Joyce</persName> anywhere. Nobody reads Joyce here. The article could
                    only hurt you, for most of the people who know anything about him thoroughly
                    detest him, I am therefore returning this manuscript to you. In many ways
                    America is less open minded than England. He may have some influence in England
                    - you seem to think so in your paper - but I hardly think he could have any
                    here. What he is doing is harm, for where other writers speak plainly and
                    honestly with a high intent, as <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> does, Joyce is merely obscene, and the
                    <orgName key="watchAndWard">Watch and Ward Society</orgName>, etc. are perfectly incapable of telling the difference
                    between obscenity and truth. The obvious disgustingness of Joyce's work would
                    simply bring the strong and true work of better men than he into strong
                    disrepute. Too bad, because yours is a good paper, but there is no place for the
                    subject over<pb n="02"/> here now. The more I know of our two countries the more I realize
                    that we are following entirely different literary orbits. There is simply no
                    audience for Joyce over here, except among certain of the intelligentsia. I am
                    awfully sorry, but there is no use in my trying to do anything with this paper,
                    I know. If you will send me another paper asggood (sic) as this, but about some
                    writer whom the public knows, I make no doubt I can place it most satisfactorily
                    anywhere.</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile my own news is none too good. <rs key="medical" type="theme">I am to be cut up again</rs> during the week
                    of <date when="1920-10-18">October 18th</date>. It is a pesky nuisance, but I have seen the biggest man in the
                    country on hernias, in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>, and he thinks that the other operations have
                    not been properly done and that there are nine cases out of ten in favour of
                    recovery. I have also got the chief surgeon in <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> on the job, and the two of
                    them are going to perform the next operation, and I have some hopes of success.
                    Unless it is successful, I see my life growing narrower and narrower as I become
                    more unable to do things, so we will hope for the best, for, except for this
                    bothersome thing, I have never been better in my life and am eager for work and
                    in full train, which makes things particularly annoying.</p>
                    <p>I will send you some poems before long, but the truth of the matter is that I am
                    so constantly sold up here that I do not get round to keeping things to send to
                    England, which seems remote as I have no real public there yet. I have already
                    lost three months this year, and this operation means another three months. Six
                    months out of a year greatly diminishes my output.</p>
                    <p>At the moment, I am working on another volume of poems to appear in the Spring,
                    as I have changed my publisher, <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> not having lived up to his contracts,
                    and <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> having made me a very good offer to return to them, which I
                    have accepted; and of course they want a new book to<pb n="03"/> make an advertising
                    campaign on in the Spring. Just now I am working very hard to live up to my
                    already incurred obligations before the 18th of October.</p>
                    <p>Write me often, as I shall certainly need letters to keep me up during the long
                    weeks when I must lie flat on my back. <persName key="harold_monro">Monro</persName> has asked me to send him some
                    things for the “<title key="chapbook" level="j">Chapbook</title>,” but again I have not got round to it.</p>
                    <p>No more for the present, as I am in a great hurry trying to finish things up.</p>
                    <closer>Always affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>