<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-06-23"
                    >June 23, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$117i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of six sheets of paper with typing on both sides. At the top of each sheet
                        (every other page) is a page number. There are some places where edits have been added in
                        pencil.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-06-23">June 23, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Your letter came yesterday and was a perfect delight to get. It makes me very happy to
                feel the staunch friendship which you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> have for me; and you must realize by this time
                how absolutely it is returned. I almost wept at the idea of your doing a portrait of me for the July
                number. I shall appreciate it very much. I am awfully glad that you have taken Hilda down to the
                country. Don’t let her do too much. So many women go to pieces because they get up too soon. I
                wish to Goodness I could see you. A year ago to-day I sailed, and now that the time comes
                around, I cannot bear to think that I am going to lose my summer with you. I am only hoping this
                terrible war will be over, and I can surely go another year; and I am still hoping that you
                and Hilda will take a trip over to America and see things with your own eyes.</p>
            <p>You do not answer a thing about whether there is any possibility of your coming and
                trying the translating job. <persName key="carl_engel">Mr. Engel</persName>, who is the one that suggested it and who is in the 
                <orgName key="bostonMusicCompany">Boston Music Company</orgName>, asked me the other day whether I had heard anything definite from you. I think,
                if you chose to come and take it, you could hold it as long as you pleased and make a good
                income out of it. But, then, as you may, you are making a little hold in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> with 
                “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>,” and I do not know what to advise. Only tell me something to reply to them.</p>
            <p>I have the best news to give you with regard to the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>. It seems to be attracting a
                lot of notice. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> told me to-day that “<title key="townAndCountry" level="j">Town and Country</title>,” in a review of another
                book, had said that three important things had happened this year: the European war, 
                “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>,” and Imagist Poetry. And he says the sale is going on steadily at the rate of about five
                copies a day. That is very good for this kind of a book, I think, and I am delighted to think that 
                in clinging to me so splendidly as you have done, you have not lost in the selling line anyway.</p>
            <p><persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> has written Greenslet a letter, complaining that we did not mention “<title key="poetry" level="j">Poetry</title>” in
                our preface,<anchor xml:id="n1"/> and I have sent her the enclosed letter in answer. I do believe we shall have to
                mention “Poetry” in the preface of the next number.</p>
            <p>And by the way, we ought to be getting that next number together, or rather thinking
                about it. We ought to have the thing all made up by December or January. I advised waiting as
                long as possible before collecting our things, so that we can all have more to choose from, and I
                think the best way would be for you to gather in the English things and send them to me, and I
                will gather <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> and mine and send them to you; and then if you object to any of mine, or I
                object to any of yours, we can try again on the disputed poems. Of course, all that will take some
                little time so I think it would be well for us to begin, and try to get our first batches over to each
                other by the first of December. Of course, if you decide to come over here, it will be much easier
                for us, and we can do it all by word of mouth as we did last year.</p>
            <p>I am not at all surprised at what you tell me about <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>.<anchor xml:id="n2"/> He has disliked me from the
                first. I believe him to be a perfectly unreliable person and, of course, I knew his feeling toward
                me when he did not review me for the “<title key="outlook" level="j">Outlook</title>.” In fact, I have really always known it. It won’t
                make any difference; we have got beyond needing his help. But the way you stuck to our
                agreement through thick and thin is magnificent, and I am awfully grateful to you.</p>
            <p>I wish <persName key="michael_sadleir">Sadler</persName> would send me a copy of his novel.<anchor xml:id="n3"/> Greenslet says it is no good, and
                that they refused to publish it over here; but, of course, this is in confidence.</p>
            <p>It is fine about the <title key="british_weekly">British Weekly</title>, and good about Kournos. There is a little poetry
                magazine here called “<title key="poetryJournal" level="j">The Poetry Journal</title>.” It has been very poor, but they have just got
                themselves re-endowed and have started again. What makes me doubt about it is that 
                <persName key="blanche_wagstaff">Miss Blanch Shumaker Wagestaffs</persName> [sic] (you remember you had a book of hers to review last year) is one
                of the editors and the chief backer, I believe. But they have asked Fletcher and me to send them
                some things, and we have each done it; and if you care to send them any, I think they would be
                delighted to receive them. The address is: <placeName key="studioBookshop">Studio Book Shop</placeName>, 68 Pemberton Sq., <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>. Or you
                can do it through me, if you had rather. <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>, who has the Studio Book Shop and is the man
                who wrote <persName key="harriet_weaver">Miss Weaver</persName> subscribing for several copies of “The Egoist” to carry in stock, is
                interested in “The Poetry Journal.” He is also making a collection of autograph copies of the
                books of all the poets he can get hold of, and he has written to ask me for your address and that
                of various other people, and I have given it to him.</p>
            <p>As for the <title key="academy" level="j">Academy</title>,<anchor xml:id="n4"/> thank you for taking such a lot of trouble to find out if it was any
                good. I do not believe in taking hold of a broken-down magazine and trying to bring it up,
                anyway. A new thing, even a little thing, would be better than that. If you were over here, and
                could be the editor, it might be worth while to see what money we could raise to get up a small
                paper, but I made a lot of inquiries here, and everybody tells me that, unless you include politics
                and sociology, there is no chance of any paper living. I thought that <persName key="may_sinclair">May Sinclair’s</persName> article was
                excellent, and I shall certainly send round those copies as soon as I get them. They have not
                come yet.</p>
            <p>I telephoned in to Ferris as soon as I got your letter about the <persName key="henri_deRegnier">de Régnier</persName> stories. He tells
                me he has written you direct, so I won’t mix up with that.</p>
            <p>I think your idea of printing poetry of the younger Frenchmen is most excellent. Harriet
                ought to want some, but you know what she is like. If you want to send me some and have me
                send them on to her, I will; but I should think you could communicate with her as well as I. I
                certainly have no more pull with her than you have.</p>
            <p>There is not the slightest doubt that we are getting on and getting on excellently. The
                head of the English Department asked me to come out to <placeName key="wellesley_college">Wellesley</placeName>,<anchor xml:id="n5"/> one of our largest women’s
                colleges, and give them a talk on “The New Manner in Modern Poetry.” I tried to be very
                eclectic and took all the poets who were any good, and brought Imagism in at the end. I read a
                couple of poems each of yours and Hilda’s, and they were immensely li`ked. I hear the very
                nicest accounts from Yale. Apparently some members of the English department are interested. I
                have a poem in the “<title key="yaleReview" level="j">Yale Review</title>” this month. It is a quarterly, and is supposed to be the best
                magazine in the country. And they have written and asked me to send another, and <persName key="sophie_hart">Miss Hart</persName> has
                asked me to give another talk at Wellesley next year. Also I am to talk before the <orgName key="nyPoetrySociety">New York Poetry Society</orgName> 
                upon Imagism and <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="fr">vers libre</foreign></hi> in November. They are getting up a little <orgName key="poetsClub">poetry club</orgName>
                here, consisting of nothing but poets, to meet once a month, and chat and rub up against each
                other. Several people came and asked me to be president, so as to jolt it out of the academic hole
                in which these things usually flounder. I hate that kind of thing, but it seemed to me that it might
                be a means of inoculating people, so I took the job.<anchor xml:id="n6"/> Fletcher is a member because, although he
                has gone out to his family now, he expects to be back next Autumn. So you see, things are really
                walking along.</p>
            <p>My book on “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">Six French Poets</title>,” being my lectures done over, is being brought out by
                <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> this Autumn. They are doing it very nicely, with portraits of each author and
                complete bibliographies. The only trouble is that they insist upon my translating all the poems I
                quote in an appendix. Of course, I am making prose translations; but as there are about 150 of
                them, it is a chore. Still, I think about the book ought to do us all good, because it will show that
                we are serious and sensible people, and not mere freaks. I am going to mention <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> and his
                admirable work for French poetry in the preface, he was so kind to me last year in helping me to
                books, etc. His letter was a little patronizing, but I forgive him.</p>
            <p>I am sending you <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> answer to <persName key="conrad_aiken">Conrad Aiken’s</persName> 
                article in “The New Republic.” I do not think it is half bad. Braithwaite brings out an <title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Anthology</title> of magazine verse every
                Autumn. It has been pretty rotten up to date, but it has an immense circulation, and now
                that he has jumped heart and soul into our cause, he says he is going to make a feature of Imagist poetry
                and write a lot out it in his preface.</p>
            <p>Don’t worry a bit about our quarrelling. We have been through a lot and have stuck like
                glue, and if we continue to stand shoulder to shoulder, I believe we shall get ahead splendidly.</p>
            <closer>Ever so much love to you both,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Some Imagist Poets, 1915.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">Aldington's November 25, 1914 letter to Lowell described his own falling out with Ford Madox Hueffer and warned that "his sentiments for you are not quite as noble as he professes."</note> 
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb">Michael Sadleir's novel Hyssop: A Novel was published by Constable, 1915, and contrary to Ferris Greenslet's comment to Lowell, an American edition came out the following year through Brentano.</note> 
                <note target="#n4" resp="mb">The Academy and Literature, formerly The Academy (1869-1902) was a British cultural magazine. It changed hands and titles many times during its run, and had three editors in 1915 alone, before closing.The publication was kept alive as a dummy magazine so that it could maintain rights to the name and was eventually absorbed into Lord Alfred Douglas's magazine Plain English in 1920 (Douglas had been editor between 1907-1910.</note> 
                <note target="#n5" resp="mb">Sophie Chantal Hart (1868-1948) was an American educator. A professor of composition at Wellesley College, she served as Head of the English Department from 1906-1936.</note> 
                <note target="#n6" resp="mb">Lowell was the first president of the New England Poetry Club, which started in May, 1915.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
