<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-09-05"
                    >Sept. 5, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$226i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is five pages long. The word Aldington is written in pencil in the top left at a 
                        forty-five- degree angle slanting upwards from left to right. The date is in the top right of all pages and
                        the annotation “R.A.--[Page #]” is in the top left of all pages after the first.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-09-05">Sept. 5, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>This will be a very short letter, as I have not much to report. I enclose a money-order for
                the <measure type="currency" num="5">five dollars</measure> which was paid you by 
                “<title key="" level="dial">The Dial</title>” for the <persName key="henri_deRegnier">Henri de Régnier</persName> article. As I wrote to
                <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> the other day, I shall have to be a little 
                patient about collecting from “<title key="poetryReviewAmerica" level="j">The Poetry Review</title>”
                for your two poems that appeared in that, as they are always slow about paying, but I think I
                shall have it in a week or two, as they always do pay in the end.</p>
            <p><persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> writes me that she will take I and IV of your 
                “<title key="springMoods" level="a"></title>Spring Moods,” “<title key="beautyUnpraised" level="a">Beauty Unpraised</title>” and
                “<title key="ave" level="a">Ave</title>.” She tells me that she is writing this to you direct. She has not returned the
                other manuscripts to me, which makes me rather angry, as I was going to try “<title key="sevenArts" level="j">The Seven Arts</title>”
                with them. I am afraid she has sent them to you.</p>
            <p>I think we are looking up, as I have been rather lucky in placing these things of yours,
                and I sold a poem of <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> to “<title key="century" level="j">The Century</title>” the other day. 
                Of the things you sent me I have sold “<title key="imagesPoem" level="a">Images</title>” and 
                “<title key="inarticulateGrief" level="a">Inarticulate Grief</title>” as well as your “<title key="mallarme" level="a">Mallarme</title>” to “The Poetry Review.” I
                have sold your “Henri de Régnier” to “The Dial,” as you see. And I have sold these other two to
                “<title key="" level="j">Poetry</title>.” I do not believe that I can get rid of the <persName key="pierre_louys">Louys</persName> article anywhere, as on account of his
                erotic quality people over here do not want to read about him. I will make a stab at “The Seven
                Arts” with it, but I do not think there is much hope.</p>
            <p>They paid very little for the Henri de Régnier article, as you see. “The Dial” has just
                changed hands, as I wrote you the other day, and they are not paying very high rates; but it has a
                very large circulation, and this is the first time that any of our group has been represented in it in
                any way – they have been our bitterest enemies hitherto – and I thought it better to accept a small
                price for the sake of the publicity; and I trust you will think I did right.</p>
            <p>Things are going very well here. I am sending you a copy of a paper called “<title key="national" level="j">The National</title>,” 
                which contains an article about all of us, and especially about me, simply because I
                happen to be here; also a copy of “<title key="independent" level="j">The Independent</title>,” which featured me this week; and as I say,
                the fact that I have had so little difficulty in selling these things that you and Fletcher sent, makes
                me feel that we are all coming on very well. I think whatever you can send me that refers to the
                war, I shall have no difficulty in placing. If you happen to write a poem, or anything you have
                experienced while in camp, send it right along. I think I can put it somewhere with the greatest
                ease.</p>
            <p>I had a letter from Hilda the other day telling me of <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence’s</persName> distressed condition. It
                came too late for me to take her advice about augmenting the amount of his royalties. As a
                matter of fact, I should not have done that anyway, for I do not like deception, and it would have
                angered me to have it practiced up on me. But I will send him some money, with a note, which I
                trust will enable him to accept it without scruple. Tell Hilda I will write to her very soon.</p>
            <p>Where is your photograph in uniform? As I wrote you, I am sure I can get it into “<title key="bostonTranscript" level="">The Transcript</title>,” 
                and I wish you would send it along. Also ask Hilda to send me another one of her, as
                I do not want to do anything to injure this one I have, and I will have it put in a review of <title key="seaGarden" level="m">her book</title>, 
                which <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> are bringing out in the Autumn. I think I can get <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> to
                write a special article reviewing that book, and using the picture, without much difficulty. All
                these things help not only the person of whom they especially treat, but they help us all, and we
                want to keep the ball rolling – rolling right through the war and out the other side – so that we
                shall be in a splendid position to realize the new interest in things other than military, when the
                war is over.</p>
            <p>I think that, as you are all on the other side except me, now, you had better all arrange
                between you the things you think best for the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>, and then send them over to me. They
                ought to reach me not later than the first of December, if possible. Then I will use my prerogative
                of objecting or accepting, as we all do, if it seems to be necessary to have any separate opinion
                over these, which I doubt; but as there is only me over here to decide, it will be much easier for
                you to get together there, so that I do not have to ask the various factions of you whether you
                approve before putting them into the book. It takes such an everlasting time for mail to go back
                and forth across the ocean nowadays, that I would rather deal directly with Hilda, and let her do
                all the collecting of the material, and not have to write specifically to each individual member.
                The book has to go to press, as you know, in February.</p>
            <p>I am doubtful about putting a preface at all in this number. It seems to me to we have
                prefaced enough, and it would perhaps seem more dignified, and look as if we were more certain
                of our position in this last one of our Anthologies (for you remember our contract was only for
                three years), if we appear without any apology or explanation of any sort. I think the Anthology
                has done its work: we have made a good position for ourselves, we are taken seriously, and I
                think we have done that almost impossible thing – come very near to changing the whole taste
                for poetry, certainly in this country. There are a number of conservative poets still writing, and a
                few people who like them, but they have nothing like the vogue they had, and the interest is all
                turning our way, I think simply because we are so absolutely sincere and have believed so
                absolutely in the things we have tried to embody in our work; and to my mind it is one of the
                most hopeful things about the whole movement that the sincerity which is in us has sprung an
                answering echo in the interest which we have been accorded. I had the following instance in the
                mail the other day. Evidently someone had compared <persName key="carl_sandburg">Sandburg’s</persName> and <persName key="george_sterling">George Sterling’s</persName> poems,
                unfavourably to the former. Sandburg writes me as follows:</p>
            <!-- The two letters that follow are formatted as letters within a letter, I wasn't sure how best to format them? I stuck with just paragraph breaks for now. I went down a bit of a rabbit hole on the TEI site, but I couldn't find what I was looking for :/ -->
            <p>“Dear Miss Lowell:</p>
            <p>I am sending copies of this to my publishers, <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> and yourself so you may
                know our supposed enemy critics do not always have the backing of our supposed enemy poets.</p>
            <p>Carl Sandburg”</p>
            <p>The copy was as follows:</p>
            <address>
                <addrLine>“Bohemian Club, <placeName key="sanFrancisco">San Francisco</placeName></addrLine>
                <addrLine>July 31, 1916</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Mr. Carl Sandburg,</addrLine>
                <addrLine>C/O “Poetry,”</addrLine>
                <addrLine>534 Cass St.,</addrLine>
                <addrLine><placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, Ill.</addrLine>
            </address>
            <p>Dear Mr. Sandburg:</p>
            <p>I have just seen the unfortunate reference to our poems in “<title key="currentOpinion" level="j">Current Opinion</title>,” and lest
                you imagine that I like that sort of thing, I write to say how deeply I deplore it, and how sincerely
                I am the admirer of the splendid vitality and imagination of your work.</p>
            <p>In the light of the new movement in poetry, I feel something of a Rip Van Winkle, which
                feeling, I fear, detracts a good deal from the compliment when I assure you that I would gladly
                change places with you in the literary (if I may call it that) world. I am not your imitator merely
                because this old dog <hi rend="underline">can</hi> be taught new tricks, but somehow has no heart for them.</p>
            <p>Long life to you and the success that you deserve!</p>
            <p>George Sterling”</p>
            <p>Of course, Sandburg is not one of our group, but he is doing a species of poetry which is
                quite unlike the old-fashioned kind, and I for one am an admirer of his effort and often of his
                achievement, though not always. I think he is one of the best things we have over here, and that a
                man like Sterling, whose stuff is so fearfully old-fashioned and who has an enormous clientèle
                on the <placeName key="pacificCoast">Pacific Coast</placeName>, should write so generous a letter is, I think, an excellent sign.</p>
            <p>Never forget when you are sitting in the trenches or doing anything else in regard to your
                present job, that you have done an immense amount to change the whole attitude of poetry, and
                that nothing can ever take that away from you, no matter what you may be doing at the moment.</p>
            <p>Send me that photograph! And with lots of love, Dear Boy, to you and Hilda, from both
                <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and me,</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>