<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-05-23"
                    >May 23, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$210i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of three sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. In the upper
                        left of the first page, “Aldington” is written in pencil. In the upper right of every page there is a
                        date, and in the upper left of all pages except the first is the page number.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-05-23">May 23, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I have not recovered yet from your letter which came yesterday. I cannot bear to have
                you go to the war! But, of course, it must be, and I can only hope from the bottom of my heart
                that you, and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, and <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> all come back unscathed, and feeling that you have gained
                something by what is, after all, a great experience.</p>
            <p>How can they take Lawrence? I thought he was very ill with consumption. What will they
                do with him when they get him? I should not think he could last long in the trenches!
                <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> sent me out <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> 
                letter to him to read, and I must say I think she is awfully plucky.
                Perhaps she is right to stay in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. I am sure I would do the same if I were in her place. But,
                of course, I wish she were here.</p> 
            <p>Fletcher has probably told you that he is sailing for England very soon. I do not think he
                has decided how long he will be gone. But it leaves me terribly alone, and I feel very blue about
                it. And this, added to your letter, is a hard thing to stand up under.</p>
            <p>I am sorry he told you about my plan for your being English correspondent of
                <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> paper. I had spoken to Braithwaite about it long ago, and he told me that he wanted
                very much to have you and would write to you himself. I preferred to have him write to you
                himself, as then the thing would be official. If he has not already done so, it is presumably
                because he does not feel able to pay for the articles yet. My suggestion was that he take you on
                as English correspondent at a yearly salary, so much a month. I have spoken to him about it
                several times, and he has always professed his interest and said that he was going to write at
                once. I will speak to him again tonight and try and get something more definite. But I had such
                an experience in suggesting a tentative scheme when we thought of getting up a paper ourselves,
                that I was not going to say anything to you about it until it was decided, so as not to raise any
                hopes which I had no power to fulfill. As Fletcher has told you, however, I may say that I think I
                can work the arrangement in the end. I shall certainly try to, very hard. And I think Hilda’s
                suggestion for managing it while you are away is all right.</p>
            <p>You must not forget, dear Richard, that even in the trenches one is not dead. Plenty of
                books are being published from the trenches all the time. They have a kind of vicarious and
                romantic interest through being written by men on active duty. <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton &amp; Mifflin</orgName> have just
                published some awful things by a man named Frankau<anchor xml:id="n1"/> in their <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">Poetry Series</title>, called 
                “<title key="songsOfTheGuns" level="m">Songs of the Guns</title>”. Their interest lies purely in the fact that the man is in the artillery and writing about
                what he knows. It is bad Kiplingesque stuff, but I imagine it sells well in England. It is not doing
                anything here.</p>
            <p>I want you to feel that although the ocean separates us, nothing else ever does or can, and
                that Hilda can always turn to me for anything at any time. I wish I could come over and see you
                before you start for the front. It hurts me very much to feel that this cannot be. But I am not in
                Fletcher’s position. If I go abroad I am obliged to take other people with me, and I do not think it
                right to endanger other lives on the high seas at present unless absolutely necessary; and of
                course it is not.</p>
            <p>I suppose it will take you some months to be trained before you can leave England. So I
                am sure that the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> will reach you some time as I sent it two weeks ago. I do hope you
                will like it.</p>
            <p>If you want to send some poems to me, I have no doubt that I can get Braithwaite to take
                them.</p>
            <p>Do write to me often and keep me posted as to all that goes on with you, and how Flint
                and Lawrence are. If you go into an officer’s corps I do not suppose that you will see much of
                them; but I hope you will know something about them. I shall write to Hilda constantly about
                anything and everything, and try to make her feel a little bit as though I were dropping in. And if
                she ever decides to come to America, please let her consider that she can come directly to me
                while she is deciding what to do. I wish she would come from the bott
                om of my heart.</p>
            <p>Good luck, dear Richard. I cannot help feeling that the war is nearing its conclusion, and
                I only pray that it will be over before you get there. I shall write constantly, if you will give me
                an address. With a great deal of love,</p>
            <closer>Sincerely yours,</closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>Mr. Braithwaite has told me that I might write to you officially, as he is so busy, and ask
                    you if you will supply him with a monthly letter about poetical affairs in England, and, if
                    possible, in <placeName key="Paris">Paris</placeName>. This would be about <measure quantity="1200" unit="words">1200 words</measure>, for
                    which he is willing to pay <measure type="currency" num="5">$5.00</measure> a month.</p>
                <p>He wants it partly literary and partly commercial, by which I mean he wants to know
                    what books of poetry are being published, as well as what are being written, and of poetical
                    events of importance. This is to be written entirely without bias of school or point of view;
                    merely with a view to mentioning these things that are good enough to be mentioned, no matter
                    under what banner the author has enlisted himself. Mr. Braithwaite is trying to make his paper
                    quite eclectic–to run it, as he expresses it, as an open forum. Of course, you and I do not
                    approve of this, but I think that his paper is worth writing for, as it apparently has a certain sale.
                    They printed <measure quantity="4000" commodity="copies">4,000 copies</measure> of the first number, as I think I wrote you.</p>
                <p>Should you feel like undertaking this job, please write to him direct –
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Mr. William Stanley Braithwaite</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>27 Ellsworth Avenue</addrLine>
                        <addrLine><placeName key="cambridge">Cambridge, Mass</placeName>. U.S.A.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    I have told him that I would collect the money and send it to you, because I think if you
                    wait for him to pay, you may wait quite a long time, as he is very unbusinesslike; and Lebowich,
                    the other editor,<anchor xml:id="n2"/> is very much of a Jew. However, they paid me promptly for my poem last
                    month, and I really do not anticipate any trouble, for Braithwaite is a thoroughly good fellow.</p>
                <p>In Hilda’s letter to Fletcher, which he let me read, she says that in case you cannot do the
                    letter yourself she thinks that she can work it up for you; and I think she could. Only bear in
                    mind that they must have an all-around acquaintance with what is going on, and that your
                    communication will be more along the lines of a bulletin than an article, although they want you
                    to connect your news with remarks and criticisms – you know the style in which all foreign
                    correspondents do. He wants to give his readers a little of the feeling as if they were in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>
                    or Paris and he could keep up with things. He would write you himself, as I have just said, only
                    he has an immense amount of writing to do; and although he means to get round to it, sometimes
                    he gets fearfully delayed. This is really true, for the man is not only editor of the 
                    “<title key="poetryReviewAmerica" level="j">Poetry Review</title>”, but poetical editor of the “<title key="bostonTranscript" level="j">Transcript</title>”, editor and compiler of the 
                    “<title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Magazine Anthology</title>”; and the correspondence and people asking him questions about poetry is enormous,
                    and he cannot afford a secretary. So that I think you can take this authorization from me as being
                    as good as a letter from him, particularly as I am getting from him a signed acknowledgement of
                    it.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Frankau, Gilbert. A Song of the Guns (Houghton Mifflin, 1916)</note> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Joseph Lebowich</note>
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>