<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-06-28"
                    >June 28, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$215i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is four pages long. The word “Aldington” is written in pencil in the top left corner of
                        the first page, slanting up from left to right. The second page has “R.A.--2” in the top left and the
                        date in the top right.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-06-28">June 28, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Your letter of June 11th has come, and I am awfully glad to know that you like the
                <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>. I think it is good this year.</p>
            <p>It is an awful feeling to me to know that you are really in the army. Of course, I cannot
                bear to have your brains and beautiful imagination knocked here and there in the rough duties of
                a private soldier’s life. But after all, poetry must be real if it is anything. We who write it must be
                virile, and capable of translating it into life when necessary and taking the drudgery merely as we
                take the drudgery of our art. This sounds sententious, but how difficult it is to say the things one
                means without sounding sententious! But you will see what I mean, and after all, it is a splendid
                experience, which will enlarge not only your outlook on life but your suggestions for poetry.</p>
            <p>The new poems you sent I think are perfectly beautiful, particularly “<title key="springMoods" level="a">Spring Moods</title>,”
                “<title key="imagesPoem" level="a">Images</title>,” and the one to <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> work. 
                I instantly rang <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> up on the telephone and
                offered them to him, as <title key="poetryReviewAmerica" level="j">his magazine</title> already has a much larger circulation than <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet’s</persName>. They
                sold <measure quantity="2600" commodity="copies">2600 copies</measure> on the newsstands alone of their second number. His judgement as an editor is
                very bad, but through his genuine interest in the subject and his desire to help poets, he manages
                to get in some good things, by a fluke as it were. He was perfectly delighted with these poems of
                yours and asked me to send them over to him at once, and he will certainly take some of them, if
                not all. I do not think I shall let him take all; I think it would be better to let Harriet have some;
                but she is very difficult to manage these days, now that <persName key="ac_henderson">Alice Henderson</persName> has left. I am beginning
                to think that Alice Henderson was the balance-wheel of <title key="poetry" level="j">that magazine</title>, and that all the good
                things were owning to her influence. She got little or no credit, poor girl, but now that she has
                had to go to <placeName key="newMexico">New Mexico</placeName> with consumption and give up her work, I can see the difference in the
                way the magazine is run – more prejudice, more reactionaryism, more admiration of youthful
                immigrants with very little talent who have imposed upon Harriet, like Michaelson.<anchor xml:id="n1"/> Also, as we
                know, Harriet keeps poems so long, whereas Braithwaite publishes his very soon, so I hope you
                will think I did right to give Braithwaite his choice.</p>
            <p>The Anthology seems to be doing fairly well. <measure quantity="1000" commodity="copies">A thousand copies</measure> were printed of the first
                edition, of which 750 were bound. Of these 750, only 225 were still in the publisher’s hands
                about two weeks ago. I rang them up to-day over the telephone to get the latest news for you, but
                the partners were all out at a meeting, so this is my latest bulletin.</p>
            <p>I sent you some reviews a day or two ago. They are not any great shakes, as you see, but
                we have a slight one, and not at all a bad one, appearing in the July “<title key="poetryReview" level="j">Poetry Review</title>,”<!--I wasn't entirely sure if this was still Braithwaite's "Poetry Review of America" magazine or if this is Monro's "Poetry Review"--> 
                written by <persName key="william_phelps">Professor William Lyon Phelps</persName> of <placeName key="yale">Yale</placeName>. Professor Phelps is more sympathetic than profound in
                some ways; his great subject is Browning, but in erudite circles, he is considered a bit sketchy.
                He is immensely popular, however, and the lectures which he gave at the Lowell Institute for 
                <persName key="lawrence_lowell">my brother</persName> last Winter had to be repeated, they were so jammed. 
                Therefore, to have him review us is distinctly a good thing for us.</p>
            <p>I have just received a letter from <persName key="wc_williams">William Carlos Williams</persName>, asking me to send something
                for the August number of “<title key="others" level="j">Others</title>.” But as I wrote you in the Winter, <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> and I decided not
                to contribute to that periodical, so I was obliged to refuse; but I am sorry, for I like Williams.</p>
            <p>Imagism is fast ceasing to be a freak subject over here and is beginning to be treated with
                respect; people are fast getting inoculated, and I think a few years more we can feel that we have
                really succeeded. It amuses me very much when I think how <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> sneered that, without him, we
                should go under.</p>
            <p><persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName> promised to give me a new instalment on his debt to you today, but it has not yet
                appeared. I shall hold this letter over until to-morrow and see if I cannot collect it. Certainly to
                get money out of that man is like wringing wine from a stone.</p>
            <p>I had a couple of letters from Fletcher by the same mail which brought yours. He is at his
                old quarters in Sydenham (37 Crystal Palace Park Road). Perhaps by this time you will have seen
                him. Can he not come and see you at the camp, even if you are no longer a civilian? And,
                Richard, why don’t you apply for work as an interpreter? With your knowledge of French, and
                German, and Italian, you would be invaluable to them; and to waste that knowledge as a private
                is plain silly. Do see if you cannot do something about it, for I know that interpreters are wanted,
                as I hear so constantly.</p>
            <p>I have sent both our Anthologies to <persName key="alvan_sanborn">Mr. Sanborn</persName>, who does the American chronicle in the
                “<title key="mercureDeFrance" level="j">Mercure de France</title>,” you remember, and who asked to see them; and he says he shall mention
                them again in his Autumn “chronique.”</p>
            <p>Do not worry about <persName key="jean_untermeyer">Mrs. Untermeyer’s</persName> poem! I understand perfectly how it is. I dished
                myself with <persName key="harriet_weaver">Miss Weaver</persName> last year when I told her frankly what I thought of <persName key="dora_marsden">Miss Marsden’s</persName>
                articles, and you can hardly expect either of those ladies to look upon me with favour. I have no
                doubt at all that it is Ezra’s influence that has caused the coolness toward you; but I think it will
                not be long before you do not need “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>.” My very good friend Braithwaite stepped in
                and saved me by instantly accepting that poem for the “Poetry Review,” so that in writing to
                Jean Untermeyer I merely substitute one paper for the other; and she is, on the whole, the gainer, as
                the “Poetry Review” pays.</p>
            <p>Braithwaite has asked me to tell you that he hopes you will accept the position of foreign
                correspondent when you are mustered out; and I am sure that if you want to send him anything,
                either poetry or an article, at any time from the front, he will receive it gladly and will remit to
                Hilda. You can either send them to me, and I will send them on to him, or you can write to him
                direct; William Stanley Braithwaite, 27 Ellsworth Avenue, <placeName key="cambridge">Cambridge, Mass.</placeName></p>
            <p>I gave both our anthologies to a friend of mine the other day, a lady who has never read
                poetry in her life before to any extent, because she never cared for it and preferred to read novels.
                You will perceive by this that she is not a literary person and only read for the human interest.
                She has now abandoned novels completely and is absolutely drowned in poetry. She wrote me 
                to-day and said: “The Imagists have caught me.” To be sure, she is a little mixed, and considers
                all modern poets of any vitality Imagists – a sort of generic title in her mind for all that is good
                and vital in verse. She was so overcome and upset by your “<title key="childhood" level="a">Childhood</title>” that she said: “Is there
                nothing I can do for that man? I can’t bear to think of the loneliness of that childhood, and it
                makes me feel that I should like to meet him.” I said I thought what she could do would be to
                talk about you early and late; and possible sometime, if we are all in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, I will arrange a
                meeting between her and you and Hilda.</p>
            <p>I think Hilda’s things in the new Anthology are perfectly beautiful. I read them again and
                again and never tire of them, and I quite agree with you that “<title key="midday" level="a">Midday</title>” following the sea things is
                a magnificent contrast. I will try to write very often while you are gone both to you and to Hilda,
                whether I get any answers or not. Neither war nor trenches shall interfere with the great strong
                Imagist band which stretches between us. It has been a real brotherhood, hasn’t it? And we can
                all feel, I think, that it has given us something of the same quality towards each other that
                comrades in arms used to have in the old days.</p>
            <closer>Good luck to you, Dear Boy, and write when you can.</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Most likely Max Michelson (1880-1953), a Lithuanian immigrant who published poetry and reviews for Poetry.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>