<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-04-17"
                    >April 17, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$199i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of three sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of the first two
                        and one side of the last. At the top of each page except the first is a page number in the left
                        corner and the date on the right side underneath the margin. Every other page has “R.A.” typed
                        in the upper right corner. There is a watermark on the paper that reads “Berkshire Linen U.S.A.” There is also
                        a Certificate of Issue dated April 20, 1916 that comes from the State Street Trust Co. in
                        Boston, MA. It is issued for cheque number 1359 and says “on London for F 2-1-6”. The
                        amount is for ten dollars. The certificate appears to have an orange wave pattern on the paper
                        and has two perforated edges, the left and bottom sides. On the back side of this certificate is
                        a hand-written note reading, “To Richard Aldington, Esq. First $10 on acct. royalties from
                        E.R. Brown.”</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-04-17">April 17, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I received your nice long letter this morning, and very glad indeed I was to get it. It is
                ages since I had heard from you or <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>, and I began to think you had both died!</p>
            <p>I am having a hard time to get that money out of <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>, as you thought I should
                have. As I told you in my last letter, I finally had to resort to my lawyer, who in this case was
                my <persName key="william_putnam">brother-in-law</persName>. As he failed to produce anything, on my return from <placeName key="Chicago">Chicago</placeName> I took the
                matter again into my own hands, with the result that Brown expressed his willingness to pay
                as soon as he could, and sent me <measure type="currency" num="10">ten dollars</measure>, which I have turned into an English draft and
                am sending you enclosed. I shall get the other twenty out of him in time, I have no doubt; but
                it takes a little time, for the boy is not only unbusinesslike, but very poor.<anchor xml:id="n1"/></p>
            <p>It was awfully sweet of you to mind <persName key="johnMiddletonMurry">Middleton Murray’s</persName> article in the <title key="dailyNews" level="j">Daily News</title>
                and the <title key="times" level="j">Times</title>, against “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">Six French Poets</title>”. I had already gathered that they were the same
                man, from the similarity of the remarks and style. Some of the English criticisms have been
                good, like the “<title key="observer" level="j">Observer</title>” and the “<title key="newWitness" level="j">New Witness</title>”; others have been bad. But one and all
                have accorded me really a great deal of space, and the English consignment of <measure quantity="250" commodity="copies">250 copies</measure>
                was sold out almost immediately and another consignment sent for. The entire first edition
                has gone, the book has been out of print for a month, and we are rushing ahead a second edition as
                fast as possible. But the numerous printers’ errors in the first edition has made the
                revising of this second one extremely arduous, and I do not think it will be on the market yet
                for a couple of weeks, at any rate. I will send you one as soon as it comes out, because I
                would rather have you have a correct copy than the singularly incorrect one you have now.</p>
            <p><persName key="theodore_stanton">Theodore Stanton</persName>, who writes the American Rubric in the “<title key="mercureDeFrance" level="j">Mercure</title>”, has come to
                America on account of the war, and I spent an hour and a half with him the other day in 
                <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>. He is an amiable old gentleman, rather weak, and I believe he means to keep up with
                the movements of the day. I told him our sorrows in regard to <persName key="remy_gourmont">Remy de Gourmont</persName>, and how I
                feared it might affect the article in the “Mercure” which he had promised you to get in. I do
                not think Mr. Stanton has any authority to get things in or take things out, but he was very
                much interested, and asked me to send him copies of all three of the “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="s">Imagist Anthologies</title>”,
                as he wanted to put a notice about them in the “Mercure”. He is only allowed such a small
                space that he cannot say much in his notices except a mere statement – but I thought a
                statement was better than nothing.</p>
            <p>The new “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>” is coming along very well. They expect to have it out on the 29th
                of April. I have already corrected the proofs, and if they do not delay fearfully, it should
                be on the market by that time.</p>
            <p><persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> was in New York the other day when I was, and saw quite a little of
                <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Kreymborg</persName>. He feels exactly as I do about it – we think there is very little future for that
                crowd, and we are very glad that we withdrew ourselves from “<title key="othersAnthology" level="m">Others</title>.”</p>
            <p>I am through my lectures for this year, and am about to settle down and write steadily,
                as <title key="menWomenGhosts" level="m">my new book</title> is coming out next Autumn.</p>
            <p>You sound very cozy in your cottage, but I should think it might be a bit lonely. But
                then, I confess to being a city dweller myself – or a suburban dweller, as I am. I do not like
                the real country for any length of time.</p>
            <p>Fletcher has decided that <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> is far the best city in America to live in, and seems
                to have taken up his abode here very pleasantly. His new book will be out the same day as
                the “Anthology”.</p>
            <p>Why isn’t <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> publishing your “Solugob” translation? I thought he
                seemed inclined to take it when I spoke to him about it, but he said he was in correspondence
                with you, so I did nothing farther. Now somebody tells me that it is to be issued by <orgName key="knopf">Knopf</orgName>.
                How stupid <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton-Mifflin</orgName> is, and what a number of opportunities they let go! Greenslet
                has absolutely spoiled his <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">new poetry series</title> by putting in everything – whether good or 
                otherwise – for which the authors were willing to pay; with the result that the thing has no
                prestige as a series whatever.</p>
            <p>I have seen the manuscript of <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet’s</persName> “<title key="newPoetryAnthology" level="m">Anthology of New Poetry</title>”, and I think she is
                going to have a very good volume there. Though it is not in all respects what I would have
                chosen, still it is excellent.</p>
            <p>I get so homesick for you and Hilda sometimes that I really don’t know what to do. It
                seems a thousand years since I have been in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, and Fletcher and I have often said what
                we would not give to see you both. If it were not for Fletcher I should go crazy. He is the
                only person here with whose work I am in sympathy. With the others it is always making
                allowance in speech, trying to put oneself into their point of view for a moment. But Fletcher
                and I keep each other going. We have had some rather nice experiences lately; among others,
                one of the <placeName key="harvard">Harvard</placeName> boys has written a long thesis on “Imagism” as his candidate’s essay for
                the Bowdoin English Literature Prize – and that’s something. Fletcher has seen a copy of it,
                which <persName key="conrad_aiken">Aiken</persName> had, and says it was excellent. We do not know who the boy is, as these are
                submitted anonymously, but I am going to find out through my brother. He quoted a lot of
                my ideas, which I gave in my address to the boys out there this Winter, so I suppose he was
                in the audience. But it all proves we are getting ahead. Sometimes I get awfully discouraged,
                but I don’t suppose that is really necessary.</p>
            <p>Who is <persName key="georges_turpin">Georges Turpin</persName>? He says he is a paroxyate, and sent me a book of his the
                other day. It is valuable to me chiefly because I did not know that my name was known at all
                in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>; although Mr. Stanton’s little notice of the 
                “Six French Poets” perhaps helped a little.</p>
            <p>Please tell Hilda that rather an unfortunate thing has occurred because she sent
                Harriet a poem of hers – “<title key="shrine" level="a">The Shrine</title>” – to print, and Harriet was accepting it, but in her
                usual dilatory fashion, she had not accepted it when I was in Chicago, and I informed her,
                with much regret, that the poem was in the forthcoming “Anthology”. She says she never
                received it until March, so I suppose Hilda must have got mixed as to what she had sent to us
                and what she was sending Harriet. I was awfully sorry to rob Hilda of the chance of selling it
                to Harriet, but it was too late for Harriet to print it before the “Anthology” came out, and we
                were already in the press. I tried to make Harriet take “<title key="pearTree" level="a">The Pear Tree</title>”, which was the only
                one of Hilda’s poems which had not been published which I had the manuscript of; but she
                thought she would rather ask Hilda to send her something else along the lines of “The
                Shrine”. It is too bad it occurred this way!</p>
            <p>Let me know how you get on, and don’t leave me so long in silence – it will make me
                feel as though a planet had come along and chipped you off from the earth; don’t you
                remember Jules Verne’s story?</p>
            <closer>
                <p>Lots of love to you both.</p>
                <p>Affectionately,</p>
            </closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington ultimately publishes his book, Images, Old and New (1916), with Edmund R. Brown's press, Four Seas.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>