<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-08-12"
                    >Aug. 12, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$126i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of two sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of the first and one side
                        of the second. At the top of the second sheet (page 3) there is a page number in the center, the
                        letters “R.A.” on the top left, and the date on the top right.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-08-12">Aug. 12, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I feel very badly to think that I have not yet thanked you for your bully article in the July
                “<title key="egoist" level="j">Egoist</title>.”<anchor xml:id="n1"/> The reason has been owing to a chapter of misfortunes. 
                In the first place, <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName>
                was taken quite ill and threatened with typhoid fever, and went to bed, with two doctors and a
                nurse. It was three weeks before she was able to go out to <placeName key="saltLakeCity">Salt Lake City</placeName>, where she is going to
                spend the summer with her family. During that time, I was of course very anxious and very much
                occupied. I tried to be with her all day, and translate those French poems for the appendix of my
                book all night.<anchor xml:id="n2"/> The result is that Nemesis has pounced upon me in the shape of violent
                indigestion and I have been feeling perfectly rotten and utterly incapable of writing anything.</p>
            <p>I got up <placeName key="bromleyLacey">here</placeName>,<anchor xml:id="n3"/> where I have not been for three years, to find the roof leaking like a sieve,
                and the avenue almost impassible from the terrible rains we have been having this year. I am
                feeling a little better now, although I am only up to about half my usual working capacity. And
                the first thing I do, I am going to thank you awfully for that article. I think it excellent. My only
                criticism would be that I hate to have attention called to the affluent side of my existence, a side
                of which I take so little cognizance myself. I am particularly glad that you liked “<title key="bath" level="a">The Bath</title>,” and
                what you said about it was just the right thing. Personally, I think your critical articles are quite
                perfect. They never seem overloaded and they are always interesting.</p>
            <p>I have just finished one on you for the September “<title key="littleReview" level="j">Little Review</title>.”<anchor xml:id="n4"/> It is not as good as I
                wish it were. That is where my health came in; but it is the best I could do under the agitating
                circumstances in which I have been living.</p>
            <p>A <persName key="randolph_bourne">man</persName> dined with me last night,<anchor xml:id="n5"/> a poor, little hunchback, who is supposed to be very
                clever. He is one of the contributors to “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>.” He told me he particularly liked
                your “<title key="" level="a">Childhood</title>,” that it was the best thing you had done. But I shall let my criticism of it stand,
                because I do think that technically perhaps it is not quite as irreproachable as your other things. I
                hope you will like the article and will not mind the few little criticisms I have made. You see, I
                do not think an unmitigated puff ever goes down with the public, and it seemed better to say
                exactly what I thought than have it read like a puff. As this is your own method, I do not think
                you will mind my using it.</p>
            <p>I forwarded a letter from you yesterday to <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>. He wrote me a little while ago that he
                expected to go still farther West, but that his plans were still uncertain.</p>
            <p>This is a lovely place. I wish you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> were <placeName key="dublinNewHampshire">here</placeName>. For two summers I have been
                away, as you know, and its beauty strikes me all over newly. It looks like <placeName key="scotland">Scotland</placeName> with its lakes
                and mountains. In fact, I believe that geographically it and Scotland are first cousins.</p>
            <p>I keep sending you clippings from time to time. I trust you get them all right. I cannot tell
                you how I miss my summer with you people and how homesick I am to see you all. I think one
                reason for my collapse this Spring is that just about that time I am used to taking the sea voyage
                and having a lot of new and pleasant stimulation; and this year, I have just kept steadily to the
                grind-stone right along.</p>
            <p>By the way, <title key="" level="m">our book</title> is going very well. We have sold <measure quantity="575" unit="copies">575 copies</measure> since the first of April,
                and our royalties are magnificent, <measure type="currency" num="28.62">$28.62</measure>. I am enclosing a money-order which represents yours
                and Hilda’s share. I am also sending <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> theirs. Fletcher, of course, I am paying
                by cheque. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Mr. Greenslet</persName> tells me what we lead the <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">New Poetry Series</title> so far. I think the notice
                in the “<title key="londonTimes" level="j">London Times</title>” singularly disagreeable; but then, the “London Times” is always nasty to
                me, so I do not mind.</p>
            <p>Tell me how you like that <title key="patterns" level="a">poem</title> of mine in the August “Little Review.”<anchor xml:id="n6"/> Fletcher and I
                rather like it. No more for the present; I have to go back to my proof reading.</p>
            <p>By the way, I have spoken to <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName> about an exchange advertisement with you for the
                “<title key="poetryJournal" level="j">Poetry Journal</title>” and he is delighted with the idea. But there is not the faintest use for your
                applying to “The New Republic.” They are highly endowed and are not looking for bargains, and
                they are altogether too stodgy to make any such arrangement. It is very good of you to want an
                advance copy of my book. I will send you the proofs when I get a complete set, and you can read
                it at your leisure.</p>
            <closer>
                <p>With lots of love to you and Hilda,</p>
                <p>Affectionately yours,</p>
            </closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Richard Aldington, "The Poetry of Amy Lowell," The Egoist, July, 1915 (Vol. 2, No. 7), 109-110.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">Six French Poets</note> 
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb">Bromley Lacey, Lowell's country home in Dublin, NH.</note> 
                <note target="#n4" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "Richard Aldington's Poetry," The Little Review, September, 1915 (Vol. 2, No. 6), 11-16.</note> 
                <note target="#n5" resp="mb">Randolph Bourne</note> 
                <note target="#n6" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "Patterns," The Little Review, August, 1915 (Vol. 2, No. 5), 6-8.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
