<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1918-06-18"
                    >June 18, 1918</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$250i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is 4 pages long. On the first page, the Aldington’s address is in the top left corner:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Richard Aldington, ESQ.</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Care of Mrs. R. Aldington</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Bosigram, Pendeen,</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Cornwall, England</addrLine></address>
                        The date is in the top right of each page, and on pages 2-4 the page number is listed in the top
                        right with the annotation “Richard Aldington, Esq.–[Page #].”</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1918-06-18">June 18, 1918</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Your letter of May 14th came the day before yesterday and I was perfectly delighted to
                get it. I am glad you have a company, which shows what an excellent soldier you are, and you
                know I have a kind of belief that a poet should be able to do everything better than other people
                do it. If a poet is not above other men, he is not good as a poet, and you are not above other men
                unless you can do their work better than they can do it if you try.</p>
            <p>And here is the point I want to get at. You say you feel out of touch with us here, with me
                perhaps also, I suppose, but you need not. Of course I am facing no such ordeal as you are, but,
                on the other hand, I am not a young man in vigorous health, and the Lord seems to temper the
                wind to the shorn lamb. But what I do want you to understand is that I have never approved of
                the “ivory tower” attitude. I believe firmly in living, in acting, and in being just plain brutal
                rushing life; and I do not believe the best poetry comes out of anything else. Also it seems to me
                that a civilization which is at the mercy of accidents is a jerry-built thing. It seems to me that if
                your poetry is sincere, if, in other words, you are the kind of person that writes poetry, you must
                do it straight through life although you are living in a hole in the ground, as you express it, which
                may be most distasteful and may not add anything to the “fine fibre of your soul.” Nevertheless,
                it could hardly affect the fundamental quality of that soul, which I feel surely must be so innate
                as not to be affected by any exterior circumstances. In other words, one should be able to go to
                the block the way martyrs of the Middle Ages did – without retracting. In such a case as you
                mention it would not be an exterior retraction but an absolute organic change of front, and I
                cannot believe that is possible to you or to anyone like you. In other words, your belief that you
                are not living a civilized life does not hold water to me. Your civilization must be above that, and
                you must go through it as you would an illness, and go through it with colours flying because
                you are a poet, and if a poet cannot be gallant, he is a decadent and has no reason to exist. There
                is a sermon for you, and all born out of my love for you.</p>
            <p>How I wish that I could see you and talk the whole thing over. You would find me far
                less removed from your present life than many of your friends, I think. There is no porcelain
                figure about me, and, although I am prevented from sitting in the trenches with you, sometimes it
                seems to me as though I should like to be able to sit there, for I cannot help being tormented (I
                suppose we all are) with the fact that I might do more. I should like to go abroad the way so
                many of my friends are doing, and do something on the spot, but, situated as I am with such
                rotten health, I know that that is merely succumbing to mob instinct and refusing to undertake
                the task that is mine. What good would it do the Allies to have me cross the water and succumb
                into a hospital upon my arrival? And as so many of the poets have gone, and as civilization must
                be kept up just for the very reason that the rest of you are living in holes in the ground and are in
                danger of getting discouraged, I feel it my business to keep the finer sides of life going, for that
                is the business of all of us women poets. Beyond everything is the ideal of art – that we agree,
                both you and I. And perhaps secondarily is the ideal of betterment of the world. But when one is
                whole-souled and believes in the civilization of one’s own race, and believes in the necessity of
                forcing it to dominate, then the two ideals merge, and in following the former one inevitably
                pursues the latter. Anyway, when I get restless and nervous that is how <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> speaks to
                me, and I have found Mrs. Russell the best guide that I have ever met.</p>
            <p>I am sending you a poem<anchor xml:id="n1"/> which I am afraid that you will not like. It will probably
                conflict with your notions of art. You may consider it propaganda, which it was not. It just came
                out because I could not help it – a hateful amateurish sentence, but what can you do when it is
                true. This is one of a series of “<title key="phantasmsOfWar" level="m">Phantasms of War</title>” that I have been writing from time to time
                when current events sounded so loudly in my brain that I could not escape them. It has been
                liked here, and you may like it or not. At any rate it is not any “ivory tower” thing. Although I
                still often write things that are merely beautiful, I cannot sit in the midst of all this pain without
                having it affect my work. I realize perfectly that I have developed differently from what I should
                have done had not the war come. I cannot think that the development has been a mistake.</p>
            <p>My next book I feel sure you will not like, which is most unfortunate because I owe its
                title to you. It consists of four historic poems in “polyphonic prose” which I know you hate. I
                will send it to you when it comes out. Its title is “<title key="canGrandesCastle" level="m">Can Grande’s Castle</title>,” and I have, dear Richard,
                quite without permission taken your poem, “<title key="atTheBM" level="a">In the British Museum</title>,” for my motto, and have
                quoted the poem on the motto page, deleting the lines from Samain which do not fit my content,
                and substituted dots in their place; otherwise the poem is entire. Of course I should have asked
                your permission before doing this, but there was not time, and I so needed the poem, and it is so
                beautiful that I just took it as I should a poem by any dead author. Will you forgive me, and if
                you do not like the book I have put it in, will you realize that I have paid you the compliment of
                admiration in public?</p>
            <p>Write to me as often as you can. I do not care how scrappy your notes are; I do not want
                to lose touch with you. You and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> are very precious to me, and as soon as the war is over I
                shall come back to <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, and we shall all have good times again.</p>
            <p>I will see that those dates are deleted in the copy as published. When it will be published,
                I do not know. <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName> has had a book of <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> for two years and has not published it yet. I
                intended to make him, if he took it, give a guarantee of publication before a certain date, but I
                understand you signed the contract without that guarantee, so I do not suppose we can hold him
                to anything. As to private publication, of course the copyright is not affected, but then the
                prestige is, and that is just where the trouble comes in. If you have any poems that you think
                would do in the place of the one the “<title key="northAmericanReview" level="j">North American</title>” took and could not publish on account of
                <persName key="charles_bubb">Bubb’s</persName> having published it before, send it to me, and I will see what I can do with it.</p>
            <closer><p>Mrs. Russell joins me in much love,</p>
                <p>Always affectionately,</p></closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "The Marching Hessians," The Independent, May 25, 1918, p. 324.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>