<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-07-27"
                    >July 27, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$219i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is five pages long. The word “Aldington” is written in pencil in the top left corner of
                        the first page, slanting up from left to right at a 45 degree angle. There’s a faint embossing at the
                        top of the paper that looks like “Berkshire Linen USA.” The date is listed on each page in the top
                        right, and at the top left of each page after the first page is the annotation “R.A.–Page [#].”</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-07-27">July 27, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Your letter of the 13th of June came a few days ago, and I was delighted to get it, and to
                know that you were really in camp. However awful it is to break up one’s life in this way, if it
                has to be done, I do think it is better to have it over, and not in anticipation.</p>
            <p>I have ordered “<title key="poetryReviewAmerica" level="j">The Poetry Review</title>” went to you via <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>. In it you will find a short and
                pleasant account of our <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> by <persName key="william_phelps">Professor Phelps</persName> 
                of <placeName key="yale">Yale</placeName>. I am also sending you the May
                and June-July numbers of “<title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>”. The latter contains an excellent criticism by 
                <persName key="mary_aldis">Mrs. Aldis</persName>,<anchor xml:id="n1"/> and both of them contain an interesting paper on you and Hilda and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>,<anchor xml:id="n2"/> 
                by <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>. In the latter also is a <title key="malmaison" level="a">poem of mine</title>,<anchor xml:id="n3"/> which I like and which I hope you will like too, 
                in spite of its being in polyphonic prose.</p>
            <p>Don’t worry, I shall write to you constantly and tell you everything that is going on here.
                You certainly shall not drop out from anything that I can keep you up in.</p>
            <p>I can certainly get your photograph into the “<title key="bostonTranscript" level="j">Transcript</title>”, if you will send it on, and they
                will let me put a few lines under it, I am sure, in which I can give you a send-off. I wish you
                would send two – one for my own pleasure and one for the paper.</p>
            <p>There is a new magazine being got up here. <persName key="james_oppenheim">James Oppenheim</persName> is the editor and 
                <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> and <persName key="robert_frost">Robert Frost</persName> are two of the 
                associate editors. It is to be called “<title key="sevenArts" level="j">The Seven Arts</title>”,
                and is endowed at <measure type="currency" num="25000">$25,000.00</measure> a year for one year. <persName key="annette_rankine">The donor</persName>, whose name I do not know, is to
                let them run it as they please for a year, and if at the end of the time he is not satisfied with the
                result, he can withdraw his support; in which case they will try to raise the money on their year’s
                work. If, however, he is satisfied, as they hope he will be, the endowment will continue. They
                wish to print things relating to all the arts, and they pay on acceptance. They have no propaganda
                whatever, and are to be the spokesmen of no school. It sounds well; and although I do not
                suppose they will follow entirely the lines which we should like, nevertheless it seems to me
                hopeful. And I hope that whatever you may send me I shall now be able to place more
                advantageously than hitherto – with “The Poetry Review” and this new magazine as places
                to put things into.</p>
            <p><persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> is considering your poems, and he will certainly take some of them, if not all.
                What he does not take I shall send to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>. Braithwaite does not pay as well as
                Harriet, as you know. In fact, he pays painfully little, as <persName key="blanche_wagstaff">his backer</persName> has only <measure type="currency" num="2000">$2,000.00</measure> a year to
                put into the magazine. But the advantage is that he prints his things at once, and he already has a
                much larger circulation than <title key="poetry" level="j">Harriet</title>. Their news stand sale last month was <measure quantity="3000" commodity="copies">three thousand copies</measure>.
                This is exclusive of subscriptions. I have also sent him your essays, and I think he will certainly
                take one of them. What he does not take I shall try to get printed elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Our half-yearly account for the Anthology comes in on the first of August, and I sincerely
                trust that I shall have some money to send you then. I sent Hilda a draft for <measure type="currency" num="10">ten dollars</measure>, which I
                got out of <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName> as the second payment on his agreement with me. He still owes you <measure type="currency" num="10">ten dollars</measure>
                on that agreement. But as I have succeeded in getting two payments, I have no doubt that I shall
                get the third in time, but probably not before Autumn. The poor devil is awfully stuck himself,
                and has just married, into the bargain. But I shall try for the last payment as soon as I return to
                town in the Autumn.</p>
            <p>If you ever see “<title key="others" level="j">Others</title>”, you will be surprised to find a poem in the current number by
                me. I say you will be surprised, because I told you that Fletcher and I had agreed not to go into it.
                This particular number is edited by <persName key="wc_williams">William Carlos Williams</persName>, and he wrote and begged me to
                send something for his sake. I like Williams, but I told him that Fletcher and I had agreed to send
                nothing without consulting each other, and that, therefore, I could not send him anything. He
                replied that Fletcher had sent him a poem from <placeName key="england">England</placeName> for this number. I don’t know why
                Fletcher did not let me know before he went back on our agreement, but in the letter I had from
                him, written two days before yours, he made no mention of this transaction. However, partly
                because Fletcher had sent a poem, partly because I like Williams, partly because I think the
                magazine has not been so objectionable lately, I did send him a poem; which fact I now greatly
                regret as I do not think this number at all good.<anchor xml:id="n4"/> It contains contributions from my particular
                detestations – <persName key="jeanne_dorge">Jeanne D’Orge</persName> and <persName key="mina_loy">Mina Loy</persName>. <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> has some more Chinese translations in it, and I
                think they are wretched. Fletcher’s poem, too, is not good.</p>
            <p>Fletcher does not seem to have seen any of you since he has been in England. I think he is
                much taken up in being married at present. He sent me two poems the other day and asked me to
                sell them to “<title key="century" level="j">The Century</title>” for him. I do not think them good, but he is so sensitive, I do not like 
                to tell him that across the water. So I immediately sent them along. I do not know whether they
                will take them or not.</p>
            <p>What you say about Hilda’s people hearing of our work in the West is very gratifying.
                There is a woman named <persName key="katherine_howard">Katherine Howard</persName> who is acting the part of John the Baptist for us,
                going from city to city in the <placeName key="pacificCoast">Pacific Coast</placeName> lecturing on our work for love, as she charges nothing
                for her lectures. She writes me that she has prepared the ground for me and that I must soon
                come. I think I shall take the advice and go out next Spring.</p>
            <p>My lectures are extremely successful and, I think, have done considerable for the cause of
                our work. I am speaking on “The New Poetry, With Special Reference to Imagism” in <placeName key="stLouis">St. Louis</placeName>
                on November 7th, and I am giving four lectures on “Modern American Poets” at the
                Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences in January. These four lectures will also be repeated in
                <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> and <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, and possibly in 
                <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> and <placeName key="phildelphia">Philadelphia</placeName>. I am to talk before an elocution
                school up here on “Poetry as a Spoken Art” next month. My four lectures on American
                poets have one drawback for me, in that they do not permit me to include you and Flint, for
                which I am extremely sorry; but it was unavoidable. I am, however, giving one lecture to the
                American Imagists, in which I deal exclusively with Hilda and Fletcher, and I shall run in
                remarks about you and Flint along with them.</p>
            <p><persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> wrote me: “We are gaily ringing our last shilling.” Whether this means his or
                England’s, I was unable to discover. I begged Fletcher to find out if he was in want, but he has
                not done so yet. If you know, I wish you would let me know, as I should not like him to suffer,
                and possibly the funds for such purposes which I left in Hilda’s hands are already exhausted. I
                hope to have some money to send him when I hear from <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> next month.</p>
            <p>My own book, “<title key="menWomenGhosts" level="m">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>”, has gone to press and will be out in October.
                I hear from <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> that Hilda<anchor xml:id="n5"/> is to be issued in this country as one of the Autumn set of
                the <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">New Poetry series</title>. That is good news, and I shall review the book for either Braithwaite or
                “The Seven Arts”. I forget whether I sent you my review of you and Flint in “The Poetry Review”;
                but at any rate, it will come with the back numbers on the subscription I have just given for you.</p>
            <p>It is amusing to see, in this number of “Others”, that <persName key="conrad_aiken">Conrad Aiken</persName>, that arch-plagiarist, is
                now trying to write a la (sic) Imagists, having gone through the stages of <persName key="john_masefield">Masefield</persName> and <persName key="el_masters">Masters</persName>!</p>
            <p>I am afraid you will not like my new book much, as it is all stories, and some are in the
                despised stanza form that you objected to so much in my last book. I am afraid I was born
                eclectic and must write in every way to satisfy my soul. Some of these, however,
                I think you will like; in fact, I know you will, because you have already liked them.</p>
            <p>My “<title key="swordBladesAndPoppySeed" level="m">Sword Blades</title>” has just gone into a second edition. It has taken it a devil of a time to
                do it, but they printed a huge edition the first time. However, the sales are
                increasing, and that is something.</p>
            <p>Write me as often as you can. I miss your letters awfully when I do not get them. I wrote
                to Hilda a week or so ago, and I shall write again very soon, as she must be dreadfully lonely,
                and I think writing is the best way to help her just now. It does look as if the war would soon be
                over, and you can be quite sure that as soon as it is I shall cross the ocean to see you all.</p>
            <closer>With much love,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Mary Aldis, "Some Imagist Poets, 1916," The Little Review, Vol. 3, No. 4 (June-July, 1916), pp. 26-32.</note>
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">Flint, "Three Imagist Poets," The Little Review, Vol. 3, No. 4 (June-July, 1916), pp. 32-41.</note>
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "Malmaison," The Little Review, Vol. 3, No. 4 (June-July, 1916), pp. 1-6.</note>
                <note target="#n4" resp="mb">Others, Vol. 3, No. 1 (July, 1916).</note>
                <note target="#n5" resp="mb">H.D., Sea Garden (Houghton Mifflin, 1916).</note>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>