<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-12-30"
                    >Dec. 30, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$152i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of five sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. At the
                        top of each new sheet is a heading, with “R.A.” and a page number on the left and the date on the
                        right. There are a few places where words have been scratched out or inserted, and there appears
                        to be a faint, illegible watermark on the paper.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-12-30">Dec. 30, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Thank you very much for your copy of the <title key="poetsTranslationSeries" level="s">Renaissance poems</title>,<anchor xml:id="n1"/> and please thank <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>
                for her “<title key="iphigeneia">Choruses from Iphegeneia</title>.” I am delighted to have them, only I wish you had written in
                them, and not merely signed them. You must write in your book for me, will you?</p>
            <p>I went through your proof on Sunday, and it is just as well I did, for there were several
                quite bad mistakes: one whole line was left out, one word was wrong, and one title was left out
                in the table of contents, besides various minor mistakes. I have sent them to Brown with a note,
                requesting that I <del rend="strikethrough">may</del> be allowed to see the proofs again after they are corrected, for I wish to do
                everything in my power to get your book quite right. It looked very well, I thought, in print,
                especially the one (whose names I have forgotten) with a little golden cock pecking at the blue
                wheat-fields of the sky. It is rather funny, in the Christmas number of the “<title key="century" level="j">Century</title>” I spoke of a
                golden cock with his mouth open.<anchor xml:id="n2"/> I did not put it as prettily as you did. I said a little piece of the
                sky was wedged in his beak; but it shows that we both have been impressed by that gesture of
                weathercocks. My poem was written last Spring, long before I saw yours, and you have never
                seen mine, which makes the unconscious plagiarism amusing.</p>
            <p>I have sent three of Hilda’s poems to “The Century:” “<title key="pearTree" level="a">Pear-tree</title>,” “<title key="contest" level="a">The Contest</title>,” and
                “<title key="seaGods" level="a">Sea Gods</title>.” I Had a note from <persName key="william_benet">Benét</persName> yesterday, saying that they should have his <add place="above">immediate</add>
                attention. I hope they will take them, for “The Century” pays very well, but I am a little bit
                doubtful, they are so queer about the things they take and the things they don’t.</p>
            <p>I had a letter from <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> the other day, and she asked me to send her some
                poems of yours and Hilda’s, saying that you had authorized her to ask for them. I sent her your
                “<title key="bloomsburySquare" level="a">Bloomsbury Square</title>” and “<title key="epigram" level="a">Epigram</title>,” and 
                Hilda’s “<title key="lateSpring" level="a">Late Spring</title>” and “<title key="night" level="a">Night</title>.” I hope that this
                will meet with your approval.</p>
            <p><persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> is making me very miserable by requesting the manuscript of the
                <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> as soon as possible. He now says he wants it by the end of January. I told him I did
                not see how we could have it as soon as that, and we were still to hear from England about some
                of the things. I have received two poems from <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> this morning. I suppose you have seen
                them; but as you did not mention them, and as he says he is leaving Hampstead at once, I am
                enclosing copies. Of course, they are neither of them Imagist poems, that is the truth of the
                matter. He writes a very nice letter, and says he knows he is not an Imagist, and he will not mind
                in the least if we turn them down, but I do not think, with this row about Lawrence in England,
                that we can turn them down. They have none of the objections that his work sometimes has, as
                you know, and I think “<title key="erinees" level="a">Erinees</title>” is really a very fine thing, although I think the end is a little
                weak. The other is just a bit too vague and cosmic for me, as I suppose it is for you too. Of
                course, there are only two, but he says they are the only ones he has which we can possibly want.
                If you know any differently, I wish you would make him add others; but these are fairly long,
                and will certainly take up as much space as he is entitled to. Send me a line, telling me that the
                rest of you approve, and I will put them in.</p>
            <p>I am enclosing some poems of <persName key="jean_untermeyer">Mrs. Untermeyer’s</persName>, which I am very anxious for you to
                see. She is very new at the business, as I wrote to you in my last letter, but I think these poems
                show good possibilities, and there is a feeling, a personality, in her verses which is perhaps more
                visible to a woman than to a man but which I personally think unusual and very beautiful; and I
                think Hilda will agree with me. Most of these poems have been accepted by magazines over
                here. On account of her husband, who is very well known, she has the inside track with a number
                of papers. But the last one, “<title key="clothes" level="a">Clothes</title>,” has not been printed, and I have asked for it for 
                “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>.” Of course, I told her that I had no right to accept poems for “The Egoist,” but I feel sure
                that you will want to print it. I also asked her whether she would be willing to go into the
                Anthology, if we did put in any extra people another year; in other words, whether she was
                willing to subscribe herself an Imagist, and she is very willing, I think delighted. As I
                told you before, it is not only a good thing to have her on our side on account of her own work, in which I
                personally recognize a high quality, but because her husband is one of the most enthusiastic and
                hard-working critics we have, and he himself is improving daily.</p>
            <p>I cannot remember whether I sent you <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> <title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Anthology</title> or not, so I am sending you another copy in
                case I did not. I think you will think <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Untermeyer’s</persName> “<title key="laughters" level="a">Laughters</title>” a fine thing. He writes for 
                the “<title key="chicagoEveningPost" level="j">Chicago Evening Post</title>.” He has a regular position there, as poetry
                critic; and to have his wife so obviously one with us at heart is certainly affecting his opinion of
                us in every way. I would not, of course, suggest your printing of one of her poems merely to get
                her husband’s good will; but both Fletcher and I think this poem, “Clothes,” excellent. But you
                understand that, if you do not like it, you are under no obligation to accept it.</p>
            <p>It is awfully nice of you to want me to send you an article and some of my poems for
                your February number. I have not been able to have the photograph taken yet, and I am
                dreadfully afraid I cannot have it taken in time for that number. The pressure of work here is
                something terrific. I am doing all I can, but I have not been able to do that, so I am afraid you 
                will have to go to press without my picture. Perhaps it is just as well, for I cannot think that my
                picture will be any gain to me.</p>
            <p>I was immensely interested in the letters from the man in the German war prison in your
                last number.<anchor xml:id="n3"/> It makes me feel more than ever that “The Egoist” is having an effect.</p>
            <p>I will send over some poems for your February number. “<title key="dinnerParty" level="a">The Dinner Party</title>” is, of course,
                one poem; and if you accept that, you will not need the shorter ones. But I am sending four short
                ones, in case you do not like “The Dinner Party,” and you can print the little ones as a group. IF
                you want to take “The Dinner Party” for this February and put the others in later, you are
                welcome to do so. If you do not want them, either all or sundry, send me back whatever you
                discard.</p>
            <p>Fletcher has written a preface for the Anthology. I am afraid it is too long and too erudite.
                He is going to bring it out on Sunday, and we will work over it together, and get it off to you
                next week. You are then to make any changes or alterations you want, and send it back again.
                The time is getting awfully short, so do hurry, as Greenslet says the latest he can possibly have it
                is the first of February.</p>
            <p>You say nothing about my poem, “<title key="turnpike" level="a">Off the Turnpike</title>,” which I sent to you sometime ago.
                Do you approve, or don’t you? The poem is under consideration at “The Century,” and if you
                like it, and if they accept it, I must make arrangements with them to publish it before the
                Anthology comes out. It occurs to me with a feeling of horror that you may be going to print
                “Off the Turnpike” in your February number. It would have been perfectly all right for you
                to do so, only I never thought of it, like a fool, and went and sent it to “The Century.” I do not believe
                they will accept it, but Benét asked me to send it. He is the first reader of “The Century,” but has
                not the final say, and the man who has, knows nothing about poetry. I know Benét is trying to
                force it on them, but I do not think he can. If you have taken it for “The Egoist,” and it is 
                too late to substitute one of these others, please cable me; and then if you will tell me how much I owe
                you for the cable, I will gladly pay it, as “The Century” makes you sign a paper stating that the
                things you sent them have never been published before; and I shall get into no end of a mess, if
                they take it for “The Century” and it appears in “The Egoist.” I am awfully sorry to put you to
                this trouble, but I had not sent it to “The Century” when I sent it to you, and it was long before
                your suggestion that I submit something to “The Egoist” came, and so I never regarded it as
                going into “The Egoist” at all. I am awfully sorry.</p>
            <p>Ferris Greenslet was very anxious to have us change the title of this year’s Anthology;
                but I told him that it was impossible, and that I did not think it advisable, and so we are
                calling it “Some Imagist Poets 1916,” with the “1916” very large and underlined. I trust that will do the
                trick.</p>
            <p><persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> wrote me a perfectly beautiful review of my “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">French Poets</title>,” so beautiful that it
                almost reduced me to tears. I have not heard from you or Hilda. I hope that does not mean that
                you do not like the book. It is doing very well here, and has nearly sold out its whole edition
                already, <measure quantity="750" commodity="copies">750 copies</measure> <add place="above">gone out</add> I heard by 
                last accounts, and <persName key="ec_marsh">Mr. Marsh</persName> says we shall have to
                reprint before long. Two professors of the English Departments of <placeName key="harvard">Harvard</placeName> 
                and <placeName key="yale">Yale</placeName> have come
                out strongly in favour. <persName key="william_phelps">Professor William Lyon Phelps</persName>, who is supposed to be one of the best
                things we have over here in literature, has written to the Macmillans to say that he considers it
                the most valuable work on French literature he has seen for a long time. Personally, I care very
                little for professorial opinion as much, but these things help with the public. I have very little
                hope for the sale in England. It is not a good time, and I do not think Americans are in very good
                favour over there just now. But still I hope. Do all you can to push it, won’t you?</p>
            <closer>
                <p>Lots of love to Hilda</p>
                <p>Affectionately,</p>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>Fletcher has just telephoned to tell me that a letter from you, which I forwarded him
                    to-day, contains the painful news that you have voted against both “<title key="clipperShips" level="a">Clipper Ships</title>” and “Off the
                    Turnpike.” I was afraid you might not like “Off the Turnpike” because, not knowing the Yankees
                    and their customs, you cannot realize how true to their speech it is. I suggested it for the
                    Anthology as a foil for the rest of the things in the book, for I have a theory that the more variety
                    one can have, the better it is, and another one of this same New England series, which was
                    published in “<title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>,” made such an excellent impression here that I thought it
                    would be good for the sale of the book to have this one in. But I daresay you are right in thinking
                    it does not go, and I am quite willing to substitute something else, but what, it is a little difficult
                    to decide.</p>
                <p>I am sending you a choice. “<title key="stravinsky" level="a">Stravinsky</title>” is the most remarkable poem of the lot, but I do
                    not approve of it for the Anthology. In the first place, one should have heard the music to
                    understand it. In the second place, its peculiar diction is sure to be taken as a huge joke by people
                    who do not know Stravinsky and have not a chance, by a number of my poems together, to see
                    what I am driving at. Therefore I do not approve of it for the Anthology, unless still a third poem
                    is added to go with it.</p>
                <p>I assume that you accept “<title key="springDay" level="a">The Spring Day</title>” as one of my contributions, since you have
                    not said anything about that to Fletcher.</p>
                <p>Now “<title key="leadSoldiers" level="a">Lead Soldiers</title>,” which I am also enclosing, is I think one of the best things I have
                    done. You may not agree, on account of the little childish rhyme which keeps coming into it; but
                    that is an effect I wanted to give, a sort of nursey rhyme, and to me it adds to the rest of the
                    poem; but I do not think this poem so good here, as in that case my contributions will both be in
                    “polyphonic prose,” and that I was trying to avoid. Too much of one metre.</p>
                <p>“<title key="timeOfDearth" level="a">In a Time of Dearth</title>” is very good, but too short to make the second contribution all by itself.
                    In that case I should advise including with it the “<title key="impressionistPicture" level="a">Impressionist Picture of a Garden</title>” or
                    possibly “The Dinner Party,” if you like it enough. And then there is always “<title key="patterns" level="a">Patterns</title>,” which
                    you can have if you want to. And here is one called “<title key="paperWindmill" level="a">The Paper Windmill</title>,” which could be used
                    with “The Spring Day” and one of the other <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="fr">vers libre</foreign></hi> things, but not as the second contribution
                    by itself, it too being “polyphonic prose.</p>
                <p>Now please send me your answer by return mail, and send back the poems at the same
                    time. Ferris Greenslet is in such a hurry that we cannot delay three days.</p>
                <p>Of these poems I am sorry that I can only submit those I mentioned in the letter and
                    which I marked “unpublished” on the manuscript, for you to print in the February “Egoist.”
                    “Lead Soldiers” has already appeared in “<title key="poetry" level="j">Poetry</title>,” and “The Paper Windmill” in “The Century.”
                    “In a Time of Dearth” has been accepted by “The Century,” “Stravinsky” is under consideration
                    by “<title key="masses" level="j">The Masses</title>,” and “The Impressionist Picture of a Garden” is the same with the “<title key="smartSet" level="j">Smart Set</title>.”</p>
                <p>I do think you are thoroughly mistaken in regard to Fletcher’s “Clipper Ships.” It is to my
                    mind one of the best things he has done. It was published in “The New Republic” and had a good
                    success. I do think that we should be careful and not let our theories of poetry interfere with our
                    taking in really excellent poems. Fletcher’s “polyphonic prose” with bits of old sea “chanties”
                    coming in, gives an extraordinarily vivid picture of the period; and even if you are not
                    particularly interested in the period or particularly interested in the form, it seems to me the value
                    of this Anthology is in allowing us all to develop on our own lines and letting the public see how
                    each one has developed from year to year and how he differs from the others. If you cut out a
                    poem of so great an originality as Fletcher’s, you will have, to my mind, set a dagger at the heart
                    of the Anthology. Fletcher has a great and remarkable originality, and originality is the important
                    thing in poetry.</p>
                <p>Do not let your translations usurp too large a place in your work. Translations, no matter
                    how good, are of minor importance compared to original work. Nobody knows that better than I,
                    for have I not spent my entire Summer in making translations? For minor men, like 
                    <persName key="edward_fitzgerald">Edward Fitzgerald</persName>, translating is important, but for poets of ambition and vigour, translating is only of
                    value for two reasons: for boiling the pot, or for doing a little something when you have nothing
                    else to do. Diving into other men’s minds is a delight and a temptation, but it must be kept in its
                    proper place like any other vice. Vice for an original worker, that is.</p>
                <p>Fletcher is not a bit sore about “Clipper Ships,” but I am rather, because I have the fate of
                    the book extremely at heart, and I know it would be a good thing for the book to have “Clipper
                    Ships” in it. Please believe my acumen when I tell you that, if we publish the present Anthology
                    and do not have it more interesting, and arresting, and unusual, than the first, more full of
                    different kinds of things, we shall come a cropper, for the first interest in our work will have
                    subsided, and mere repetition of the same kind of thing will interest nobody. Our first Anthology
                    was better than <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra’s</persName> Anthology because it was not so monotonous. I think you must remember,
                    in judging poems for this Anthology, that monotony is the great thing to be avoided. My only
                    objection to including my own “Patterns” from our Anthology was that I thought the public had a
                    right to demand something new, and “Patterns” Has already been published in Braithwaite’s
                    Anthology and copied in many papers over the country. But if you want it, all right.</p>
                <p>Of course, you shall have “<title key="whitechapel" level="a">Whitechapel</title>” if your heart is set on it. Neither Fletcher nor I
                    intended to take any arbitrary stand, we merely pointed out that we did not think it up to your
                    standard. In judging poems to admit or exclude, we follow an entirely different line from the one
                    that you follow. You take an abstract standard and insist that all poems shall conform to that. We
                    have no hard and fast standard, we take your work on its own merits, and see whether it comes to
                    measure favourably in effect with other work you have done. It would not make any difference if
                    we were together and could pick them out, but with the mails taking so long to go and come, this
                    choosing is a little bit difficult.</p>
                <p>Now please write me back exactly what you want me to do about my own things.
                    Fletcher and I will look over his things on Sunday and send you some more to choose from. Only
                    whatever you say this time must be definite, as we have no time for the mail to come across
                    again. Personally, I believe from the point of view of the public you are wrong not to let me have
                    my “Off the Turnpike.” I am sure it would help sell the book. But, of course, if you feel strongly
                    about it, that is all right, I don’t mind a bit.</p>
                <p>On reading this over, I think I sound huffed. I am not, the least little bit in the world. I can
                    perfectly understand that you don’t like dialect poems. Lots of people don’t. I would have
                    written it in ordinary spelling, the same way <persName key="john_synge">Synge</persName> wrote Irish, but Yankee dialect is more a
                    question of pronunciation and elision than of twisted syntax, and the effect would have been lost.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington has sent Lowell a copy of a volume of the Poets' Translation Series, a series of twelve pamphlets of Greek, Latin, and Italian translations by Aldington and H.D. published by the Egoist Press.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">"Paper Windmill," The Century, December 1915 (Vol. 91, No. 2), 232-235.</note> 
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb">"Extracts from the Letters of a Prisoner of War,' The Egoist, December 1, 1915 (Vol. 2, No. 12) 185-186.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>