<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document
will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rngC:\Users\kpart\OneDrive\Documents\XML\ALLP_ODD-6.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> <!-- Change href to your RNG file location locally -->
<!DOCTYPE doc [
    <!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                        key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date
                        when="1920-02-20"
                    >February 20, 1920</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="drr">Danielle Nasenbeny</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$304i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is 5 pages long. It is typed on carbon paper. The date is in the top right, and to the left of the date on each page is a backwards slash with 46 above it. There is an annotation at the top of the page starting on the second page (Mr. Aldington - [Page #]). There is a certificate of issue after page 2, before page 3.</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement>LOCATION OF LETTER WRITING</settlement>
                    <date>DATE OF LETTER WRITING</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter"> 
                    <opener><dateline><date when="1920-02-20">February 2, 1920</date></dateline>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
                    <p>Your letter of <date when="1920-01-05">January 5th</date> came a day or two ago and has given me great
                    pleasure. I am delighted to know that the “<title key="angloFrenchReview" level="j">Anglo-French Review</title>” has 
                    “<title key="oneTwoThree" level="a">One, Two, Three</title>” and “<title key="summerNightPiece" level="a">Summer Night Piece</title>.” Of course a <measure type="currency">guinea</measure> is a 
                    ludicrous price; over
                    here I get <measure type="currency" quantity="25">$25.00</measure> for short poems and more according to length. Sometimes I get
                    a great deal more, sometimes as much as <measure type="currency" quantity="100">$100.00</measure>, but here I am somebody while in
                    <placeName key="england">England</placeName> I am nobody, and I am glad to have a chance to publish there even at the
                    price of a guinea.</p>
                    <p>I think your idea of publishing the things in “<title key="coterie" level="j">Coterie</title>” most excellent, but I am
                    sorry to have <persName key="conrad_aiken">Aiken</persName> in it as Aiken is one of solidest enemies over here. The man
                    has me on the brain. Evidently I annoy him. I notice in his book, “<title key="skepticisms" level="m"><choice><orig>Scepticisms</orig><reg>Skepticisms</reg></choice></title>,”
                    that I am mentioned more times than any one else in the book, and almost always
                    in wrath. I am sort of a complex with him, and really, from the way he takes it,
                    it is almost a compliment to be so perpetually in his thought even if he does
                    not like me. However, if “Coterie” will take these things of mine, I quite agree
                    with you that the publicity is valuable.</p>
                    <p>You say you have two poems of mine; I think you have three, if I am not
                    mistaken: “<title key="granadilla" level="a">Granadilla</title>,” “<title key="carrefour" level="a">Carrefour</title>,” and “<title key="paradox" level="a">Paradox</title>.” Kindly tell me which two you
                    have, since I must keep track of these things as I am constantly having
                    applications for poems.</p>
                    <p>“<title key="dial" level="j">The Dial</title>,” as you know, has changed hands, also its format and its whole point
                    of view. I thought <persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName> had paid up all his debts before going to the
                    <placeName key="southSeaIslands">South Seas</placeName>, whither he has retired to hide his chagrin. The new owner is a man
                    named <persName key="schofield_thayer">Schofield Thayer</persName>. I do not know him. I meant to see him in <placeName>New York</placeName> a
                    couple of weeks ago, but I did not have time. However,<pb n="02"/> I shall try to see him
                    when I am in New York in <date when="1920-06">June</date>, and mention your claim for <measure type="currency" quantity="20">$20.00</measure>.</p>
                    <p>It amuses me to know that the “<title key="londonTimes" level="j">London Times</title>” only has a circulation of 34,000.
                    How small the scale in England is compared to that of <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>! I do not know
                    what the circulation is of the “<title key="newYorkTimes" level="j">New York Times</title>,” for which I write, but I think
                    a million and a half is nearer the figure.</p>
                    <p>What you say of the animosity of the <orgName key="poetryBookshop">Poetry Bookshop</orgName> is one of the things that
                    most annoys me. When <persName key="harold_monro">Harold Monro</persName> wrote me of his resuming “<title key="poetryDrama" level="j">Poetry and Drama</title>”
                    under a new form, I wrote him and suggested that he should allow me to have one
                    of the issues to write a simple resumé<!--is this a special character?--> of American poetry, with illustrations.
                    He waited about five months before answering me, and then said that he thought
                    the idea was a good one, but that he had already given it into other hands
                    before my letter reached him. Now I am afraid he has given it into the hands of
                    <persName key="charles_stork">Charles Wharton Stork</persName>, who runs a very feeble paper over here. Stork's interests
                    are entirely reactionary, he publishes the poorest poetry written <date when="1920">to-day</date>, and
                    his little paper, to which people contribute gratuitously, has no standing
                    whatever. He is always discovering poets whom nobody ever hears of. I really
                    believe he is the worst poet in the world himself, and anything but a gentleman
                    to boot. He came to call on me, the other day, and made a pleasant afternoon
                    call, and went away and told everything I said to a <placeName key="philadelphia">Philadelphia</placeName> paper as if it
                    had been an interview.</p>
                    <p>The reason I think he has been entrusted with this issue is because he told me
                    he had also written to Monro asking for it, but at the time he was here he had
                    not received an answer. If Monro puts himself in the hands of Stork, he will
                    have the most ludicrous misrepresentation of American poetry that could possibly
                    be given. How they do go wrong, Richard, and how anxious they are apparently to
                    choose the wrong people to inform them.</p><pb n="03"/> <!--There is a certificate between these pages -->
                    <p>I wonder who is doing the American notes for the “Times.” From what you say, it
                    is undoubtedly the same thing there.</p>
                    <p>What you say about my own books gives me great pleasure. I had an idea that you
                    did not like my books very much, taking them by and large. They have recently
                    been taken over by <persName key="basil_blackwell">Basil Blackwell</persName> who is very much interested in them, and I
                    hope the public will back him up a little as he is taking all the risks. He
                    would not even take the sheets from <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>, as he thought he could print more
                    cheaply over there. I have no doubt he is right, but of course it makes a
                    tremendous risk for him. He is to bring out “<title key="canGrandesCastle" level="m">Can Grande</title>” this <date when="1920">Spring</date>, and follow
                    with the other volumes at six month intervals if the sale of “Can Grande”
                    warrants his so doing.</p>
                    <p>Who will review it for the “Times,” you or who? Reviews make or mar a book so
                    much in England, and there is not a soul I know of who will speak favourably of
                    it except possibly yourself. <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> writes that she would like to review it if
                    she were to be in England, but as she is going to <placeName key="greece">Greece</placeName>, I suppose that will go
                    by the board. My work will probably go slowly at first as it did here, but I
                    have no real doubt about my future in England.</p>
                    <p>At last we are waking up to the fact that we have American poets and that they
                    are some good. You will be amused to learn that I have been offered the degree
                    of Doctor of Literature by a <placeName key="BaylorU">Western University</placeName>, which high honour I am to be
                    invested in at Commencement next <date when="1921-06">June</date>. As I Believe I am the first of the modern
                    poets, man or woman, to receive an academic recognition of this kind, I am a
                    good deal amused.</p>
                    <p>I do not know whether you have a <orgName key="phiBetaKappa">Phi Beta Kappa</orgName> society in England. It consists
                    of the first ten scholars in every graduating class, and is supposed to be,
                    therefore, the greatest body of intelligent men which can<pb n="04"/> exist. Every year,
                    each chapter of the Phi Beta Kappa has a meeting at which an orator and a poet
                    are chosen to speak, at Commencement, and I have been asked to deliver the Phi
                    Beta Kappa poem at <placeName key="columbiaU">Columbia University</placeName> this <date when="1920-06">June</date>. I gave the Phi Beta Kappa poem
                    at <orgName key="tufts">Tuft's College</orgName> some years ago, but Columbia is a much larger university. So
                    you see things are moving. These details, of course, do not matter a button
                    really. They are usually given to the wrong people, and I am probably one of the
                    wrong ones, but they do show a desire on the part of the public to help a native
                    poet.</p>
                    <p>What you say about not being able to get interested in anything does not
                    surprise me at all. The soldiers I have seen are all the same. Of course the
                    shock of <rs key="ww1" type="theme">what you have been through</rs> is terrific, and it will take some time to
                    get over it, but your interest will come back, my dear boy, it is certain to
                    come back as you grow stronger.</p>
                    <p>I am delighted that you are on the “Times,” for that is a permanent something to
                    cling to and keep you going until the urge for poetry writing comes back, and
                    even then I do not think it is too arduous for you to do your own work on the
                    side. I often review for the “Times” here, and although it takes a good deal of
                    time, you know my theory that one should do these things as the professionals do
                    them, even though one does not have to work, but can sit on a cushion and create
                    as one likes.</p>
                    <p>I do not agree with your opinion of <persName key="john_masefield">Masefield's</persName> “<title key="reynardTheFox" level="m">Reynard the Fox</title>.” I think that
                    it a fine thing of its kind, but perhaps I am more eclectic than you are. Is
                    that because I have less critical faculty, or because I am older? Who knows.</p>
                    <p>By the way, <persName key="michael_sadleir"><choice><orig>Michael Sadler</orig><reg>Michael Sadleir</reg></choice></persName> has asked me to send him some of my poems for a
                    little paper called “<title key="voices" level="j">Voices</title>,” the editor of which seems to like<pb n="05"/> my work, and on
                    the theory that it is better to be read even if unpaid, I did so. I wish I could
                    come over to England, but I am to have an <rs key="medical" type="theme">operation</rs> <date when="1920-02">next week</date>. It is a nuisance
                    because it cuts off the rest of my <date when="1920">Winter</date>, and it will be some time before I am
                    able to work again, but it cannot be helped. I have waited too long as it is.</p>
                    <closer>With much love,
                    Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>