<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1918-04-11"
                    >April 11, 1918</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$243i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is seven pages long. The word Aldington is written in pencil in the top left at a 
                        forty-five-degree angle slanting upwards from left to right. The date is in the top right along with the
                        page annotation “Mr. Aldington–[Page #]” from the second page on.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1918-04-11">April 11, 1918</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I am overcome by <title key="reverie" level="m">your book</title>,<anchor xml:id="n1"/> which I think truly magnificent for the most part. I confess,
                I think the war poems reach a higher mark than the love poems, probably because it is almost
                impossible to give love adequately in words. To me this is far the strongest work you have done,
                and I think you have lost none of your beauty and delicacy, as you seemed to fear you had. The
                poems that I already know I feel about as I did before. But there are some new ones here that I
                had not seen before, and which I think are as fine as any of your work.</p>
            <p>“<title key="fatigues" level="a">Fatigues</title>” I like especially. I read it the other day in a programme of war poems which I
                gave for a war charity. I read that and “<title key="apathy" level="a">Apathy</title>,” and they were both exceedingly well received. I
                think “Apathy” is perhaps the finest poem in the book, but it is difficult to say the finest when
                most of the poems are on such a high level. I am also very much interested in “<title key="trenchIdyll" level="a">Trench Idyll</title>.” I
                like “<title key="trenches" level="a">In the Trenches</title>” too, and 
                “<title key="earthGoddess" level="a">An Earth Goddess</title>” is exceedingly striking. I sold this last to the
                “<title key="northAmericanReview" level="j">North American Review</title>,” but unfortunately discovered immediately afterward, what I had
                forgotten, that it had appeared in <persName key="charles_bubb">Bubb’s</persName> “Reverie.” This is too bad for of course the “North
                American Review” will not take anything which has already appeared. Personally, I always
                regret any of these little <orgName key="clerksPress">privately printed books</orgName>, as they interfere so dreadfully with public 
                printing later on, and the circulation is not large enough to make them worthwhile, but I
                know you have not thought so.</p>
            <p>The love part does not seem to me so good as the war part, to be strictly honest. It is just
                about impossible to do, that is the amount of it. If I had a criticism it would be, not that your
                poems are too physical in their expression, but that for the first time in your work you have
                entirely obliterated the other side of love – the spiritual. Of course, they are both true, and they
                must both exist together in any real love, and possibly, after the trenches, the more physical side
                seems the most important, but I cannot help feeling that you will be somewhat misunderstood by
                the expression of this section. A little change here and there, a poem or two inserted to stress the
                love side in contradistinction to the lust side, would have made the balance truer, I think. Do not
                misunderstand me. I am not in the least shocked, and personally I like these poems and think
                them extremely strong, but I think them only the voice of half a feeling, not of a whole feeling,
                and I think they may create a certain undeserved hostility in some minds, which would of course
                be unfortunate. That you will escape by being published by <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>, as his clientèle is small and
                thoroughly “in the know,” but I dreamed of finding you a larger audience, and, from your letter
                and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> I supposed you had not already clinched with Brown, so I took the manuscript to
                <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> when I was in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>, and urged them to print it. They were most inclined to do
                so. <persName key="george_brett">Mr. Brett</persName>, the head of the firm, was extremely interested from my description. But after they
                had read the volume, they returned it to me saying that they thought it was one of the strongest
                books they had received, but that they literally did not dare to publish the poems of the second
                part as they stood, and as there seemed very little chance of getting you to alter this section when
                you were going back to the front, there was nothing for them to do but decline the volume. Had
                you been here I think everything could have been arranged satisfactorily. Brown does not know
                this, so don’t tell him.</p>
            <p>No sooner had I got home from New York than Brown informed me that he had already
                sent you the contract, and had heard from you saying that you would agree to let him have the
                book. Therefore there is nothing more to be done about it. Brown is always so out of funds that
                when he accepts books he does not always print them for ages. He has had a book of <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName>
                for a year and a half, and it has not appeared yet. My one aim was to get you into the hands of
                one of the established publishers, and I am awfully sorry that this could not have been done.</p>
            <p>I do not believe that it is what one says in a poem that matters, it is the kind of light that
                plays over it; and I do think you played the physical rather more than most people can appreciate.
                I have a theory that you have been somewhat influenced in this by <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>, and do you mind
                my urging you to be careful not to let his influence go too far? He has ruined his own public by
                his attitude, and I am dreadfully afraid of its effect on you, particularly as it is not in the
                least your natural mode of speech. By this time you are sighing and saying, “Oh Lord, Puritan New
                England!” but you know it is not that. I suppose the real crux of the situation lies in the extreme
                difficulty of touching anything so sacred as the relation between man and woman without
                vulgarizing it. A prurient world reads vulgarity into certain expressions which do not in the least
                connote vulgarity. But, after all, words are a means of communication, and if one communicates
                something other than what one intended, I think the result might be termed “bad writing.” That is
                the blunder which Lawrence makes, I think. To you and me and a few people like us, he
                expresses exactly what he means; but those people are a handful, and it has always been so. To
                most people, he says something entirely different. Now you may say that you do not write for the
                ignorant masses, but for the cultivated few, but I do not believe you do. Only the minor poets do
                that. Great poetry is and must be universal, above the customs or cliques or the delight of the
                initiated.</p>
            <p>You said something in one of your letters to me which gave me infinite pleasure and
                much food for thought. It was that the war had made you realize “the supreme importance of
                literature and the supreme unimportance of literary life.” The trouble with most of us, and the
                reason we do not develop into great poets is that the literary life catches and clips us,
                and we cannot see beyond it.</p>
            <p>This is hardly a criticism, merely a suggestion. If you were here and we were going over
                these poems, I should suggest very few changes, merely the addition of a few more poems on a
                different basis. Certain changes I would suggest, and since you ask for my criticism, I am going
                to be bold enough to make them.</p>
            <p>For instance, in “<title key="oldSong" level="a">An Old Song</title>” your last two lines read:
                <q rend="centered"><l>“Into uttermost hell shall I go</l>
                    <l>For sweet sin with this lady.”</l></q>
                Now by “sweet sin” I take it that you mean that you are worshipping a human being more than
                the virgin, but everybody else will read it as meaning a regular debauch. I think “<title key="sleep" level="a">Sleep</title>” 
                out-Lawrences Lawrence. In fact, I cannot remember any modern poem that goes quite so far as this.
                Was that necessary, do you think. On the other hand, I think “<title key="beforeParting" level="a">Before Parting</title>” is fine with the
                exception of “love-plaint” which I do not like. In “<title key="nightsOfLove" level="a">Nights of Love</title>” I should leave out the dates.
                This I think really very important, and I hope you will write to Brown to leave them out. They
                seem to me a rending open of the veil of privacy which is almost painful to the reader, and in a
                published book creates a sort of disgust.</p>
            <p>I hope, dear Richard, you will not mind my telling you these things. You asked me for
                criticism, and therefore I am taking the liberty of making these suggestions.</p>
            <p>Your work seems to me improving steadily. The war is making all of us more real I think.
                I confess that I find the ivory tower much less congenial than I did. Things are too big for us to
                be content with the merely precious. I hate to tell people what I think of their things. I hate to tell
                you most of all when by any possible chance I do not like anything, for I admire your work so
                entirely and admire you and your attitude toward life so much that any criticism seems
                impertinent. Still, I know you will forgive me and if you do not like these suggestions you
                will not take them.</p>
            <p>Things are absolutely drowned in war here, but there is still a great interest in poetry. I
                am doing a great deal of reading poetry aloud for war purposes and have found my audiences
                most interested and eager. If the war lasts too long of course it will kill all the refinements of life,
                but if it can be ended in a year or two, I think it will have done poetry an immense service. There
                is already less freakishness and more seriousness, more of the real stuff of poetry coming out to-day. 
                Of course one discounts all the popular songs of the war. They are sure to exist and do not
                count either way. But your book is a proof to me that the war has done you good, and that when
                you come back and take up the business of poet again, you will be a far greater poet than you
                ever would have been had the war not come. Alas, suffering is the very stuff out of which poetry
                is wrought! I do not believe that the poet is made of sugar candy and melts at the slightest touch.
                If he is worth anything he is strong enough to endure, no matter what happens to him; and, after
                the endurance, he should be tempered to a tool capable of much.</p>
            <p>By the way, what is the matter with Fletcher? I do not suppose you know, but he writes
                me the most extraordinary letters. I had a letter from him yesterday in which he informed me that
                he should feel obliged to break off his friendship with me because <persName key="james_oppenheim">Oppenheim</persName> had written a long
                didactic poem which <persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName> had published in 
                “<title key="dial" level="j">The Dial</title>.” Fletcher thinks that because
                neither he nor I have had long poems in “The Dial” for Johnson to have printed Oppenheim’s,
                which he does not like, is an insult to us, and that if I am not willing publicly to resent this event,
                I can be no friend to him, Fletcher. Did you ever hear such an insane notion? What business has
                any one to dictate to Martyn Johnson how to run his paper? Or to James Oppenheim what poetry
                he shall write? It is doubtless unfortunate that Martyn Johnson prefers James Oppenheim’s
                poetry to Fletcher’s and mine, but I fail to see that we have any business to go on the war path
                because he does, and that Martyn Johnson opens his pages at all to poetry is, I think, a happy
                omen. I am not going to answer Fletcher at all, and I think he will forget all about it, he usually
                does. But the whole thing seemed to me so unbalanced and peculiar that I cannot help thinking
                that the strain of the war and the lack of food has upset his health. If you know anything or can
                find out anything I wish you would let me know.</p>
            <p>I am sending Hilda a copy of my lecture on you and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> and Lawrence which I gave at
                the <placeName key="brooklynInstitute">Brooklyn Institute</placeName> a couple of weeks ago. In it you will see how greatly I admire you. It was
                in preparing this lecture that I came to realize more completely what a thunderingly fine poet you
                are. There is nothing like preparing one of those critical lectures to show up a man’s real
                qualities. I am sorry to say that Flint’s work crumbled to dust as I touched it, and Lawrence’s
                became almost painful in its lack of variety, but yours stood up strong, refreshing, and clear.
                All hail to you, my friend, go on! I think there is a lot ahead of you.</p>
            <p>Write me often: scrawls on postal cards, scraps of paper – anything. By the way, my
                nephew, <persName key="james_roosevelt">Captain James A. Roosevelt</persName>, is sailing for <placeName key="france">France</placeName> immediately. Of course I cannot tell
                his regiment, but I have told him about you, and if you should ever run across him, just tell him
                who you are, and you are sure of a friend.</p>
            <p>Goodbye for the moment.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">It is unclear whether Lowell is talking about Aldington's Reverie: a Little Book of Poems for H.D, published by the small, private, Cleveland Ohio-based Clerk's Press in 1917, or a draft manuscript of poems that would be published as Images of War in a small, hand-printed edition by Beaumont Press (London, 1919), and later by Allen and Unwin (London, 1919) and Four Seas Co. (Boston, 1921).</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>