<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-03-08"
                    >March 8, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$187i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of two sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of the first and
                        one side of the second. At the top of the back side is “R.A.” in the left corner and the date in the
                        right. There appears to be a watermark on the paper that reads “Berkshire Linen,” visible upside
                        down on the top of the first page.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-03-08">March 8, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I hope you will approve of what I have done with <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>. It consists chiefly in having
                given him a delightful jolt.</p>
            <p>As <title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">your book</title> is not yet out, and as I have waited some two months since you asked me to
                take the sheets away from him, I decided that I had better take the sheets away from him at once.
                So I telephoned him to that effect. He was extremely angry, and told me he would not relinquish
                them; whereupon I waxed wroth in my turn and told him that if they were not forthcoming the
                next day, I should send a lawyer to get them. If he refused to give them to the lawyer, I should go
                to court. We had a long and heated discussion, in which I made him realize pretty firmly that my
                reputation for honesty was unassailable, whereas his was not; and that if he went to law with me
                on the subject, it would ruin his professional reputation completely. I also told him that I should
                conduct the lawsuit myself, so that he need not think that his only adversary was some one living
                in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>.</p>
            <p>I then hung up the receiver and awaited developments. They came a few hours later, in
                the shape of another telephone message from Mr. Brown, containing the following amazing
                proposition: namely, that he would pay you royalties for <measure quantity="500" commodity="copies">500 copies</measure> in advance of publication!</p>
            <p>Your contract calls for 10% of royalties of the gross receipts, up to the first thousand
                copies sold. He is going to retail the book at <measure type="currency">60¢</measure> a copy, which would make <measure type="currency">$30.00</measure> your
                royalties for 500 copies. This he agrees to pay on or before the 15th of the
                present month.</p>
            <p>This proposition was made to me to induce me to allow <orgName key="fourSeasCo">him</orgName> to continue the publication
                of the book.<anchor xml:id="n1"/> I accepted it, which I hope you will consider was the right thing to do; for it seemed
                to me that the chances of your selling 500 copies of this book anywhere else within a reasonable
                length of time – particularly as we have no other publisher over here (and it is doubtful if you
                can get one) – are extremely slim. Also, you will easily perceive that Brown would want to
                reimburse himself as quick as possible for the $30.00 paid you. It will, therefore, be very clearly
                to his advantage to push the sale of your book.</p>
            <p>I do not in the least fear his not paying the money, as I and <persName key="william_putnam">my lawyer</persName> and my lawsuit are
                still ready to jump upon him if he does not come up to time. And if that suggestion has
                frightened him so much once as to have him make you this offer, I imagine that its potency will
                not evaporate in two weeks.</p>
            <p>I think then I should leave him <del rend="strikethrough">about</del> a little over six months to sell his 500 copies in, and
                then I think we can properly ask him for a statement of sales up to date, in case he owes you
                farther[sic] royalties. I trust you will think I have done well. Personally, this is far beyond my
                wildest hopes. Of course, it is true that you have lost the copyright on a certain number of the
                poems in this volume. But Mr. Brown intends to copyright the book just the same, as he says no
                human being will ever <del rend="strikethrough">go through</del> <add place="above">search</add> the English edition to see which poems are really
                copyrighted and which are not, so that, for all practical purposes, your claims are protected.</p>
            <p>I have no faith, nor any improvement to hope for, in Brown. I think he has proved himself
                not only unbusinesslike, but untrustworthy, and I certainly should not recommend his publishing
                any other books to anybody. <del rend="strikethrough">And</del> <add place="above">But</add> if at any future time you want to, I imagine you can buy
                the copyright from him without much difficulty. And I think, further, <del rend="strikethrough">than</del> that he will be out of
                business before long. At the rate he is going, and in that case would be quite willing to part with
                the copyright.</p>
            <p><persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> writes me that you have gone to <placeName key="devonshire">Devonshire</placeName>. Lovely country! I once passed a
                whole summer there.</p>
            <p>We expect to get the “<title key="some_imagist_poets" key="m">Imagist Anthology <hi rend="underline">1916</hi></title>” out in the <del rend="strikethrough">month</del> 
                <add place="above">middle</add> of April. I will, of course, send you copies as soon as they come.</p>
            <closer>Great deal of love.</closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>Here is your contract, signed. Brown says he has already sent you one, but I doubted it so
                    much that I made him give me another.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington ultimately publishes his book, Images, Old and New (1916), with Edmund R. Brown's press, Four Seas.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>