<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-08-05"
                    >Aug. 5, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$224i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is two pages long. The word Aldington is written in pencil in the top left at a 
                        forty-five-degree angle slanting upwards from left to right. The date is in the top right of both pages
                        and the annotation “R.A.--2” is in the top left of the second page.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-08-05">Aug. 5, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I enclose a draft for £16-3-2, representing yours and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> share of the
                August 1st royalties from our two volumes of “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Imagist Poets</title>.” The sales were as follows:
                249 Imagist Poets, 1915. .36 1/4 $90.26
                389 Imagist Poets, 1916. .36 1/4 <hi rend="underline">[$]141.01</hi>
                                                 [$]231.27 <!--I wasn't sure how to format this block of text where AL calculates the sales of the SIP 1915 and 1916-->
                <add place="below">There are 3 undivided cents, + as I cannot divide them amongst six people, I am keeping
                    them as my commission!!</add></p>
            <p>We are within <measure quantity="35" commodity="volumes">35 volumes</measure> of as many sold of the 1916 volume as of the 1915 at this date,
                with the exception of the English sale. <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> are extremely careless, and <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName>
                was either careless or unwilling. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> says he was away on his vacation; at any rate, I
                left it to them to arrange with the English house how many copies they would take, and somehow
                it slipped up and the English house has not ordered any copies yet. I had a talk with Greenslet
                about it just before I came up here, and he said that their contract with Constable was such that
                C. must take the book, and that he would see that they did it at once. But of course no sales from
                them appear on this statement. Houghton Mifflin were very careless about this, and it is awfully
                annoying, but we are doing the best we can about it now. The book is making a nice little
                property, as you see, and the fact that the first one is still selling is a very hopeful sign.</p>
            <p>I had a nice letter from Hilda the other day. She tells me she is leaving Devonshire to be
                near you, and that she will let me know her address later. I have not yet received it, so I cannot
                write to her. She sent me a number of <persName key="john_cournos">Cournos’</persName> poems, which I sent on to <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName>. Whether
                he will take them or not I do not know. Between you and me and the gate-post, I am not much
                struck with them, and I think there is very little chance of my being able to place them, but I will
                do my best.</p>
            <p>There is nothing new. This is a peaceful place and very little happens here. I am engaged
                on the proof-sheets of “<title key="menWomenGhosts" level="m">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>” which will come out in October, and also my
                lectures on modern poets. My “<title key="craftsman" level="j">Craftsman</title>” article<anchor xml:id="n1"/> has met with quite a little success. I am
                sending a copy of it to you.</p>
            <p>Will write again soon, and with love to Hilda when you see her, believe me,</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "Is There a National Spirit in 'The New Poetry' of America?" The Craftsman, Vol. 30, No. 4 (July, 1916), pp. 39-49.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>