<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-03-02"
                    >March 2, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$185i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of one sheet of paper with typewriting on both sides. At the top of the
                        back side is “R.A.” in the left corner and the date in the right. There appears to be a watermark
                        on the paper, but it is unreadable under the text.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-03-02">March 2, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I have received your letter telling me that <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> made the changes, in the <title key="frenchPoetsReview" level="a">article</title> on me,
                himself, and I hereby apologize most sincerely for scolding you or having done it. Of course, you
                were quite right to make Flint take out the personal remarks. I did not like them at all, and
                regretted that I had no authority to take them out before the article was printed in 
                “<title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>.” I do, however, feel that Flint has shown rather poor taste, and a very slight lack of
                psychology, by taking out praise of my book which he had originally put in, and which he knew I
                had already seen in his first draft of the article. But I should not have assumed that it was you
                who did it, and I am very sorry.</p>
            <p>I am beginning to think that perhaps I made a mistake about <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>. I thought he was
                honest, but I don’t at all like the way he is holding up <title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">your book</title>. And <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Mr. Braithwaite</persName> told me
                last night he manages his affairs so badly that he practically does not get his books sold in the
                bookshops at all, and I think I shall be obliged to take your book away. I don’t know how to
                make it up to you. I shall do my best and see what can be done; but I really think it must be taken
                out of <orgName key="fourSeasCo">Brown’s hands</orgName>. I am awfully sorry, and I feel very badly about it; but, of course, I
                supposed it would be all right – though I knew he wasn’t very well off.<anchor xml:id="n1"/></p>
            <p><title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Our book</title> is in the press, and they expect to bring it out the first or second week in April.
                I think it should be very good. Please forget the things I said about your blue-penciling of the
                article, and remember how differently things sound, coming across the Atlantic.</p>
            <p>I am sending you a <title key="andOtherPoets" level="m">little book of parodies</title> by <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName>, which I think is most
                amusing. And I am writing <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> about the royalties.</p>
            <p>Hilda says to address you at “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>”, so I suppose you are leaving Hampton. Please
                send me your new address as soon as possible.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Aldington ultimately publishes his book, Images, Old and New (1916), with Edmund R. Brown's press, Four Seas.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
