<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1917-07-20"
                    >July 20, 1917</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$232i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is five pages long, with a sixth page that was discarded. It was originally the second
                        page of the letter, with a line and a half typed with a pencil strike-through. The same sentence is
                        typed again at the top of the fully typed second page, with two small changes that I note in an
                        inline comment. The word Aldington is written in pencil in the top left at a forty-five-degree
                        angle slanting upwards from left to right. The date is in the top right of all pages and the
                        annotation “R.A.—[Page #]” is in the top right of all pages after the first.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I have just received “<title key="">The Love Poems of Myrrhine and Konallis</title>,” printed by <persName key="">Mr. Charles C. Bubb</persName> in 
                <placeName key="">Cleveland</placeName> with a letter from him in which he tells me you asked him to send me the
                book. I am so glad to get it; these poems are absolutely beautiful. I thought so when I read them
                first, and I think so again now even more perhaps, and in this terrible time of agitation and horror
                they come to me with a particularly soothing touch and remind me keenly of those delightful
                days we used to pass together when I was in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>. It all seems so long ago now. I wonder
                when it will come again.</p>
            <p>I want to thank you very much for the letter you wrote me about <persName key="">my brother’s</persName> death in the
                Winter. I could not write before; you know how it is. This is the first break in our family, and my
                brother and I were very sympathetic. You will remember that he was in London the last time that
                I was there, and, although I think you did not meet him, you must have heard me speak a great
                deal about him. I was terribly ill at the time of his death, so ill that they could not tell me at once,
                and I am only beginning to get my health back now, within the last month or two. I find work a
                great power of taking one’s mind off morbid thoughts, and, luckily for me, my power of work
                seems to continue unimpaired, but it has changed; I realize that.</p>
            <p>The war has affected me tremendously. I cannot escape it. I feel it on all sides pressing
                against me and mounting over me. The result is I know it has tinged my work, whether for the
                better or not, I cannot say; it is inevitable. Even many of my poems, which do not seem to
                have anything to do with the war are quite referable to it, if one could but see far enough.</p>
            <p><persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> writes me that she is bringing out a new volume of your poems, and has asked me
                to send back to her all those I have here to put into it, as she has not copies, and I am sending her
                everything I have by this mail.</p>
            <p>I wonder if you like the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Imagist Anthology</title>. It is not being received 
                very well – not as well as the others. It is partly because we are no longer a novelty, and partly because the war has
                affected everything here, just as it has in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. I think the volume has done its work,
                however, and, even if there had been no war, I think the moment for group publication is over,
                and now that we have got our ideas before the public so that people speak of Imagist verse as a
                kind of verse, almost as if it were already a classic term, still it seems to me the time has come
                for us to continue our reputation by our own separate publications. As I have just written Hilda,
                it is inevitable that we should develop our individualities, and that in doing so we should
                apparently grow farther and farther apart. I do not feel we really will do that; at least I shall not,
                because I admire and like your poetry as much as I ever did, but I am the sort of person who
                must write in many manners and about many subjects, and I realized that this is not always
                sympathetic to the rest of you, but it cannot be helped. I only hope that you will still like some of
                the things that I have done. Hilda wrote me an awfully nice letter about “<title key="" level="m">Men, Women, and Ghosts</title>,” 
                but I have never heard from you on the subject, so I am afraid you did not care for the
                book. That would be a sincere grief to me, as I regard your opinion so highly.</p>
            <p>I think of you often and wonder what you are doing, and whether you are in any of these
                battles we read about in the newspapers.</p>
            <p>I saw Hilda’s mother when I was lecturing at <placeName key="">Bryn Mawr</placeName>, and I thought she was afully
                nice, and we had a very nice little talk.</p>
            <p>I have written an article on Hilda’s work for <persName key="">Brown’s</persName> “<title key="" level="j">Poetry Journal</title>,” which is really a
                slight condensation of my long paper on her in my new book. I hope you will like it. Some of it I
                suppose you will not agree with, but most of it I think you will like very much. I hope it may
                induce people to read “<title key="" level="m">Sea Garden</title>” and to see for themselves what I have only been able to
                indicate.</p>
            <p>It was a great regret to me that this book of mine – it is called “<title key="" level="">Tendencies in Modern American Poetry</title>” 
                – being of course <add place="above">about</add> American poets only, gave me no chance to discuss your work. 
                Some day I hope to do that in another volume. Nobody could possibly admire your
                work more than I, and nobody could more firmly believe in its future than I do, and I am sorry
                that I have been able to be of so little use in the publication line. It is not easy to find publishers
                for any poetry, and most of the smaller ventures like <persName key="">Mr. Bubb’s</persName> are in the Western cities. Brown
                you have already conferred with, and know how little he is to be depended upon.</p>
            <p>The booksellers here are refusing poetry right and left. I do not know where I should be,
                but I have a contract with the Macmillan Company to publish everything I write, so that unless
                the war changes conditions very materially, they have got to take what I offer them. Of course,
                should they advise very strongly against the publication of anything, I should not insist, but
                hitherto they have not taken that stand.</p>
            <p>Did you know “<title key="" level="j">The Seven Arts</title>” had taken your “<title key="" level="a">Leave Taking</title>” 
                and “<title key="" level="a">On the March</title>” and <persName key="">Harriet Monroe</persName> has taken your 
                “<title key="" level="a">Fatigues</title>?”</p>
            <p>Harriet is doubtful whether she will be able to raise the money to carry on her magazine
                for the next five years. Many as are the blunders she makes, I still think it would be a very bad
                thing for all of us if she were to stop publication, but of course people are not anxious to give
                money to poetry magazines just now when what between taxes and subscriptions for war relief
                nobody has a surplus of funds.</p>
            <p>I have sent all the criticisms of “Some Imagist Poets, 1917” to Hilda, who will doubtless
                send on the ones to you which she thinks you would like to see; they are not worth anything. The
                book came out just as war was being declared, and it was knocked on the head thereby.
                <orgNamek key="constable">Constable</orgNamek> is printing an edition from a copy of the book which was sent to England, as England
                has placed an embargo on plates and sheets made in this country. This has actually cut out the
                publication of my new book in England, as it is too expensive a book, and I have too
                inconsiderable a public there for <orgName key="macmillan">The Macmillan Company</orgName> 
                to think of issuing an English edition, I think. I have not asked them, but I think it is improbable.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, there is a movement to translate the book into French and have it
                issued in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, but that is so much in the air at present that I do not know whether it will
                amount to anything. I will ask the French publisher to send you a copy, if it should ever come out in
                French.</p>
            <p>There are a lot of Frenchmen here now; we have a number of French officers instructing
                our army, and there are various Frenchmen sent over here on missions of one kind or another. In
                fact, for a hundred years or more there has never been such an influx of foreigners in this
                country. It is doing us a great deal of good, and I think will help to improve the taste in this
                country more than anything else in the world. I find that my “<title key="" level="m">Six French Poets</title>” is universally
                known by these young Frenchmen, which is very gratifying, and they also seem to think it would
                interest their countrymen to be introduced to the modern American poets. They know something
                of the English poets, but nothing of the American.</p>
            <p>I miss you terribly on “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>” and the fact that <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> has got his foot in again fills me
                with horror, particularly as he seems to have got <persName key="">Margaret Anderson</persName> under his thumb and to be
                now practically writing all the articles in “<title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>.” In spite of all this, he has
                absolutely no standing here in America, and is not known at all outside a small circle. I have just
                renewed my subscription to “The Egoist,” although I do not care for it at all when you and Hilda
                do not write for it, but I always hope you will be back there writing again before long, so I
                thought it best to keep subscribing.</p>
            <p>Believe me, dear Richard, no matter how little I write and how much I seem to disappear, I never do, and 
                there is nothing in the world that I wish more to do than to make everybody
                understand what remarkable poets you are – you and Hilda. No matter how many years it may be
                before this war permits us to meet again, nothing in my friendship will ever change – please
                believe that.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb"></note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>