<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-05-10"
                    >May 10, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$206i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of 2 sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. On the
                        top of the first page is “Aldington” written in pencil. On the top right of each page is the date,
                        and on the top left of each one (excluding the first) is R.A. and a page number.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-05-10">May 10, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I sent you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> each two copies of 
                “<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Some Imagist Poets <u>1916</u></title>” by mail
                yesterday. I hope that you will like them. I know just how you will feel about the tribute to
                <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>, and I feel so too. But we have gone over all that before, and
                there is no use weeping over spilt milk.</p>
            <p>What I feel even worse about is that I forgot to put in <persName key="fs_flint">Flint’s</persName> dedication to you in
                front of his poem “<title key="easter" level="a">Easter</title>”. He sent it as an after-thought on a postal card, and, somehow, the
                postal card got mislaid and I never found it until yesterday. I have written to him telling him
                how sorry I was for this stupidity on my part, and saying that I would correct it if the book
                went into a second edition. But I hardly hope for this luck this year, for the reasons that I
                have already told you.</p>
            <p>I enclose the only review we have, which came out on the day of publication last
                Saturday – nominal publication, that is, for, as a matter of fact, the books were not on the
                market until Monday, which is the reason I could not ship any copies to you until yesterday. I
                think it is, on the whole, a very good review, and I think it a very good idea to have put in
                your woodcuts. I did it on purpose, because, as you see from the enclosed advertisement, the
                publishers undertook to feature <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> and me in this first announcement. That was quite a
                national and commercial venture on their part, for our poems are well-known here and these
                particular poems of ours have been much discussed in the papers. But it seemed to me that
                the English side was being rather badly represented. I suppose it is natural that American
                reviewers should pay more attention to American contributors, as the English reviewers do
                the English contributors. But these woodcuts of you and Flint seemed to make the balance
                square – square from the advertising view, that is. I am afraid it is impossible to make the
                American reviewers speak as much about the English side of our book as about the
                American. But that is more than evened up, because the American reviewers do speak
                constantly of the English side, whereas the English reviewers pay almost no attention to the
                American side.</p>
            <p>The advance sales have been about normal. I saw <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Greenslet</persName> yesterday, and he thought
                about <measure quantity="250" commodity="copies">250 copies</measure> had been ordered before publication. 
                He had not heard from <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> yet, but he thought they would take about <measure quantity="100" commodity="copies">100 copies</measure>. 
                You say you know somebody at Constable’s, and as they are printing <title key="seaGarden" level="m">Hilda’s book</title> in the Autumn, perhaps you could get your
                friend to take a real interest and push this a bit. Ferris tells me that they are particularly
                interested in <persName key="conrad_aiken">Aiken’s</persName> <title key="turnsAndMovies" level="m">book</title>; which is amusing, as Aiken’s book is doing nothing on this side
                of the ocean. I am sending you a copy, so that you may see what it is like. Aiken is one of our
                bitterest enemies, and personally I think his book an insincere copy of “<title key="spoonRiver" level="">Spoon River</title>”,
                although I admit that it is clever. But it is such a false picture of life on the vaudeville stage
                that it does not take at all over here.</p>
            <p>I am reviewing <title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">yours</title> and <title key="cadences" level="m">Flint’s</title> books for <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> new “<title key="poetryReviewAmerica" level="j">Poetry Review</title>”. He
                has a backer who is quite well off, and although they are paying very little at present, they
                have a distinct commercial sense. The man is a lawyer and knows the world, and Braithwaite
                has been in journalism too long not to know the ropes of that business. If it falls down it will
                be because of his incurable enthusiasm for everything, and his lack of judgment. But he is the
                only person here who has been steadily and consistently loyal to us, as I have written to you
                several times. The paper is got up entirely without any bias. He intends to print all schools
                and have all poetry review represented in his criticism. This will, of course, frequently irritate
                us, but on the other hand he is most welcoming to our work and will print us with great
                frequency, I think. They printed <measure quantity="4,000" commodity="copies">4,000 copies </measure>of the first number, and it is the only one of the
                poetry magazines which has been taken hold of by the American News Company. This
                company owns all the railroad and subway news stands throughout the entire country, and it
                is a great help to be constantly on sale in that way. I have subscribed to the paper to be sent
                you regularly, and although I think it may often annoy you to tears, I am sure in the end it
                will be a good thing for us to have it succeed.</p>
            <p>Braithwaite’s “<title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Anthology</title>” is already in its fifth thousand, and all these things help us
                all. The more people read poetry, the sooner we shall have discerning people reading it. I
                have just contracted to give a series of four lectures in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> next Winter on
                “Contemporary Poetry”; and, of course, one of the lectures will be devoted to our group. I
                think I shall repeat these lectures in <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> and possibly in 
                <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>. <persName key="ec_marsh">Mr. Marsh</persName>, of the
                <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan Company</orgName>, tells me that he can trace increasing sales in the 
                towns in which I have been speaking.</p>
            <p>I think this volume is a great advance on the last, but I should not wonder if
                Braithwaite were right when he says that reviewers will find it more difficult of
                comprehension. I will send you the reviews, as I did last year.</p>
            <p>I have not heard from you for ages, it seems to me, and I cannot tell you how much I
                miss it when I do not get any letters from you or Hilda.</p>
            <p>Flint has never acknowledged the letter containing the money order for royalties,
                which I sent him in February, and I have written to ask him if he ever received it. Do find out
                and let me know.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
