<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1916-02-05"
                    >Feb. 5, 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$181i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of two sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. There
                        are some areas where words are scratched out with pencil and pencil is added for corrections.
                        There appears to be a watermark on the paper, but it is unreadable under the text.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Your letter of January 18th is here, and your generosity in regard to the matter of my
                poems gave me great pleasure. Neither <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> nor I have any desire to put in things which you
                people do not like and do not want. As I have written you several times, “<title key="turnpike" level="a">Off the Turnpike</title>” is
                definitely out of consideration. My contribution will now run: “<title key="patterns" level="a">Patterns</title>,” 
                “<title key="springDay" level="a">A Spring Day</title>,” and “<title key="stravinsky" level="a">Stravinsky</title>."</p>
            <p>Your feeling about the onomatopoeic lines in the “<title key="stravinsky" level="a">Quartet</title>” is unfortunate, as I am afraid
                I cannot change them and leave the poem the kind of thing it was meant to be. I was
                endeavouring to reproduce not only the movement, but as much as possible the sound, of the
                music; and the wheeze and bumps to which you so strongly object were to give the effect of the
                squealing pipes and the dissonance and jolt of the drums on another key. Read aloud, it does
                have this affect. I suppose it is veristic, if you like, but I am afraid it is quite impossible for me to
                confine myself within the strict Imagist tenets originally set down by <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>. You remember that
                last year, when we severed our connection with Ezra, we decided to become broader, and we
                have certainly done so. In the main, I think Fletcher and I both agree with your interpretation of
                Imagism, but we are both intensely dramatic in our work, and I think both of us are willing to
                sacrifice some of the more astringent Imagistic rules for the sake of vividness and life. I think we
                should, within reason, allow such variations of type, as I am sure it tends to make the movement
                more interesting, not only to the public, but in itself as art, and I feel sure that there is in Imagism
                something very vital and real, which can withstand differences and yet remain itself. But I think
                that your contention that the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> should be kept to the more perfectly Imagistic type, as
                much as we can do so without restraining ourselves too much, is right, and I trust that you will
                forgive me, therefore, if I leave in the onomatopoeic lines, realizing of course that in general
                your contention is just.</p>
            <p><title key="images" level="m">Your book</title> has just come, and I am perfectly delighted with it. I think those coloured wood-cuts 
                that <persName key="harold_monro">Monro</persName> puts on his books are most attractive, and I only wish that I could have a
                book come out in that way. I am afraid I am going to have a very bad time with the “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">French Poets</title>” 
                in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, judging from the snippy notice in the “<title key="times" level="j">Times</title>.” This is not the moment for
                American authors to publish in England. It is too bad that our shilly-shallying Democratic
                government has lost us all our friends in Europe. For those of us who are heart and soul in favour
                of the Allied cause, the situation is not only annoying in the extreme but ludicrous. However, my
                remarks about toleration in one of my letters referred to the necessity of social intercourse, and
                not to my opinion, as I supposed you realized. I only hope you did realize it. I should so much
                regret any misunderstanding on that subject. The country is becoming extremely warlike, and the
                future, I think, will depend entirely on the results of the presidential election.</p>
            <p>I am rather sorry I pitched into you so hard about cutting <persName key="fs_flint">Flint’s</persName> <title key="frenchPoetsReview" level="a">review</title>. I was very
                grateful to you for leaving that out about the champagne, etc., but what did annoy me was your
                feeling obliged to put in a “so far” where Flint said: “These are the best translations of the
                Symbolist poets;” and also, I was sorry that you left out the sentence about the reading of the
                book being El Dorado to anyone who did not know the poets in question. It seemed to me that
                “so far” would be naturally understood in the sentence. Everything one writes must necessarily
                be “so far;” there can never be a final judgment, and to insist upon it I thought was unfortunate.
                Of course, I know that both you and Flint are engaged in French translations. He is doing
                Varhaeren, I think, and I suppose you will have many in your <persName key="remy_gourmont">Remy de Gourmont</persName> book. Then if
                you beat me in translating, well and good. So be it. We can only all do our best, and who beats
                the other does not really matter at all, as we are a group and all working together for the same
                ends.</p>
            <p>To go back to your book, I don’t wonder it sold so many copies. It is appetizing to look
                at, and it is excellent reading. You know what I think of these poems, and in reading the proofs
                of your American edition, I have got to like them even better. I particularly like “<title key="nightPiece" level="a">Night Piece</title>,” as
                I think I wrote you, and I greatly approve of your leaving out the last line; I was not crazy about
                that “posthorn of the coach of romance.” “<title key="evening" level="a">Evening</title>” is awfully good, and your referring to
                Samain in “<title key="atTheBM" level="a">At the British Museum</title>” amused me and pleased me, showing that we were thinking
                of the same things. But what in the name of Patience did you mean by leaving out “<title key="poplar" level="a">The Poplar</title>?”
                Man alive, it is one of your best poems! Monro has been doing a little editing, hasn’t he? I think
                that the American edition, although it won’t be half so attractive, will represent you better than
                this does. I miss your “morsel left half cold on Caesar’s plate,” and I could weep over “The
                Poplar” not being there. However, it is a pleasure to know that the books will not be exactly the
                same, although I think this one is a triumph of book making as well as a very attractive
                collection, only the whole of you is none to much for me.</p>
            <p>I do hope to hear from <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> soon about her poems, in answer to my last letter on the
                subject, and then we can go right to press. We are fearfully late now, and do not forget to cable
                about the Preface.</p>
            <p>There is considerable discussion here about <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="fr">vers libre</foreign></hi> in all the papers. It is understood
                very little, and I think our preface is most important to explain it to the lay reader.</p>
            <p>By way of making things peculiarly awkward, I have just received the poems from
                <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> which he says have been returned to him from Italy. I have not had time to go through
                them yet, but I do not see how we can take them anyway, as there is certainly not time to send
                them over to you, and get your opinion about them. It is a shame we did not get them before, for
                I have no doubt that there are some here that we should like better than “<title key="resurrection" level="a">Resurrection</title>.” But it
                cannot be helped now, I really think; we shall not be out until Autumn if this goes on. He has
                asked me to find a publisher for his poems, and I am to take them in to <persName key="">Ferris Greenslet</persName> on
                Monday. I want him to take them for the Autumn set of the <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">New Poetry Series</title>, if possible.</p>
            <p>It is hard arranging all these things at a distance, and letters are particularly difficult,
                because you write in one mood, and I answer it in that mood, and the chance of its being the
                mood you receive it in are slight. The result is that sometimes you sound cross and depress me,
                and sometimes I undoubtedly sound the same way. We must just forget those things, and put it
                down to the difficulties of distance. I think the new Anthology will be a better book than the last,
                which is something.</p>
            <closer>Lots of love to Hilda.</closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>Here is a little clipping from the “<title key="chicagoTribune" level="j">Chicago Tribune</title>.” I suppose H.D. means
                a skit upon Hilda. I thought you might like to see it. Parodies are one side of success, you know.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>