<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1920-05-29"
                  >May 29, 1920</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="kmp">Katrina Partlow</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="drr">Danielle Nasenbeny</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$315i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc><p>This letter consists of four typed pages on carbon paper. In the upper left corner of the first page is the address line of Richard Aldington. The upper right hand consists of the date line. After the first page, there is a header aligned to the right of the center (Mr. Aldington - [Page #]).</p></physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            &personography;
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc>
  <correspAction type="sent">
   <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName>
   <settlement>LOCATION OF LETTER WRITING</settlement>
   <date>DATE OF LETTER WRITING</date>
</correspAction>
   <correspAction type="received">
  <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
        <div type="letter">
         <opener><dateline><date when="1920-05-29">May 29, 1920</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p>Thank you ever so much for your two letters which I have to answer. I have been
                <rs key="medical" type="theme">pretty ill</rs>, and the worst of it is that my <rs key="medical" type="theme">operation</rs> is not entirely successful. In
                other words, the Fascia has again stretched and we are afraid it will come again, so
                I shall probably be a martyr to this thing the rest of my life. It hardly seems
                worth while to undergo another operation. This is particularly annoying, but it is
                better than having a cancer, or consumption, or any of those things. Perhaps I
                should feel better if it were a disease and not a sort of accident. <!--Possibly tag the doctor-->The doctor tells
                me not to lift anything, and as far as possible to forget it. It makes me a little
                helpess for I cannot walk far, but I am thankful to say that it leaves my capacity
                for work unimpaired.</p>
                <p>What you tell me about <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> is no news to me. That old gossip, <persName key="clement_shorter">Shorter</persName>, had told
                it to me long ago. I quite agree with you that Fletcher is quite childish and
                irresponsible and must be taken as such. I do not like most of his present work,
                with the exception of that one poem in “<title key="coterie" level="j">Coterie</title>” “<title key="londonNightfall" level="a">London Nightfall</title>,” which I think
                is as fine as anything he has ever done. He has appeared over here and is coming to
                see me <date when="1920-05-29">this afternoon</date>. I do not anticipate any real pleasure from the visit because
                whatever he says or does in future I shall know that it is subject to immediate
                change, for I shall consider him an irresponsible person and under the circumstances
                of course one can have but little satisfaction in intercourse with him. As to
                <persName>Cournos</persName> I have always hated that man even when the rest of you liked him, and
                O'Brien I have known for years for what he is, an ignorant little toad.</p>
                <p>I am very glad to know that <persName key="ts_eliot">Eliot</persName> is not responsible for Fletcher's<pb n="02"/> attitude,
                because, although I think Eliot's work is more interesting on the technical side
                than any other, and although I regard him as only a rehash of the <date when="1880">eighties</date>,
                particularly <persName key="jules_laforgue">Jules Laforgue</persName>, nevertheless the man has sincerity, application, and
                energy and a very nice sense of words and feeling for rhythm.</p>
                <p>I have got into a horrid mess lately with Clement Shorter, as I suppose you have
                heard. It seems that <persName key="basil_blackwell">Basil Blackwell</persName>, who is to bring out my “<title key="canGrandesCastle" level="m">Can Grande's Castle</title>,”
                went and asked Shorter to write the preface. Of course I do not know how Shorter is
                regarded in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, but he is such a laughing-stock over here that I could not feel
                he had very much prestige over there. He is an indefatigable gossip and knows
                nothing at all about what we are doing, and although I know he wishes me well, I
                feel that an introduction from his pen would be lamentable. I was therefore obliged
                to request Mr. Blackwell not to have the introduction. By way of making things fifty
                times worse, Mr. Shorter proceeded to very nearly embroil me with Blackwell by
                informing Blackwell that he should issue a collected edition of my works, and
                informing me that I must pay for the same. Considering that <rs key="ww1" type="theme">the war</rs> has left me
                strapped - decidedly strapped - and that I had just spent all my spare cash on an
                old book, and considering also that my contract had been made with Blackwell on a
                royalty basis and I did not want it interfered with, I thought Shorter's action
                unwarrantable and interfering. I am thankful to say that Basil Blackwell turns out
                to be a gentlemanly, reasonable, and understanding chap, and Shorter's undoubtedly
                well meant, but very blundering, interference has not in any way queered our
                relations.</p>
                <p>I wrote Mr. Shorter as tactful a letter as I could telling him I did not wish him to
                write the preface, but I believe him to be distinctly<pb n="03"/> annoyed, all of which is most
                unfortunate but cannot be helped.</p>
                <p>Apropos of Fletcher's letter <date when="1919">last year</date> to Mr. Shorter, I told Mr. Shorter that he
                ought not to have paid any attention to it whatever. He should have torn it up and
                thrown it in the waste-basket. He ought to have known that nothing was reliable that
                came from such a source as Fletcher; but Mr. Shorter truly loves gossip in any form.
                I do not think the old gentleman means any harm, but like many people of his type
                the harm he does is incalculable. I cannot see how the <persName key="winifred_bryher">Ellerman</persName> family can have
                anything to do with him, but then I do not know the Ellermans.</p>
                <p>You tell me that I am to place <title><persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>'s book</title><!--not sure what book this is referencing--> here in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>, but that is the first I
                have heard of it. Neither Winifred nor Hilda have asked me to do anything of the
                kind. I shall be very glad to undertake the job if they want me to, as I have
                written them, but I have heard nothing, in fact, I have not had time as I have only
                just sent off the letter.</p>
                <p>I think you are quite right not to make any arrangements for English publication
                yourself. I am glad you have gone to <persName key="a_knopf">Knopf</persName>, for I think him to be an honest little
                Jew who will really publish you, not really pretend to like <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>. As to the money
                which Brown owes you, I cannot do anything about it without a power of attorney, as
                I have told you before. Brown is simply dishonest to a degree and he has not any
                money.</p>
                <p>I am going to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> on <date when="1920-05-31">Monday</date> and shall see the “<title key="dial" level="j">Dial</title>” people while I am there
                and try to get them to pay you what the old “Dial” owes you. Of course I do not know
                at all on what terms they bought the paper, whether they are responsible for the old
                debts or not, but they are very decent young fellows and I will see what I can do.</p>
                <p>I hardly think you can expect American criticism to be just like French criticism. I
                admit that American criticism at the moment is at<pb n="04"/> very low ebb, but i do not think
                the French method would suit this country at all. It is too long, too meticulous,
                and too dull in the way of expressing itself. I think in looking at us, Richard, you
                must realise that you are dealing with a new people who are evolving their own type
                of literature, and to expect us to be like anybody else at any time is to injure any
                particular excellence we may eventually evolve.</p>
                <p>I am afraid the boys on the “Dial” are not going to be very clever in their
                management of it, however, which is too bad as they are literally the only paper in
                the field, but when I see the little English papers like “Coterie” and “<title key="voices" level="j">Voices</title>,” I
                think we have got a good way beyond those things. They remind me of <date when="1916">six years ago</date>
                over here, and “<title key="littleReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>” at its brightest and grandest.</p>
                <p>It seems to me that many of your poets are copying the very things that we were
                doing some years ago. They are just getting to it. You in England are very good
                technicians, you know more. There are more who know about the art than with us, but
                with the few of us who are at the top here we show a really greater originality on
                the whole, I think.</p>
                <p>I understand that <persName key="vachel_lindsay">Lindsay</persName> is going to descent upon England this year. I hardly think
                that he will make a great success of it, but one never can tell. Many English people
                think we are still in the backwoods stage, and Lindsay appeals to them as being very
                American in that capacity.</p>
                <p>Well, I must stop as I have lots of things to do and no time to do them in before I
                leave. Write soon again.</p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
