<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-05-20"
                    >May 20, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$94i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of 4 sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides. At the top of each sheet
                        (every other page) there is a page number in the center, with the exception of the first page. In
                        several places, there is inserted type between lines. The last page has a piece torn from the side
                        that does not meaningfully interrupt text.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-05-20">May 20, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>Here’s your draft for payment in full, I believe; at least I think it is as full as the cheque
                was. <title key="newRepublic" level="j">They</title> have just sent it to me this morning, and I am hastily getting it off to you. Do not say I
                have not done your business well, for I certainly did slave to get them to pay in the beginning,
                and then, when I had to return the cheque, I sweated blood for fear they would dock it when they
                put it into a draft; but here you are, safe and sound, and don’t make any scruples about taking it.
                It is legally and ethically yours by every possible account.<anchor xml:id="n1"/></p>
            <p>I feel so dreadfully about that number of “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>” that I lie awake at night.<anchor xml:id="n2"/> It is a
                shame that all those good articles should be lost, not really lost, of course, for you have your own
                distribution, but not circulated <add place="above">by us</add>. But I know <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris</persName> is right when he says it would be folly to
                do it. You must try and believe that we do know our public over here, and that you have not any
                real intimacy with them as a public, and we know the way it is likely to jump.</p>
            <p>I haven’t had any answer to my cable sent you yesterday, and when I took the trouble to
                pre-pay it, I think that is a little queer. I don’t want you to write that refutation of <persName key="harold_monro">Monro’s</persName>
                remarks on me. I know you can, out of the very things you said in your review of me. You see,
                as none of the poems in regular metre, which you do not like <add place="above">(at least you don’t like mine)</add>
                appear in the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>, and as you seemed to like all these poems when they were shown to
                you, you ought not to have much difficulty in saying something which shall at once down
                Monro’s sneer and be true to your own principles.</p>
            <p>Yours and <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet’s</persName> correspondence has caused me a little sigh of despair. I think you are
                both wrong.<anchor xml:id="n3"/> I think it is foolish to protest against reviews, although I have just written a letter to
                Monro himself; but I felt at liberty to do so, because he pitched into me about my “<title key="letterFromLondon" level="a">London Letter</title>”
                last Autumn. On general principles, I am sure reviews should always pass unnoticed,
                whether they are good or bad, and she would have a much more efficient way of getting back at
                you by simply never accepting any more of your poems for <title key="poetry" level="j">her magazine</title>. That is what I think
                the majority of editors would do, and it speaks well for Harriet’s singleminded devotion to poetry
                that she prefers to squeal on paper and run the risk of a snub, rather than hurt her magazine by
                refusing your poetry or being unjust to you as a poet. That is pretty fine of her. Of course, I do
                not like her poetry any more than you do, or rather that is not quite fair, I think there were points
                about “The Hotel,” as you said yourself, and there was a dirge about a little nephew of hers who
                died which, if old-fashioned in expression, was extremely sincere in feeling. I am sorry that you
                and Harriet should get at odds, because she does try so hard to make her magazine good; and I
                must say, when you take the whole thing straight from the first issue to the last, as I had occasion
                to do the other day in connection with my talk on modern poets, it is a fact that there is no poet in
                the English-speaking countries of any note whose work has not been printed in her pages. I bet a
                hat that is more than any other magazine can boast.</p>
            <p>I think in everything in this world, even in art, even in business, one should not lose one’s
                sense of the amenities of life. I remember your counseling me this way when <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> wrote that
                terrible letter to Macmillan in the Autumn. I followed your advice and have never regretted it.
                Harriet is a poor woman, with hardly enough money to live upon, on the wrong side of middle
                age. She is lonely and exceedingly unattractive. Her one consolation in life is to believe herself
                talented. It is frightfully pathetic, and is a subject in which Balzac or Maupassant would have
                revelled. Would it hurt you, who are young, vigorous, and have a future before you, to have done
                what we call “letting her down easy”; and would it have done any serious harm to those artistic
                principles in which you believe? I do not think it would have, and I do believe in always
                remembering the good English pugilistic rule that in fighting you must take a fellow of your own
                size. What has struck me so much in my studies of the French poets this winter, is the
                extraordinary courtesy with which they treat each other. I do not think our literary life is
                overflowing with courtesy, and it is a jolly bad thing for our poetry that it is not.</p>
            <p>I think that your contention that Harriet should have written to you, as an editor, through
                the columns of your paper, is (pardon me) ridiculous. We all write personal letters to editors
                which are not meant for publication, and they are never ignored, but always answered again
                privately, as letters between two individuals should be. I see no reason why you should print her
                poem, I think she is foolish to ask you to, and you certainly cannot recant your criticism in your
                own paper, and I think the suggestion that she write to you is a very good one. But I think a little
                air of “<foreign xml:lang="fr">bonhomie</foreign>” strewn over your relations would grease the wheels and do no harm to
                anybody. It is none of my business to give you advice, of course, but since you sent me the
                correspondence, I thought I would tell you how I feel about it.</p>
            <p>I do wish you and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> could come over here this summer, as I cannot get over there.
                Would you consider coming if I could get you a translating job to keep you while you were here?
                <orgName key="bostonMusicCompany">The Boston Music Company</orgName>, one of the branches of the largest publishing firm in America, and
                the people who issued yours and <persName key="walter_rummel">Rummel’s</persName> 
                <title key="tenSongsForChildren" level="m">book</title>,<anchor xml:id="n4"/> have a lot of song translating to do. It is rather
                fussy, because it has to be done to music already written. I have done an awful lot of it, so I
                know its difficulties; but it is not uninteresting work, and they pay <measure type="currency" num="5">$5.00</measure> a poem and up. They
                always have a great lot on hand, and they applied to me for names of people who can do it.
                <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> has just done six poems for them, and I have no doubt I could get you some work of that
                kind, if you care to come over. Then you could stay permanently or not, as you choose. I do
                think a sojourn in America, whether long or short, would be an interesting thing for you, and I
                think you would learn and awful lot about this country which you never suspected. If the idea
                appeals to you, let me know, and I will see what can be done.</p>
            <p>I was sorry about <persName key="michael_sadleir">Sadler’s</persName> books, but please <add place="above">realize that</add> every one of the 150 copies that
                <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> ordered have already been paid for. They own them; we do not. They are marked on
                our list as already sold. I hope that, if they dispose of them all, they will send for some more; and
                I should keep in pretty close touch with Sadler, if I were you. They left here in a freight boat on
                the 16th of April straight to <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, and when they got over, they had to have new title pages put
                in and be bound, so it is not surprising that they did not come before. I know Sadler is thoroughly
                interested in the movement and, if you talk over your various schemes with him, I think you will
                find him willing to cooperate, if you make him think that you are co-partners in a common cause,
                and do not push him.</p>
            <p>They have sent me the revised list from <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> to-day, in which it appears that
                Ferris Greenslet’s original figures were wrong, and that our sale up to date, including the
                advance copies, is 460 copies.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">See <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-05-06">May 6, 1915</date>, about payment for articles contracted but not used by <title key="newRepublic" level="j">The New Republic</title>.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">See <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, May 1915, explaining her decision to buy up and not distribute copies of the “Imagist Number” of <title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>, Vol. 2, No. 5 (May, 1915) in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>.</note> 
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb"><persName key="richard_aldington">Aldington</persName> negatively reviewed <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe’s</persName> You and I (Macmillan, 1914) in <title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title> Vol. 1, No. 24 (<date when="1914-12-15">Decemer 15, 1914</date>) 458-459.</note> 
                <note target="#n4" resp="mb"><persName key="walter_rummel">Walter Morse Rummel</persName> (1887-1953) pianist, composer, and music editor. His Ten Songs for Children (Boston Music Company, 1913) included songs with words by <persName key="hilda_doolittle">H.D.</persName> and <persName key="richard_aldington">Aldington</persName>.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
