<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1917-12-07"
                    >Dec. 7, 1917</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$238i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is five pages long. The word Aldington is written in pencil in the top left at a 
                        forty-five-degree angle slanting upwards from left to right. The date is in the top right along with the
                        page annotation from the second page on (R.A.–[Page #]).</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1917-12-07">Dec. 7, 1917</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>It was perfectly delightful to have a letter from you again. It is so long since I have heard
                from you direct, but <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> is a brick and writes often and keeps me up with things. This war has
                meant to me an exile from some of the people I care for most and from the only people whose
                work I sincerely and unequivocally admire, but that is very little a sacrifice to make considering
                how many more terrible ones other people have to undergo.</p>
            <p>What you say about keeping alive the tradition <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="fr">des libres esprits</foreign></hi> interests me very much. I
                have worried considerably about my part in this war. I have such rotten health that there has
                been no use in thinking of going to <placeName key="france">France</placeName> or doing anything active. I had a very unpleasant
                illness last year, as you know, that pretty nearly wiped me off the face of the earth, and although
                I am very much better, I have almost no endurance physically, and to make things more amusing
                my eyes have given out, and it is with the greatest difficulty that I can get through the work I
                have to do. You would laugh to see me; I am be-spectacled like a German.  All this does not
                matter, of course, except that it seemed almost impossible to do my bit, but I have at last come to
                the comforting conclusion that there is a bit to be done in merely keeping alive the spirit of
                civilization through the only medium I know – that of poetry.</p>
            <p>For us women who cannot fight, and who are handicapped in other ways from taking any
                active part, I feel that the truest thing we can possibly do is just this, and I must say I have been
                happier since I have come to the conclusion. We must keep a world going for the rest of you
                when you come back. We must keep alive the spirit of beauty, of gentleness, and of idealism. It
                may be that the war will go on so long that these things will perish perforce for a time, but the
                whole strength of my mind is now turned towards poetry – not that it always was not so, but the
                thing has taken on a higher meaning and a greater reality, if that were possible, and I think that
                when you come back from the army, the world you will have to work in will be more inclined to
                listen than it ever was before. At least that seems to be coming to be true of <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>, and I have
                the gratifying sense of realizing that my efforts on behalf of poetry in this country are beginning
                to bear fruit at last. I do not at all share with the “<title key="littleReview" level="j">Little Review’s</title>” attitude of “Rough Men.” I
                have never dwelt in an ivory tower, nor found it possible to divorce myself from the facts of life.
                I think there is a great deal more poetry in these sort of people than one realizes, although, of
                course, it is largely an untrained taste. Here we have had a most curious experience. Each of the
                training camps has a library, and they tell me that the demand for poetry in these libraries is
                phenomenal. Of course the kind of poetry is not always what you and I would choose, for they
                like Kipling and Robert Service as well as a lot of other things, but that a lot of private soldiers
                that come from every walk in life should loudly demand poetry is such an extraordinary thing
                that I cannot explain it except by thinking that this country is at last seeking for beauty and an
                expression of the other side of life. I do not think there has ever been a time when common
                soldiers have requested poetry, and the thing seems to me highly significant of the whole attitude
                which this country has towards the war.</p>
            <p>Nobody can hate war worse than I do, but I believe in this war with my whole heart and
                soul, in the absolute necessity of it – melancholy though that is.</p>
            <p>The Brookline Public Library has asked for donations of books to send to the various
                camps, and at their request I am sending six libraries of poetry, chosen by myself, and if these
                are successful and they want more, I stand ready to supply them. Of course there has been much
                poetry already given to the soldiers, but they still want more, and by choosing the libraries
                myself, I can give them what I think they ought to have, peptonizing it with a judicious mixture
                of what they probably want. Of course I am including “<title key="imagesOldAndNew" level="m">Images</title>” and “<title key="seaGarden" level="m">Sea Garden</title>” in all these
                libraries.</p>
            <p>Do not let your spirits go down, and do not think that because you are not writing at the
                moment it means anything for the future. I am quite certain that when the war is over and you get
                back to civil life, you will find that the experience has done you good, and the contact with
                rough, real life and simple, elementary men has been an advantage rather than a disadvantage. Of
                course you may say it is all very well for me to talk this way who am not in it, and perhaps that is
                true, but still I think if I had the health, I could stand the rest of it. However, that is only
                conjecture, and perhaps I could not. Never mind.</p>
            <p>Your account of your life is exactly what I wanted, only I should like a little account of
                your entering the army, and your rise from private to officer. I know this is immaterial to you,
                but I think it shows your character, and, as you can see from “<title key="tendencies" level="m">Tendencies</title>,” I like every little
                thing that tends to illustrate the character of my poets.</p>
            <p>I do not wonder you feel grateful to <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra Pound</persName>. In spite of his having treated me very
                badly, I feel grateful to him too, and he is now writing me conciliatory letters. I wish I did not
                know that he thinks I have made a success and does not want to be on bad terms with me.
                However, that is Ezra all over, and I have answered him shortly and pleasantly. I will not publish
                in “The Little Review,” which is given over to him and his satellites, but I bear him no ill will,
                and I think he has written fine poetry – very fine poetry. My objection to his work is that it is
                simply derivative. I do not think the man has an original thought or an original characteristic, but
                he is extraordinarily skillful in adopting the characteristics of a remote past, and when people do
                not know the past very well, this passes for originality. He has played his cards so badly that he
                is little better than a failure, which is unjust to him. But if only plays poetry like politics, one
                must expect to be treated like a politician. I do not believe people succeed, in the long run, who
                do not take poetry as religion.</p>
            <p>There is a great deal of interest in your work over here, and it is considered very highly. I
                shall undoubtedly take these lectures and make certain chapters of a new book later on.</p>
            <p>“Tendencies” is doing very well, and seems to be having quite an influence. You will see
                with amusement how much afraid of this influence <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName> is, and how she fears that her
                own judgments will go to the wall in face of mine. I have seldom read anything more shivering
                with fear than her review of the book in December “<title key="poetry" level="j">Poetry</title>.”<anchor xml:id="n1"/></p>
            <p>I cannot escape the war now; I must write about it. It seems to be all round us, and I must
                say I think the few poems of yours which I have seen, dealing with the war, are excellent. Do not
                despise the war as a theme for poetry; do not despise any fact of life in that connection. Poetry
                should be the great underlying substance of every poet’s life, and none of his experiences can be
                alien to it when seen through his eyes. I am afraid this sounds a little didactic. That is the worst
                of the war. It brings one down to one’s bottom, and when one talks about the bottom, one always
                sounds goody-goody. Anyhow, I mean it.</p>
            <closer><p>With lots of love and thanks for your good letter,</p>
                <p>Affectionately yours,</p></closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Harriet Monroe, "Miss Lowell on Tendencies," Poetry, Vol. 11, No. 3 (December, 1917), pp. 151-156.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>