<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-10-13"
                    >Oct. 13, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$129i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>[The letter consists of five sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of the first four
                        and on one side of the fifth. The first sheet has a hole punched at the bottom near the center, but
                        the last four have the same size hole punched on the top instead. On the first page, a small
                        amount of text is cut off on the left side but it does not interrupt the comprehension of the letter.
                        At the top of each sheet (every other page) except the first, there is a hand-written page number
                        in the center top.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-10-13">Oct. 13, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>My dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I received two very nice letters from you and the first pamphlet of the translations, just
                before I left <placeName key="dublinNewHampshire">Dublin</placeName>. This one is in no sense to be an answer to those letters. That must wait. It is
                just a little business letter, written off in a hurry, because I am so frightfully busy. I am on the
                final proof of the “<title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">Six French Poets</title>.” and the publishers put “Rush” on every set of proofs they
                send me. I am so sick of tracking mistakes down long pages of print that I do not know what to
                do, but the 132 translations are done, thank goodness, and it is only a case of rushing to get
                everything off my hands. To my intense astonishment <persName key="harold_macmillan">Mr. Macmillan</persName> in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> has bought one
                hundred copies. Why, I cannot imagine, as I did not suppose his experience with “<title key="swordBlades" level="m">Sword Blades</title>”
                had endeared me to him. But such is the fact, and I only hope the poor man will be justified.</p>
            <p>I have not heard a word from you as to whether or not you liked my article on you in the
                September <hi rend="underline"><title key="littleReview" level="j">Little Review</title></hi>.<anchor xml:id="n1"/> I do hope you did, because I only said what I believed to be the
                absolute truth, but still there are such a lot of knocks on this business, and so little comfort, 
                that I should like a lot to feel that I had given you a momentary pleasure.</p>
            <p>I have just taken upon myself to give <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> permission to include a couple of
                <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> poems which appeared in our <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> 
                in his “<title key="magazineVerse" level="m">Anthology of American Magazine Verse</title>.” 
                I suspect you won’t like the book, because Braithwaite is no great shakes as to
                judgement, and to my mind his past Anthologies (it is an annual affair) have been beneath
                contempt. But he is anxious to learn, and very enthusiastic, and I think I have had considerable
                influence on him during this last year, though not nearly as much as I wish I had. One has to go
                slowly and tactfully in trying to affect a person’s ideas, and he had not the education to be
                affected very far. All of this is for your private consumption – yours and Hilda’s – and please do
                not pass it on, even to <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, for the man has been as white as snow to me, and has helped us a
                good deal. There is one advantage about his Anthology – it sells enormously. All the schools buy
                it, and the sale runs up into 5000 or 6000 somewhere. I will send you a copy of this one as soon
                as it comes out. I knew he could not have you, as you are an English-man, so I thought it would
                be all right to give him permission for Hilda’s things. Nobody ever refuses permission to
                anything, because it is a wonderful way to get before the public. Now here is the difficulty as far
                as I am concerned. You say you would like to have “<title key="patterns" level="a">Patterns</title>” in our new <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title>, but to my
                intense astonishment Braithwaite has informed me that he has taken “Patterns” for his
                Anthology. Of course, it being in his Anthology does not in the least preclude it from being in
                ours, but the only thing is, the public may get tired of seeing the same poem repeated too many
                times. I should have much preferred to have had it in our Anthology, but Braithwaite had it all in
                print before he asked my permission, saying with a sweet smile that he knew I would not refuse
                him.</p>
            <p><persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> is at the moment in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, and he expects to be <placeName key="boston">here</placeName> by about the middle of
                November. As soon as he comes, he and I will go over our poems together, and send you over
                some things to choose from, and then you can turn down what you don’t like, and so we can
                gradually get to a position where we are all pleased. Fletcher and I will mark those we send,
                naming them first, second and third choice, and then if you turn down the first and pitch on the
                second, we will take the second, and so on, or you can mix them round differently. I suggest that
                you do this with yours in England. You collect Hilda’s, Flint’s and <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence’s</persName> and your own,
                and arrange them in what you think is the best way. Arrange them in the order of your choice,
                and then send them over to us to agree upon. For above all things, we must keep, on both sides,
                the democratic freedom of our Anthology. We must all be pleased with the arrangement as we
                were last year. I will be spokesman for the American group, Fletcher and myself, and you be
                spokesman for the English group, and then you and I will only have to deal with each other.</p>
            <p>It is very generous of you, dear Richard, to offer to have the Anthology turned round and
                go backward, for the sake of giving me first and you last, but I think that would be a mistake,
                grateful as I am for the suggestion. I am sure that the best way is to keep our alphabetical order.
                It gives you a little advantage, I admit, but I think that is the only fair way to do. Whatever
                advantage you get comes from the accident of having a name beginning with “A”, whereas if we
                went turn and turn about, the people in the middle might complain that they never had a chance
                to be first, and they would certainly complain with reason, and to have a different order each
                time seems unnecessarily laborious.</p>
            <p>I have been trying to get hold of <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>, and get at the two poems for our Anthology, but
                he has taken out his telephone and I have not been able to get in town yet, but I hope to round
                him up this week.</p>
            <p>Now as to your suggestion that we print one poem each of a few of the younger people, I
                am very much averse to any such suggestion, and I think I am quoting Fletcher correctly when I
                say that he is too. Unless there is someone whom it is evident would add greatly to our value if
                included in the Anthology, I see no advantage in adding anyone to our little group. If we are any
                good as a group our influence is sure to widen, and to include every young aspirant who has been
                at all affected by our point of view would make our Anthology unnecessarily jejune. You say
                yourself that none of the people you know, <persName key="clara_shanafelt">Clara Shanafelt</persName>, <persName key="marianne_moore">Marianne Moore</persName>, etc., have seven
                poems good enough to put in the Anthology. Now a poet who has not seven good poems is still
                only a tyro. I think as our contract was only for three years, it would be much better for us to stay
                just as we are for 1916 and 1917. We shall confuse the public less that way, and we are more
                certain to stay as a group and not be confused with the <persName key="guido_bruno">Brunos</persName> 
                and <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Kreymborgs</persName>, who, 
                hard-working and energetic young men as they are, hardly seem exactly of our way of thinking.</p>
            <p>By the way, I see that you are to have some poems in November “<title key="others" level="j">Others</title>.” I think the
                best think Kreymborg has published in that paper is <persName key="wallace_stevens">Stevens’s</persName> “<title key="peterQuince" level="a"></title>Peter Quince,” but Fletcher
                writes that he has seen other things of Stevens’s, and they are not any good. This does not at all
                mean I think Stevens belongs in our group, but merely as a remark. All of which means that if
                you have no great objection, it would be better for the next two years, while our present contract
                lasts, for us to keep simply the six of us together who were in the Anthology last year.</p>
            <p>By the way, if you see Lawrence, tell him that I am sending him his money order. He
                changed his address, and I was afraid to send it in the dark, and just as I was on the eve of
                sending it to you I got a letter from him, and it should reach him very soon, but if you mention
                having received royalties and he has not got any, he may think I am trying to keep him without
                any.</p>
            <p>If you are really very anxious to include some of the younger people in the Anthology,
                why, we might talk it over some more, but I think it would [be] a little better not to.</p>
            <p>I have just heard of the death of <persName key="remy_gourmont">Remy de Gourmont</persName>, which must be a dreadful blow to
                you. I am extremely sorry, and I am afraid he must have suffered terribly before his death. He
                was so kind to me in sending me his picture for the book, with such pleasant words of
                encouragement, and one of the things I was looking forward to was sending it to him. I feel we
                have all lost our best friend, and find myself feeling a very personal loss, although I never saw
                him.</p>
            <p>I enclose money order to pay for my <title key="poetsTranslationSeries" level="m">ten sets of the translations</title>. I like them so much, and
                am giving them round to various people. I am going to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> as soon as I have finished my
                book, and am going to see if I can get <persName key="laurence_gomme">Gomme</persName> to take them on and sell them for you.</p>
            <p>Love to Hilda.</p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Amy Lowell, "Richard Aldington's Poetry," The Little Review, September, 1915 (Vol. 2, No. 6), 11-16.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>

