<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>, <date when="1915-05-19"
                    >May 19, 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sl">Sam Lepak</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425540184$83i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>The letter consists of 6 sheets of paper with typewriting on both sides of each. At the top of each
                        new sheet (every other page) there is a page number in the center. In some places there are lines
                        crossed out and replaced with pencil marks.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-05-19">May 19, 1915.</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I am afraid you are going to be awfully disappointed but, after careful consideration,
                <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName>, <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>, and 
                I thought it would be a mistake for us to distribute this number of
                “<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>” over here.<anchor xml:id="n1"/> There are three reasons for this.</p>
            <p>In the first place, <persName key="dora_marsden">Dora Marsden’s</persName> being on the front page makes it extremely doubtful
                whether anyone seeing the paper would care to buy it.<anchor xml:id="n2"/> To advertise it and attempt to sell it as an
                Imagist number when the most prominent thing in the paper is Dora Marsden’s is almost certain
                to wreck it in the American market.</p>
            <p>The next reason is that <persName key="harold_monro">Harold Monro’s</persName> article is distinctly unfavorable, and pitches into
                us all and the movement in general with the most delightful impartiality.<anchor xml:id="n3"/> I think much that he
                says is good; but clearly for anyone who does not know our work to read it will go far towards
                prejudicing them against the book at the start. Now for us to take pains to distribute a hostile
                criticism is excessively poor business. We shall get hostile enough criticism as it is – hostile,
                futile, and silly – as you must have seen by the clippings I am sending you. We need someone to
                tell the world what we are trying to do, even if they cannot say we have already done it. And for
                us to take special pains to distribute an article to tell the world of what little value we are would
                certainly be a silly thing. Ferris Greenslet who knows the book buying condition over here from
                A to Z, is firm that it would be a mistake to distribute this number. I think, Richard, that
                sometimes in your anxiety to be quite fair, you stand up so straight that you fall over backwards.
                One may not do anything to force pleasant criticism nor to prevent hostile; but in our own paper,
                our own organ, if I may call it so, to publish a distinctly hostile article in a number which was
                presumably got up to make our work better known, is hardly necessary, and you can see yourself
                that it is a distinctly bad business proposition.</p>
            <p>The third reason, and to my mind the most cogent of the lot, is <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence’s</persName> poem, which I
                think for pure, farfetched indecency beats anything I have ever seen.<anchor xml:id="n4"/> Unfortunately these things
                are very quickly remarked on over here. Two years ago “<title key="international" level="j">The International</title>” had a cover which I
                considered perfectly harmless, but they were sued for sending indecent matter through the mails.
                Now I do not believe there will be prominence enough given to this poem of Lawrence’s for us
                to be sued, although there might be: the Watch and Ward Society is very active; but it would do
                us immeasurable, incalculable harm to be associated with such an outpouring. I know you did
                not like the poem, because you said so, but I wish you had told him frankly that it simply could
                not be printed in our number, and that he must either substitute something else or go
                unrepresented. You know how careful we were what we printed in the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Anthology</title> of his. He 
                loses his eye about things; sometimes I think his condition is almost pathological, and that he has
                a sort of erotic mania.</p>
            <p>Now I knew how hard you worked over this Imagist number, and I know that you will go round cussing the 
                stupidity of Americans at not being able to see the value of our book through a
                hostile criticism, or make allowances for Lawrence’s poem, or brush away Dora Marsden as if
                she were an intruding fly. But you must not forget, Richard, that in working with people we have
                to take them as they are, not as they should be. It is not fair to publishers to injure the sale of the
                book because, although I have paid for the printing, they have a part interest in the
                recipients as they are handling it. The publication of “<title key="spoonRiver" level="m">Spoon River</title>” and <persName key="robert_frost">Frost’s</persName> books at the
                same time as our Anthology has rather injured our sale, and we must not be party to anything
                that will injure it more.</p>
            <p>They told me at <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin’s</orgName> that we have sold in all 415 copies up to date. That is
                very peculiar as a little while ago they told me that the advance sale amounted to 481 copies.<anchor xml:id="n5"/>
                They are now verifying the two reports, and I hope they will find that the first figure they gave
                me was correct. You will see that the sale is neither very bad nor very good. But there is an
                immense amount of hostility and flippancy which we have to contend against. <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra’s</persName>
                lucubrations have done us an immense amount of harm; I do not mean now, but all his writings
                in the past, so that not only Imagism, but free verse in general is having a hard time, unless it is
                so done as to be quite popular. They take “Spoon River” because they can understand it; and they
                are quite right to take “Spoon River,” it is one of the greatest novels ever written and is worthy to
                rank with Dovstoysky[sic]. <persName key="el_masters">Masters’s</persName> free verse <del rend="strikethrough">I say</del> they will take for the sake of the subject
                matter; but ours is a very different thing. It would have been better for the sale, had I taken the
                liberty to advertise myself and “<title key="bombardment" level="a">The Bombardment</title>” in it, because I am fairly well known over
                here now and my own book has sold remarkably well; but it seemed to me that would be pushing
                myself up above the crowd, so I have carefully refrained from mentioning my name. I think the
                book will do fairly well, though I very much doubt whether its sale will be brilliant. But it is so
                much touch and go, that you can easily see yourself that we must do nothing to weigh down the
                balance on the wrong side.</p>
            <p>This is plain business, Richard, and you must not object if it clashes with your principles
                of fairness. The man who repeats all the disagreeable things people say about him to every new-comer, 
                for the sake of being fair, I think you will admit is but a fool. To distribute this Imagist
                number would be to be like such a man. I think perhaps you put the importance of criticism
                higher than I do. I have personally never received the slightest hint which was of any value to me
                in a printed article. Reviews seem to me much more in the nature of advertisements than
                anything else. Of course, some people’s opinions are of value – yours are, I think mine are, and
                Greenslet’s and possibly <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer’s</persName> – but the great mass of reviews are only important to the
                author or publisher because they make people talk about, and buy, the book reviewed.</p>
            <p>I do not want to do anything that is the least unfair to anyone and, although I regret the
                loss of all those single reviews of our work, and regret the suppression of the poems, except
                Lawrence’s, particularly as I gave you what I considered my very best, Fletcher, Greenslet and I
                do not think we can, in fairness to ourselves or to you, be a party to any distribution of it. I don’t
                want you to get a mess with <persName key="harriet_weaver">Miss Weaver</persName> or to have Miss Weaver think that I am impuning your
                judgment, and in my letter to her I am merely stating that the presence of Dora Marsden in the
                front pages has diminished the value of the number so greatly that we do not feel it would be
                wise for us to distribute it; and in order that there may be no hard feeling of any kind, I am
                sending her a cheque of fifteen dollars, the price she said she should charge the publishers as
                commission. I have not told her anything at all about my objections to Monro’s article or
                Lawrence’s poem, merely basing my objection upon Dora Marsden’s prominence.
                This method should, I think, prevent her having any feeling against you.</p>
            <p>If you understood conditions in America better, you would see that we are only doing the
                sensible thing, and our disappointment is no more keen than mine. I could not sleep
                all night the night after “The Egoist arrived, I felt so terribly about it.</p>
            <p>I have ordered <persName key="michael_sadler">Sadler</persName><anchor xml:id="n6"/> to send you ten copies at once to distribute to your various
                reviewers. I got Houghton Mifflin to cable with their private code, and copies should have
                reached you by now.</p>
            <p>I have been able to give us quite a little sendoff through various talks I have been giving
                here: one before the <orgName key="poetsClub">Poetry Society</orgName>, which I think I wrote you about, one before the 
                <orgName key="roundTableClub">Round Table Club</orgName>, and the other before the graduating class 
                of the English Department of <placeName key="wellesley_college">Wellesley College</placeName>,
                one of the largest women’s colleges here. I think time and our own efforts will land us where we
                wish to be. But we must be awfully careful to persuade the public that we are serious, high
                minded, and hard-working people, and not cranks. The most important thing for us is to have a
                strong “esprit de corps,” and to think the success of one member is an honour to all. In a letter I
                received from <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> yesterday, I perceived that he was not very delighted with Fletcher’s article 
                on me in “Poetry,” and I have written to him saying to him exactly what I am now saying to you,
                that “esprit de corps” is necessary for any people who are working together for the good of all.</p>
            <p>Thank <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> for her nice letter, and try not to be too disappointed. After all, nobody will
                know, because these papers have never been on sale <add place="above">before</add> in the shops to which I recommended
                them, <del rend="strikethrough">before</del> and the shops won’t know, because they have already forgotten about my
                suggestion. Your paper will go out through the usual channels among the people who will
                understand it. It is only that we will not try to stimulate an artificial sale among a different kind
                of public.</p>
            <closer>Very affectionately,</closer>
            <postscript>
                <label>P.S.</label>
                <p>Your letter and postal of the 6th and 7th of May have just come. I am delighted that <persName key="remy_gourmont">Remy de Gourmont</persName> 
                    has written about us in “<title key="laFrance" level="j">La France</title>,” and I am very glad that somebody is defending us
                    from Monro’s article.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <back> 
            <div type="notes"> 
                <note target="#n1" resp="mb">Lowell paid for and kept all copies of the May, 1915 “Special Imagist Number” of The Egoist (Vol. 2, No. 4) sent for distribution in America.</note> 
                <note target="#n2" resp="mb">Dora Marsden’s five page editorial “Truth and Reality,” about subjective and objective reality, begins the issue (65-70).</note> 
                <note target="#n3" resp="mb">Harold Monro, “The Imagists Discussed,” The Egoist, Vol. 2, No. 4 (May, 1915), 77-80.</note> 
                <note target="#n4" resp="mb">Lawrence’s war poem, “Eloi, Eloi, Lama Sabachthani.” Lowell might object to his comparison of the moment when a soldier kills an enemy combatant to sexual intercourse: “And I knew he wanted it. / Like a bride he took my bayonet, wanting it, . . . I have sown him with the seed / And planted and fertilized him” (75).</note> 
                <note target="#n5" resp="mb">See AL to RA, April 24, 1915.</note> 
                <note target="#n6" resp="mb">Michael Sadler (née Sadlier) (1888-1957), British writer, translator and publisher. Lowell references him in his role at Constable & Co. publishing firm.</note> 
            </div> 
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>