<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="file:/Users/amadacastillo/margaretandersonletters/ALLP_ODD-6.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> <!-- Change href to your RNG file location locally -->
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName>, <date when="1914-09-10"
                  >September 10, 1914 </date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ah">Alin Haberle</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ama">Amada Castillo</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ama">Amada Castillo</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425543136$1i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc><p>The letter is four pages long. It is typed on plain paper. The words “Little Review” are written in pencil at the top.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            &personography;
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc>
  <correspAction type=”sent”>
   <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
   <settlement>LOCATION OF LETTER WRITING</settlement>
   <date>September 10, 1914</date>
</correspAction>
   <correspAction type=”received”>
  <persName>Margaret Anderson</persName>
</correspAction>
</correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener><dateline><date when="1914-09-10">September 10,1914</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear<persName key="margaret_anderson">Miss Anderson,</persName></salute>
            </opener>
         <p>I have received the<date when="1914-09">September</date> number of the <title key="littleReview" level="j">Little Review,</title> and am very glad to see that you printed my two poems in it. I am awfully sorry that you did not get the <title key="letterFromLondon" level="a">“London Letter”</title> in time to put it in, as you advertised it to appear, but it was quite out of the question for me to get it off to you any sooner. The conditions prevailing those first weeks in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> were not only absolutely against the possibility of writing, but also I literally had not the time to give to it in the press of other and more urgent duties. I got off the letter to you, however, before I sailed for home, and I think that by this time you must have received it.</p>
         <p>There are two corrections I should like to make in that article. One is the spelling of the name <persName key="henri_regnault">Henri Regnault</persName>,<!--Henri Regnault is not in personography yet - proposed addition 3/31/25 AC--> which I know I spelled wrong, and alas I should like to put a star in the footnote after the passage where I say that the English <gap><desc>there are lines missing in between the pages</desc></gap> 
         <pb n="2">
         condition has materially changed since the time of writing.</p>
         <p>Will you be so kind as to send me a proof of the article?</p>
         <p>Three typographical mistakes in the two poems which you printed this month make it most imperative that I should read my own proofs. Indeed it is a thing I always insist upon where it is possible. In <title level="a">“Clear, With Light Variable Winds,”</title><!--Also not in site index yet - proposed 3/31/25 AC--> you have changed the order of two of my words. In the line, <quote type="english">“Am I not more worth than your day ladies”</quote> your version reads, <quote type="english">“Am I not worth more,”</quote> which is somewhat of a change in meaning, and certainly a very great change in the style. Also, after the <quote type="english">“Gemmed with the moon,”</quote> there should have been a stanza space which is missing here, and may I suggest that <quote type="english">“veil”</quote> is not usually spelled <quote type="english">“vail?”</quote> Nobody knows better than I the woes of proof reading, and therefore I am all indulgence to any errors that may occur, but I must say it is more satisfactory to feel one has committed the blunders oneself, if they must be committed.</p>
         <p>May I ask you to send me one copy of the <date when="1914-08">August</date> number of the Little Review. The copy 
         <pb n="3">
         <choice><orig>Which</orig><reg>which</reg></choice> you so kindly sent me to <placeName key="england">England,</placeName> and which I read with so much pleasure, and was most grateful for your kind mention of my poem in the <title key="anthologyDesImagistes" level="m">Imagistes Anthology</title>, was <choice><orig>siezed</orig><reg>seized</reg></choice> upon by <persName key="richard_aldington"><choice><orig>Richard Adlington</orig><reg>Richard Aldington</reg></choice></persName>, as he was so delighted with your mention of the <orgName key="imagists">Imagistes</orgName> and of him, and he wished to send it to his father. He assured me that I should have it back promptly, and that is the last I have seen of it.</p>
         <p>May I make a criticism, a very friendly one, and which seems to me should be made by somebody? Namely, I do not think you should have quoted <persName key="fs_flint">Flint’s</persName> <title key="theSwan" level="a">“Swan”</title><!--proposed 3/31/25 AC--> in your <date when="1914-08">August</date>number quite the way you did. You did not acknowledge the fact that it had appeared first both in <title key="poetry" level ="j">“Poetry,”</title> and in the Imagistes Anthology, and it looked as if it were appearing for the first time in your magazine as a regular contribution. That, of course, was not quite fair to the other volumes it had appeared in, and Mr. Flint was quite incensed at your putting in no acknowledgements about it, and of course you <gap><desc>sentence missing between the pages</desc></gap> 
         <pb n="4">
         time to sue you. Of course Mr. Flint was much pleased at your quoting him, but I think one should try to be on the right legal side in questions of that kind. Forgive this criticism from a well-wisher, and please let me have the proof of the London Letter without delay.</p>
         <p>I am, as you see, at my home in <placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName>, where everything in the future should be sent. Did I tell you that I have asked Messrs.<orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan and Company</orgName> to be so kind as to advertise my new <title key="swordBladesAndPoppySeed" level="m">book</title> in your magazine? I know that all advertisements help, and think also that your audience will probably be a friendly one to me.</p>
         <closer>Yours truly,</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>