<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-01-12">12 January 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$6i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Seven pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-01-12">January 12, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Your letter with the poems came safely a few days ago. You have certainly improved
            enormously. Your poems are splendidly strong now, and seem to me to lose nothing of
            their perfection with the added vigour. Both <persName key="john_fletcher"
               >Fletcher</persName> and I are perfectly delighted with them. The only trouble with
            this batch which you have sent us is that it oversteps our limits of space. As far as we
            are concerned, we should like to have them all in, but the publishers do not think it
            possible to print a larger book than we had last year in that series, for the price at
            which that series is issued; and as in signing the contract the <title
               key="some_imagist_poets">Anthologies</title> were supposed to be a part of their
               <title key="newPoetrySeries">New Poetry Series</title>, I am afraid we must keep to
            our original plan.</p>
         <p>You remember that our rule last year was that we should each have a space which was
            about equal, and to make it as near as possible, we agreed to have either seven short
            poems apiece, or two very long poems, or one moderately long and five short. And I think
            we might continue on that plan and say two moderately long and three short.</p>
         <p>Now as far as my work is concerned, I was suggesting two long poems, as in the last two
            Anthologies I was represented by short poems. I quite understand your objections about
            "Off the Turnpike," and <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> thinks that
            it would not go well with the other poems in the Anthology anyway, so I willingly
            withdraw that poem from consideration, as I wrote <persName key="richard_aldington"
               >Richard</persName> the other day.</p>
         <p>I sent you a batch of my own poems to choose from about ten days ago. But what Fletcher
            and I really think would be best for my contribution, if you agree, is "A Spring Day,"
            "Patterns," and "In a Time of Dearth." You asked me to send some short poems, and I did
            so, but I wrote with a </pb>view to their being printed in "<title key="egoist">The
               Egoist</title>," not in the Anthology. I am very anxious not to appear with short
            poems in this Anthology, and I hope you will let me have my way in this. I take back my
            objection to "Patterns" because the poem has met with a better reception than anything I
            have ever done, and an amusing part of it is that it has even been parodied (a vicarious
            kind of fame) in a <placeName key="sanDiego">San Diego</placeName> newspaper, which
            shows that it has wandered far afield. Fletcher is also anxious to have it included, and
            I think these three moderately long poems of mine should make up my contribution.</p>
         <p>Now to go back to yourself. You have here three short poems and four moderately long
            ones. The long ones are not as long as the three I propose to put in of my own. But
            still, if you put them in with the short ones, both Fletcher and I think that it will be
            rather more than we bargained for, as they are in several sections each. And of course,
            if you think mine are too long, why let us leave out "In a Time of Dearth" and put in
            simply "A Spring Day" and "Patterns."</pb> Of course, new titles is what takes up space,
            because each title requires a separate page. But the pages of the Anthology print rather
            less than our pages do. Roughly speaking, we have thirty lines to a page, and the
            Anthology has twenty-four. We think, therefore, that if you put in "The Shrine," "The
            Temple," "Sea Gods," and either "The Contest" or the three short ones, it would be about
            the right amount. Personally we prefer the three short ones to "The Contest." I should
            suggest therefore beginning with "Sea Gods," with "The Shrine" next, then "The Temple,"
            and then the three short ones in the order in which you have them here: "Moonrise,"
            "Huntress," and "Mid-day." But if you have a very definite feeling that you prefer "The
            Contest" to those three, why of course it shall be as you wish. Please let me know as
            soon as possible as every minute counts. And please also let me know if you approve of
            "A Spring Day," "Patterns," and "In a Time of Dearth" for me, or if you prefer simply to
            have me put in "A Spring Day" and "Patterns." One reason why I think "Patterns had
            better go into the Anthology is because it also refers to the War, although I have put
            it back in another war. Still this condition would be the same at all times.</p>
         <p>Now as regards Richard’s poems, of course, if you feel that "Whitechapel" is very
            important, we will include it. I do not think we should exclude each other’s poems
            except for reasons other than personal taste. And although I still feel "Whitechapel" to
            be less important than you do, still I quite understand why Richard wants it, and I get
            his symbolism absolutely. However, we will consider that in. We still feel, however,
            that <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>’s "Evil" is out of key, and if you could
            induce him to put in something else instead of it, Fletcher and I would be very
            grateful. I also understand why Richard wants the order he has here, and perhaps from
            the point of view of the War, it is the best order. I am naturally sorry not to have
            "Eros and Psyche" open the book, as "Eros and Psyche" is the most considerable poem, and
            publishers always say that poems which open a book are half the battle. But we are quite
            willing to leave these in Richard’s order if he prefers. With my contribution, I should
            begin with "A Spring Day" and end with "In a Time of Dearth," because the poems read
            better in this order; but if you prefer to end on a note of war, "In a Time of Dearth"
            and "Patterns" can be changed and "Patterns" finish the book.</p>
         <p>Fletcher’s preface was quite out of the question, not in matter but in manner. It was so
            violent and militant, and I think we have got through the phase where it is necessary to
            gird at critics. With his permission I am rewriting it, using much that he says but
            putting it in a more conciliatory form. I think we must now take a stand upon our
            principles quietly and without bitterness. We have done very well, we have made</pb>
            considerable impression. I was amused at a friend of mine here<!--should this person be tagged? I'm not sure who AL is referring to here-->, who has always written
            children’s poems in a perfect metrical style and who a year ago was utterly down on our
            type of poetry. She has now taken to writing vers libre, which is not by any means good
            enough to count yet, but it shows that the wind is blowing in the right direction.</p>
         <p>Now I want to prepare you and Richard for a fact which I fear is about to happen. I do
            not think that this new Anthology will create as much stir as the last one did, for
            although most of our critics were hostile, nevertheless there was a great deal of space
            given to us and our theories. Now we have come to that critical moment in the career of
            every poet when he ceases to be interesting principally because he is new, when his
            theories have become sufficiently digested to no longer pique heavy jokes and violent
            opposition, when he is taken for granted as a poet, and his work must justify itself
            slowly and without flamboyancy. I believe every artist, every school of artists, must go
            through this period before they reach a fame which is unquestioned, which fame really
            comes before the artist’s death. It is just this long, arid stretch, when people appear
            to be indifferent, when the artist must work without much encouragement, even the caviar
            encouragement of publicity, which kills so many promising young people. I think that we,
            as <orgName key="imagists">Imagists</orgName>, and we, as individuals, are entering on this stage, and I have no doubt we
            shall miss the discussion. We cannot miss the praise, because we have had very little,
            but we shall miss the interest and the antagonism that we have enjoyed. I have very
            little hope of this Anthology’s selling as well as the last, although the work in it is
            clearly better. I am delighted with it as a volume, and I am more and more sure that the
            work will live, some of it at any rate. But I know that we are all going to feel a
            let-down this year, and I want to warn you of that, so that you may be prepared for it
            when it comes. Fletcher and I have talked this over, and we agree absolutely. As Richard
            says, it is the slow and gradually increasing seriousness with which our work is taken
            which makes for fame.</pb> And this is true in both <placeName key="england">England</placeName> and <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>, but America has less
            real artistic knowledge than England and dearly loves a novelty. It is in America that
            we have made the most impression, but it is America that is going to pay the least
            attention to us as the years go on. I think that our Anthologies have done us a great
            deal of good, and I am thankful that our idea of publishing together for several years
            has been justified, as I feel it has been abundantly. Whether or not it would be
            feasible to keep up the Anthology after our three years I do not know, but that we are
            vey much more seriously regarded and in a better position than we were a year and a half
            ago is incontestable.</p>
         <p>Fletcher and I went over another batch of his poems on Sunday, and he was to send you
            some which we thought would do for the Anthology. His new book has knocked out our
            calculations, as we wrote you; but personally I think the <placeName key="arizona">Arizona</placeName> poems and the Old
            South are a far better group for him than these long ones that he has just sent you. Not
            that the new ones are not good, but they are more like his other work and do not fairly
            represent his progress. He feels that the others, being American subjects, will make
            them unsympathetic to you, but I have no such feeling. I do not think you turned down
            "Off the Turnpike" because it was American, but because it was in dialect, and many
            people hate dialect poems. I confess I do not like them myself, and I only wrote a few
            of them because I wanted to broaden my technique, and I needed to make a fresh effort to
            avoid the pitfall of preciosity. I have not written any Yankee poems since Autumn, and
            maybe I never shall write another. The three I did write represented a necessity at the
            moment, and I do not regret them. But Fletcher’s American poems do not fall under this
            ban, and as the largest circulation of our book is in America, I think American subjects
            are not a mistake.</pb> Also I do not think that the English public particularly respect a
            man who appears to have no interest in his own country, and I cannot think that these
            poems of Fletcher’s will do him any harm in England.</p>
         <p>I am sorry to say that the <orgName key="century">Century Company</orgName> has refused the poems of yours which I sent
            them. Editors are very difficult things to manage. My friend, Mr. <persName key="benet">Benet</persName>, is
            assistant-editor, and he is all for them; but Mr. <persName key="doty">Doty</persName>, the head man, turned them down,
            although he said many of them were "Stunning." His reasons are that he has all the poems
            they can use at the moment. I am sorry to have been so inadequate at getting your poems
            placed in American magazines. It is not easy to get the new poetry printed in the old
            established magazines. I have the greatest difficulty with my own, and it is only
            occasionally that I get by.</p>
         <p>I have written to <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Kreymborg</persName> refusing to be included in <title key="others">his Anthology</title>, and Fletcher has
            done the same. I trust that you and Richard will follow our lead and write to him
            yourselves, although I think that none of your poems have yet appeared in his paper. But
            Richard has had poems in it, and the man will certainly print them without even asking
            permission, unless he is warned off. Fletcher has received no letter from him asking to
            include his poems, and we both think that his writing to me was largely as a feeler, and
            that it is possible there may be no Anthology if we take a firm stand and refuse to let
            our poems go in.</p>
         <p>I will send you the preface as arranged by me in a day or two. Whatever you send now in
            the way of poems or changes must go in as you put it, because there is no time for any
            more writing back and forth. Any changes you choose to make in the preface, of course I
            shall submit to; but I beg you to remember that my object is to persuade, not to
            antagonize. I have succeeded in persuading many people in my talks, and I think that the
            method is working well. I am not writing a second letter to Richard, because this is to
            him as well.</p>
         <p>By the way, here is a funny thing. If you will read the "Hellenica"</pb> by <persName key="edward_obrien">Edward J. O’Brien</persName>
            in the December "<title key="littleReview">Little Review</title>," you will see that we are having an effect. I do not of
            course know whether these are real translations or whether they are original, but Mr.
            O’Brien has for years written the worst metrical prose I think I have ever read, and
            this certainly is an advance. Courage, my Children, we are getting there!</p>
         <closer>Affectionately,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
