<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1923-03-30">30 March 1923</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$137i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Four pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Manager, Lloyd’s Bank, 67
                     Kingsway, <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W.C.2. <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned. Date was changed from March 20,
                     1923 to March 30, 1923; the change was made in pencil. At the end of the letter, "Draft according to exchange" was added in pencil.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1923-03-30">March 30, 1923.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I believe I have never answered your letter of last October, and I am sure I never
            thanked you for your Christmas card, all of which deserves <subst><del type="strikethrough">my</del><add place="above">a</add></subst> sincere apology. But really, my dear, I find letters exceedingly hard to write, with
            this terrible <title key="johnKeats"><persName key="john_keats">Keats</persName> book</title> taking all my time and all my energy. Perhaps, when it is
            finished, I shall burst into a perfect flame of correspondence. But now I have something
            most important to write you, and my only regret at not writing earlier is that you may
            have heard it first from <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName>. <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> will take your <title>book</title><!--which book-->. I gave
            Ferris your <placeName key="london">London</placeName> bank address, as he was very anxious to see you when he went over,
            which he did about three weeks ago. I told him I had no idea whether you were in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>
            or were going to be there, and I think he was not going on <placeName key="europe">the Continent</placeName>, but probably
            he will succeed in reaching you somehow and you can talk over the terms he suggests,
            which I strongly advise you to accept, although they are not calculated to turn <add place="above">your royalties</add> into a mine of gold.</p>
         <p>My experience with Houghton Mifflin is that they make very severe contracts with their
            authors, but that they live absolutely up to the letter of them and frequently interpret
            them to the author’s advantage. It <subst><del type="strikethrough">is</del><add place="above">was</add></subst> just the other way with
            <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>, who made what seemed like an extremely lenient contract, and then crept up on
            it on all points. As I told <persName key="marianne_moore">Marianne Moore</persName> that Houghton Mifflin had accepted it, and as
            she is more prompt in her correspondence than I, I think you may have heard the news
            from her as well as from Ferris.</p>
         <p>My only wish that you had not sent <title>your new poetry volume</title><!--which one--> to <orgName key="holt">Henry Holt</orgName>, as my
            experience, and that of all the authors with whom I have talked, is that it is better to
            be published by one firm, and not to scatter one’s</pb> books among a number of
            firms, for in that case no firm takes the same interest in you as they would do if they
            were your sole publishers. I think Houghton Mifflin are beginning to see the error of
            their ways in not accepting "<title key="hymen">Hymen</title>" and having all your books in their hands. Being a
            perfectly honest person, I was compelled to tell Ferris that Marianne Moore had told me, <add place="above">on the whole, I think it was <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> who told me; not Marianne Moore</add> that Henry Holt had taken your new poems, but he must want to publish your
            things as in spite of this he is willing to take your essays, which shows he must want
            them a good deal. If you do see him or if you do correspond with him, I hope you will
            agree to give him first chance on whatever new books you have, as I think he is
            realizing more and more that you are a very important person in this poetry renaissance,
            and that it would be a good thing for his firm to be your publishers.</p>
         <p>Here is the little pittance for our half-yearly royalties on the "<title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthologies</title>."
            They sell os little now that the few copies we have left of each volume seem to go on
            forever, but, as I have long since given orders that they are not to be reprinted, I
            suppose these liter doles of five and ten cent pieces will end in time. They report that
            there are 25 copies of the 1915, 23 copies of the 1916, and 31 copies of the 1917
            volumes left over.</p>
         <p>I should have sent you this money last month, but I have been away for six weeks touring
            the Middle West and giving seventeen lectures. It was a most interesting experience, but
            a little too strenuous for me. I came home with a wretched cold which it has taken me an
            age to throw off, but I am all right now.</p>
         <p>I am not coming to <placeName key="london">London</placeName> this Spring as I had hoped, because I have got the Keats book
            ready for the press and they are very anxious to publish it next Autumn. I hope that
            I may get it done in time, but the mere manual</pb> labour of writing seems
            to make that doubtful, though I have not said as much to the publishers. However, I am
            getting on swimmingly, and, if I could write more hours a day and if there were more
            days between now and Autumn, I could certainly finish it in time. As it is now, it is a
            mere question of how long it will take to put it down on paper, for this book is now
            entirely crystallized in my mind, and my stacks of notes are now numbered and in order
            so that I have no difficulty in using them. Two years is a long time to meditate on a
            book and do the preliminary work on it, and that I have reached the stage of writing is
            almost an intoxication to me after the drudgery which preceded it.</p>
         <p>I heard of you last from <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Bryher</persName>, although she said she had not seen you. She
            and <persName key="robert_mcalmon">McAlmon</persName> seem to be getting along all right. I cannot quite make out how. Marianne
            Moore seemed to think it was a marriage of convenience and that they were not living
            together as husband and wife. Personally, from Winifred’s letters, I should doubt this.
            I should doubt it all more from her poems, and I do not know whether Marianne Moore
            knows any more about it than I do, as neither of us have seen them since they were
            married. I wish you would give me your opinion on the subject; in confidence, of
            course.</p>
         <p>If there is any more I can do for you at any time to forward your work here, or anything
            else that ou would like, you know you can always command me. I thought your poems in the
            "<title key="miscellany">Miscellany</title>" were particularly fine. I wonder how <persName key="conrad_aiken">Aiken</persName>’s "<title key="americanPoetry">Anthology</title>" is getting on in
            London. The book has had long reviews; scarcely, I think, favourable ones. The animosity
            of the English press toward American poetry is one of the things that prove how
            extremely vital and interesting American poetry is, I believe.</p>
         <p>Well, my dear, this rambling around must end. I will try not to be so dilatory in
            answering your next letter, which is a hint that you write me at</pb> once and
            tell me your news, because, like most bad correspondents, I like getting letters.</p>
         <closer><persName key="ada_russell">Ada</persName> sends her love, and I am as always, Affectionately yours,</closer>
         <p>Statement of Account.</lb>
            By sales:</lb>
            21 Imagist Poets at (in pencil) .67-1/2 $ 14.18</lb>
            13 " " 1916 .67-1/2 8.77</lb>
            13 " " 1917 .67-1/2 8.78</lb>
            1/6 of $31.73 is <measure type="currency" num="$5.29">$5.29</measure>.</lb>
            <add place="below">Draft according to exchange.</add></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
