<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1919-07-14">24 July 1919</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$100i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington care of Mrs. Randall, 3
                     Christchurch Place <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, N.W. <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned. Includes a postscript.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1919-07-24">July 24, 1919.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I got your very nice letter from <placeName key="mullion">Mullion</placeName> a few days ago, and also your poems, but, in
            the first place, let me congratulate you on the birth of your <persName key="perdita_aldington">daughter</persName>. I did
            congratulate <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>, and I meant to write to you long ago, but I have been swamped with
            the proof of my <title key="floatingWorld">new book</title><!--I think-->. Both <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and I are perfectly delighted to know that
            everything passed over so successfully, and that you are entirely recovered from the
            pneumonia. You do not know, dear Hilda, how fond I am of you and how much your happiness
            means to me.</p>
         <p>You speak of wanting to be in a warmer place for the Winter. I suppose nothing could
            induce you to come to <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>. It would be so nice to have you here, and I quite agree
            with <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Ellerman</persName> in thinking that this is the place for poetry now. I make no
            doubt that I can dispose of your poems satisfactorily, and I shall set about it at once.
            Do not worry about not being <foreign xml:lang="fr"><hi rend="underline">dans le movement</hi></foreign>. The "Movement" as I now see it is mostly
            an artificial one, and I believe that the better poets will always write as they feel
            without any regard for the fashionable thing in the minds of <foreign xml:lang="fr"><hi rend="underline">les jeunes</hi></>. I have seen so
            many movements go under since I have been on the <hi rend="underline">tapis</hi> that I am no longer worried about
            the fate of anything that is really good, and I think it is rather an advantage to be
            out of it than otherwise. I have been in it for years and have borne the brunt of
            ridicule, jests, diatribes, and am now reaping the benefit of a reasonable success, but
            the result of it all to me has been to make me feel that one must write as one wishes,
            and that one can force the public to take it if it is good. You have no idea of the
            exaltation of poetry</pb> here in America. I have been asked to compile a Book Shelf of
            Modern Poets by <orgName key="doubledayPage">Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</orgName> suitable for sale in department stores and
            railway terminals. Conceive of such a thing! All this love for poetry naturally is not
            very critical.</p>
         <p>I think that your idea of sending Winifred over here is just the proper one, but I wish
            that you would send yourself and your little daughter over too. We need you, and I am
            just cheeky enough to think that you need us.</p>
         <p>This takes lots and lots of love from Mrs. Russell and me.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
         <postscript>P.S. I will write again when I have disposed of the poems.</postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
