<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-02-08">08 February 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$13i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-02-08">February 8, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>It was very nice of you to give us an opportunity to chip in a little bit. That is what
            I call being really friendly, and I am perfectly delighted that you should have written
            to me. It is a wonder to me that your remittances from home ever come, with the mails in
            the state they are, and there must have been lots of mail lost when the various vessels
            have been sunk. As a matter of fact, I had received a couple of days before <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName>’s statement. We have sold 428 books, and the total amount of the sales amounts
            to $219.08, of which one-sixth is $36.51; therefore, I owe you and <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> <measure type="currency" num="73.02">$73.02</measure>. I
            added just a little to it to make it a round sum, as I thought that probably you were
            still stuck, as your letter only said that your remittances were coming, and coming is
            not come. Please do not think anything about it, and do not dream of paying it back.
            Take it as the most natural thing in the world, as I do. You see, my Dear Girl, I know
            what it is to have shattered nerves, I had nervous prostration for seven years once, and
            it is not a nice condition; so you just mustn’t have anything to worry about. Now if
            anything else happens of a like kind in future, just let me know, for I am most anxious
            to do everything I can for "the cause," and if you and Richard are not "the cause," I
            don’t know what is.</p>
         <p><persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> has sent me some more poems, which he says come in the collection he left
            behind in <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>, and which has apparently just reached him. On the whole, <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> and I
            think three of them distinctly better than "Resurrection," and we have taken the liberty
            of substituting them for it. There is not time to send them over to you and get your
            consent to them, and it has worried me a good deal as to what to do on the subject, but
            finally</pb> both Fletcher and I agreed that the wisest thing to do was to calmly take them
            for the book, trusting to your approval of our choice. As you have left us the carte
            blanche to do what we wanted to with our own things, we thought this might extend to
            Lawrence’s poems as well. We were all so agreed on the subject of the badness of
            "Resurrection," or rather perhaps I should say its inadequacy and its inappropriateness
            to our volume, that I thought the others would be better than that anyway. Of course, in
            writing to Lawrence, I did not tell him my objections to "Resurrection;" I said all the
            nice things I could about it, and suppressed the others, as I did not like to hurt his
            feelings, but I am telling him now that we think these others that we have chosen are
            better for the book, and I am sure he will not object. I cannot even send you copies of
            them with this letter, because Lawrence asked me to see if I could find a publisher, and
            I took them in to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> yesterday, with a view to his publishing them in the
            Autumn set of his <title key="newPoetrySeries">New Poetry Series</title>. He asked if he could keep them for a day or two,
            and entirely forgetting that I wanted to make copies for you, I left them with him, and
            he has gone off to <placeName key="washington_dc">Washington</placeName> on business for a day or two, and I cannot possibly get
            hold of the poems until he comes back. This is excessively annoying, and I ought not to
            have done it; but as there would not be time to hear from you anyway, I hope you will
            forgive me, and I will send you the copies just as soon as I get them back.</p>
         <p>The only thing that is delaying us now is my not having heard from you as to exactly
            which of the various selections of the poems we made you will agree to. I hope you
            understand that making this selection was merely a matter of space and nothing else. We
            can go to press with the poems, without waiting for the Preface, as soon as I hear from
            you.</p>
         <p>I do wish there were any chance of getting you over here, for I am sure we should all
            have a splendid time living in the same town together. Fletcher is improving so much; he
            is much less nervous and seems to be very happy, and is writing busily all the time. He
            seems to like it here, and I am sure that you and Richard would like this town better
            than any other in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>.</p></pb>
         <p>I am giving one of my talks at the <placeName key="littleTheatre">Little Theatre</placeName> in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> on <date when="1916-03-19>March 19th</date>, and I am
            rather looking forward to it, as I should like to make some impression there. I think
            they are altogether too fond of <persName key="carl_sandburg">Sandberg</persName>, and <persName key="el_masters">Masters</persName>, and <persName key="vachel_lindsay">Lindsay</persName> in Chicago.</p>
         <p>Ferris Greenslet has made a ridiculous mess of his New Poetry Series by putting in
            anything and everything, utterly regardless of its fitness, with the result that the
            only volume of the Series which seems to be doing at all well is our <title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title>. I think
            that has really done pretty well, and apparently it is still selling, for when I went in
            there yesterday they told me that they had just had to take over 85 more copies of the
            220 copies of the second edition they had still unbound, and bind them – that since the
            <date when="1916-01-01">first of January</date>. I hope the next one will go as well.</p>
         <p>I am adding a note to my "Stravinsky Cuartet"[sic] as follows: "This Quartet was played
            from the manuscript by the <orgName key="flonzaleyQuartet">Flonzaley Quartet</orgName> during their season of 1915 and 1916. The
            poem is based upon the programme which M. <persName key="igor_stravinsky">Stravinsky</persName> appended to his piece, and is an
            attempt to reproduce the sound and movement of the music as far as is possible in
            another medium." I think this would explain to people why the onomatopoetic lines are
            there, and that the poem is not intended as a joke or a take-off.</p>
         <p>I have written to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> to say that I have here any of your poems which she desires. I
            am not altogether pleased with her attitude just now; there seems to be a great deal of
            <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> in it, judging by <title key="poetry">the last number</title>, although you will see that I did succeed in
            bullyragging her to put in <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>’s things in time for us to use them. I think the best
            way would be for me to see Harriet when I go out, and read her these things and try to
            get her to take them. I have always found that I could do more with her by</pb> personal
            contact than in any other way. I am delighted with the contents of the new book; I think
            it shows us all in advance of our last year’s work, and the bibliography shows an
            advance in the publications of the group.</p>
         <p>Now, Hilda, don’t you think it would be a good idea if a book of yours came out in
            print? Have you got enough things to go in a book? I will do my best to force Ferris
            Greenslet to take it if you have. I hate to have you the only one of us who does not
            appear to have published a book, although for that very reason, the publishing of books
            seems futile.</p>
         <p>I wonder why Richard feels as he does about "polyphonic prose." Last year, in his review
            of my book, he commended the metre as an interesting one, and said he had written
            several things in it, and recommended young poets to study it. Now he writes me that he
            does not like it, and the only things of mine he likes in it are the "Bombardment" and
            "Spring Day." That seems to me a very curious volte-face, and I cannot quite see why he
            takes it. Fletcher and I are devoted to the metre. We find it excellent for dramatic
            things. Perhaps the reason Richard does not care for it is because he writes very little
            dramatic poetry.</p>
         <p>I am sending you an article in a Chicago monthly called the "Trimmed Lamp," which I
            think shows the way the wind is blowing.</p>
         <p><persName key="mary_aldis">Mrs. Aldis</persName> wanted to offer a prize for an <orgName key="imagists">Imagist</orgName> poem, through the auspices of "<title key="littleReview">The Little Review</title>"; but her judges were very peculiar: they consisted of myself, <persName key="arthur_ficke">Arthur Davidson Ficke</persName>, and <persName key="john_powys">John Powys</persName>. The whole thing seemed to me too absurd, and I
            disapprove of prizes anyway, on principle, they so seldom get awarded justly; though, as
            a matter of fact, I think when prizes are, and one cannot help it, it is a fine thing to
            win them. But to begin with prizes for Imagist poems when almost nobody knows how to
            write them, with myself as the only judge who knew what they were when written, would be
            too idiotic. Fletcher entirely agreed with me, and we have persuaded Mrs. Aldis to
            withdraw her suggestion – luckily, it had not got into print. Fletcher and I felt that
            as the only original group of Imagists could run in competition, we should be put into
            the curious position of half</pb> of us sitting in judgment of the other half, which seemed
            most unfortunate. I hope you will approve of my action.</p>
         <p>If I do not hear from you in a couple of weeks, I shall just have to take the matter
            into my own hands and arrange your poems according to the group we most advised in our
            letter. Next year we must begin a great deal earlier with our Anthology, that is, unless
            the mails go more quickly.</p>
         <p>Lots of love to you both, and don’t you let yourself get tired, Hilda, and don’t you
            worry about anything! <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> joins me in sending much love.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
