<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-02-07">07 February 1917</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$45i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Mrs Richard
                     Aldington" in pencil at the top of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-07-07">February 7, 1917.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I have waited in vain for your second letter about <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>’s and <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>’s opinions in
            regard to my "Lacquer Prints", but although it is two weeks since I received your last
            letter, I have had no other. We can no longer delay going to press.</p>
         <p>I rather thought you might send me some more of Flint’s things, as his contribution is
            short, but in a letter I had from him this morning, he does not mention the subject, so
            I suppose I may take it that nothing more will come.</p>
         <p>Fletcher advised me to send "Lacquer Prints" so I suppose his permission is given and I
            hardly think that Flint will disapprove. Whether or not you have sent them to <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>,
            I do not know, but I trust that I am doing right in considering that they are
            satisfactory.</p>
         <p>Of course, as you say, we must do everything that <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> wants, and I have changed the
            poems in accordance with his list with one exception. I have not included "Middle Ages"
            because I really do not think that the American public would care for it, and I am more
            anxious than any one else to have Richard well liked over here. His poetry is, to my
            mind, so exceedingly beautiful that I cannot bear to print anything that I think people
            would not understand, as I want his reputation to grow by leaps and bounds.</p>
         <p>I am glad to say that I have sold two of his poems to "<title key="sevenArts">The Seven Arts</title>", namely, "Leave
            Taking" and "On the March". Of course I cannot place any of the others now that are
            coming out in the <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthology</title>, and I am afraid it would be impossible to think of
            publishing "Malady" and "Middle Ages" over here.</p></pb>
         <p>Richard’s contribution now runs: "Vicarious Atonement", "Bondage", "A Moments
            Interlude", "Field Manoeuvres", "On the March", "Leave Taking", "Inarticulate Grief",
            "Captive", "R.V. and Another", and "Prayer". The last one I absolutely insist upon
            having as I love it so much. This is more than the seven titles which Richard is really
            entitled to, being, in fact, ten, but the space is no more than you have, as well as I
            can calculate it, and not as much as Fletcher’s, so I think we can strain a point.</p>
         <p>I have included your new contribution exactly as you sent it; that is, "The God",
            "Adonis", "Pygmalion" and "Eurydice", taking out your "Tribute". The other contributions
            remain as they were when I wrote you last.</p>
         <p>I shall have to put in the acknowledgements a word of thanks to <persName key="arthur_ficke">Arthur Davison Ficke</persName>, as
            I got the original of my adaptation of the Japanese poet <persName key="yakura_sanjin">Yakura Sanjin</persName> from his book
            "<title key="japanesePrints">Chats on Japanese Prints</title>".</p>
         <p>I have an appointment with Mr. <persName key="roger_scaife">Scaife</persName> on the firm of <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.</orgName> on
            Wednesday, when I shall hand him this manuscript.</p>
         <p>Fletcher has sent me a book of his which he wants Houghton-Mifflin to take and in which
            two of the poems of his contribution appear; namely, "Lincoln" and "Armies", but I think
            we can make the arrangement which we have done before that our volume appears a month or
            two in advance of his. If I cannot do that, I don’t know what the dickens I shall do,
            but I am not going to cross that bridge</pb> until I get to it.</p>
         <p>Our statement has come in from Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co. for the six months ending <date when="1917-01-31">January 31, 1917</date>, but I do not think it is quite correct, and I am going to speak to Mr. Scaife
            about it and get it fixed on Wednesday, so I cannot send you all your shares until after
            that date.</p>
         <p>I have five dollars more which I have collected from Brown to send, also, which leaves
            him only five dollars to pay on the <measure type="currency" num="$30">thirty dollars</measure> he agreed to pay<add place="above"> Richard</add> last year. I think then we shall have to give him another year before we dun him
            for more royalties for Richard’s "Images".</p>
         <p>I also have a <measure type="currency" num="$20">twenty dollar check</measure> here which "The Seven Arts" sent me for the two poems
            they have taken.</p>
         <p>I will put all this, together with his share of the Imagist royalties and yours, in a
            draft and send it to you as soon as I have had my interview with Scaife.</p>
         <p>I imagine that now we are so near the verge of war that the sailings will be uncertain
            and for that reason I think it is not wise to wait for further word from you.</p>
         <p>I am thankful that our government has taken a definite stand and that we may no longer
            appear to the world to hold a neutrality which we certainly do not feel.</p>
         <closer>With lots of love, dear Hilda, Affectionately,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
