<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1917-12-03">03 December 1917</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$64i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington 44 <placeName key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>
                        <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1917-12-03">December 3, 1917.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>The enclosed letter was opened by me by mistake. The other letters lay over it, and I
            did not see your name until after I had opened it and saw that it began "Dear Hilda,"
            and I am sending it to you envelope and all that you may see that it was not altogether
            extraordinary that I should have opened it.</p>
         <p>I wonder if you ever got my book<!--which book?-->>. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> got his copy, which I sent at the same time
            as I sent yours, but I have not heard yet from any of the others I sent to <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. If
            you did not get it, please let me know and I will send you another copy. I hope you like
            the essay on you. People are calling it the "almost lyrical appreciation of 'H.D.'."
            Also, I am anxious to receive that biographical material about <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> as soon as
            possible, as I must begin to prepare my lectures shortly. Also I should like some
            news.</p>
         <p>I think Richard must be an officer from what you say, and <persName key="helen_doolittle">your mother</persName> tells me that he
            may be sent to the Eastern front, but I do not feel that I know anything definite, and I
            should be awfully glad to be brought up to date.</p>
         <p>I sent Richard’s letter and poems to <persName key="brown">Brown</persName>. I do not think I like these rhymed things
            quite as much as Richard’s vers libre, but neither does he, as he says in the letter. I
            am not quite like the rest of you – everything that interests me turns into poetry, and
            just now I cannot get away from the war. I am writing a series called "Phantasms of War"
            for "The Independent," and I am sending you enclosed the first one which I think may
            interest you. It may not be what Richard calls art, but somehow I cannot divorce art
            from life, and if <persName key="homer">Homer</persName> made art out of the</pb> Trojan war, it seems to me we ought to be
            able to do the same with this war. Anyhow, I am trying and if I fail – well, it is all
            in the day’s work.</p>
         <p>This is not much of a letter, but there is not much to say. I do nothing but work, and
            the whole country is given over to war preparations.</p>
         <closer>Write soon and with a great deal of love to you both, Affectionately
            yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
