<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1925-03-23">23 March 1925</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$147i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington care Manager, Lloyd’s Bank, 67
                     Kingsway, <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W.C.2, <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1925-03-23">March 23, 1925.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Your letter of <date when="1925-03-06">March sixth</date> was very nice to get. I do not advise your having the "<title key="johnKeats">Keats</title>"
            sent to <placeName key="europe">the continent</placeName> if you are running round, for he is really very bulky, and you can
            get it when you come to <placeName key="london">London</placeName>.</p>
         <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and I land in <placeName key="england">England</placeName> on <date when="1925-04-21">April twenty-first</date>, and we sail for home on <date when="1925-07-18">July eighteenth</date>, so that gives us a good leeway; in case you come to England, I am almost
            sure to be there.</p>
         <p><persName key="jonathan_cape">Jonathan Cape</persName> has done nobly with the lectures, and I am booked for about twenty
            readings – at all the English universities and before various poetry societies, etc.</p>
         <p>If you think that the London reviews of the "Keats" are good, that is not my idea
            of good. On the other hand, the provincial papers and the Scottish papers have been
            really good. The London papers, in spite of the space that they have allowed me, have
            adopted their usual sneering tactics, but their interest to hear me speak is surprising.
            I am giving a lecture at <orgName key="birminghamU">Birmingham University</orgName> on "Modern American Poetry" and shall
            read some of your things there. I feel that it is really going back ten years and expect
            to be greeted with potatoes and rotten eggs. But, as far as I can make out, it is the
            literary set who are hostile, the public at large seem well enough disposed. Poets are a
            jealous crowd, and when I saw <persName key="edith_sitwell">Edith Sitwell</persName> patronizing you and me in "<title key="vogue">Vogue</title>" the other
            day, I could not help smiling.</p>
         <p>I have not seen the collected edition of your books published by Boni and Liveright, but
            I am very anxious to get it. The English can talk as they want, but I think the American
            poets beat them all to a frazzle, and I expect to hint as much, gently but firmly, in my
            lecture.</p></pb>
         <p>I am sending this to the bank so that you may receive it
            somewhere, some time. I wrote to <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Bryher</persName> the other day and sent my book to her
            <placeName key="audleyStreet">South Audley Street</placeName> address. I hope she will get it sometime.</p>
         <p>I did not send you any royalties from the <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist anthologies</title> in February for the simple
            reason that there were none. 1915 and 1916 are out of print and there are only six
            copies of 1917 left, so we shall soon have done with it altogether. It did its work and
            served its turn, and I, for one, shall be glad to have it entirely disposed of.</p>
         <p>Both Mrs. Russell and I are looking forward very much to seeing you. We shall be at the
            <placeName key="berkleyHotel">Berkley Hotel</placeName>, but my bank address will probably be safer. It is care of Messrs. <orgName key="brownShipley">Brown, Shipley &amp; Co.</orgName>, 123 Pall Mall, London, S.W.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
