<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-09-13">13 September 1916.</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$28i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-09-13">September 13, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I received your letter last night, containing <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s poems. I think "Prayer" and
            "Bondage" are very beautiful. Whether or not I can sell them at once I do not know. You
            see, I have already done considerable selling of Richard’s things of late. Papers like
            "<title key="sevenArts">The Seven Arts</title>" I do not think are very understanding in Imagist work. I fear "<title key="poetryReview">The Poetry Review</title>" is rather filled up to the present, and I know there is no use in asking
            <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> to buy more until she has published those she has. I think I shall try "<title key="century">The Century</title>" with one of these; but that is a very problematic amusement. Anyway, I will see
            what I can do to get them into something, and to get the best price for them.</p>
         <p>You will be glad to know that our old <title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title> – the 1915 one – has just had to be
            reprinted for the third time. We sold over fifty copies of it in the last month. Also
            <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> has ordered 165 copies of the 1916 Anthology, 15 of these for review purposes,
            making 150 for sale. That is not so bad. Do keep your eyes out for the criticisms, and
            let me have them.</p>
         <p>I see that <persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName> has announced Richard as one of his contributors to "<title key="dial">The Dial</title>," which he has just bought. He was so in love with Richard’s paper on <persName key="henri_deRegnier">Henry de Régnier</persName> that I think he will take a good deal of Richard’s prose work. They publish no
            poetry. "The Dial" is not a general magazine, it is a magazine of criticism only,
            criticism in all the arts, so that any articles on the war or anything of that sort
            would not be pertinent. But any critical article that Richard feels like sending, I am
            sure would meet with consideration.</p>
         <p>I have told "The Dial" and everybody else with whom I have to do that</pb> I am acting here
            as Richard’s agent, and that they must send their cheques to me. By this process I know
            when he has been paid, and also I am on the spot and can enforce payment. "<title key="poetryReview">The Poetry Review</title>" wrote me the other day and asked me to whom they should send his cheque for the
            <persName key="stephane_mallarme">Mallarmé</persName> article, which was published this month, and I told them to send it to me; it
            has not come yet, and I suppose it won’t for some little time; but I hope to have it
            before long.</p>
         <p>There is not much to tell you. I am busy with the proofs of my new book, as I suppose
            you are with yours. I have also written some poems. I wish I could see you all, but I
            trust the war will not last forever. Now I must go back to my proofs.</p>
         <p>With a great deal of love from <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and me to you and Richard,</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
