<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-10-13">13 October 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$31i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of the first page. Unsigned. Includes a postscript.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-10-13">October 13, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am enclosing a bank draft for <measure type="currency" num="£1.16">£ 1.16</measure>.
            This represents <measure type="currency" num="$5">$5</measure> for <persName
               key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s article on "<persName
               key="stephane_mallarme">Mallarmé</persName>" and <measure type="currency" num="$4"
               >$4</measure> for his poems in the August "<title key="poetryReview">Poetry
               Review</title>".</p>
         <p><persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName>, the editor of "<title key="dial">The Dial</title>", wrote to me the other day and asked me if I
            could give him Richard’s address, as he was delighted with the <persName key="henri_deRegnier">Henry de Régnier</persName> article,
            and he wanted to have Richard do some more articles for him. I instantly told him to
            write C/o "<title key="egoist">The Egoist</title>", and as "The Dial" has quite a circulation, I think it will be a
            good thing for Richard, if he can find time to write anything for it.</p>
         <p>I saw a long letter in one of the numbers of "The Egoist" by <persName key="wc_williams">William Carlos Williams</persName>,
            which I suppose he got in through <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>. The "<title key="others">Others</title>" group has entirely failed,
            apparently, and they are very bitter with us because we haven’t. I suppose that is
            inevitable. They failed because of the ridiculous manner in which they ran their paper,
            and the spirit of bad-boys-out-on-a-frolick which they permitted to imbue it. I have a
            correspondence with William Carlos Williams which, I think, will open your eyes to their
            attitude. The first letter I took half in fun, as you will see by my answer. The second
            letter is an astonishing document, and shows the fine Italian hand of Ezra. I enclose a
            copy of my answer. Please show these to Richard. It is as well to know our friends from
            our enemies.</p></pb>
         <p><persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> writes me that you all dined together the other day. He also tells me that you
            are all to have your poems in your hands on November first. That is good, because they
            ought to be here to me by December first, and I will send my contributions to you to get
            there by the same date.</p>
         <p>I think Fletcher feels it would be better not to have another "<title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title>", and I suppose
            as far as the effect of the movement is concerned it won’t make much difference whether
            we do or not. The "Anthology" has done its work, has lifted us out of the attitude of
            young charlatans in which Ezra had unfortunately left us, and has shown the world at
            large that there is a section of the new poetry which is serious and hard-working and
            has something in it. It has succeeded beyond my wildest dreams, and I do not think
            another number will help or hurt the cause. We are now accepted, and, of course, it will
            be our individual effort in future which will count.</p>
         <p>On the other hand, we signed for three years, and although that is immaterial (the
            publishers being willing or not, as we choose), we have told so many people that it was
            for three years and as our sales amply justify another number, I have come to the
            conclusion that it would be better for us to continue and round out our three years.
            Also, the failure of "Others" and the success of our "Anthology" has proved that the
            public does distinguish</pb><!--what should we do when a page break occurs in the middle of a word?--> between good work and charlatanism. Not that I think all the
            "Others" contributors were charlatans. In spite of Williams’s childish bitterness and
            injustice, I think he is a sincere fellow and an honest worker, and I think various
            others of their contributors were so, too. Unfortunately the policy of the paper was the
            reverse of this. It was because I felt this so strongly, that I wanted us to withdraw
            our support from "Others". Now I feel that if their anthology and their paper have gone
            to the wall and ours still continues to appear, it will prove, more conclusively than
            anything else can do, the value of our work. Therefore, after taking one thing and
            another, I have decided that it would be distinctly better to print this year’s
            "Anthology". I do not think there is any reason to extend the contract for any years
            after this, nor do I think it would be wise to do so. Imagism has come to mesh a
            definite artistic point of view. That we all differ slightly in our individual
            interpretations of that point of view, I know quite well. But the attitude at large has
            become as distinct a phase of art as Romanticism, or Impressionism, or Classicism, or
            any of the other names by which main groups of artistic tendencies are known.</p>
         <p>Ezra and his group may bite and scratch all they want. As far as the public here is
            concerned, they do not exist. Much as I admire much of Ezra’s work, his output is so
            slight that he has fallen into a backwater, and his violent diatribes against</pb> everything
            and everybody have served to make him a laughing-stock. And those of his disciples who
            swear by him are not only in the backwater, they have never been out of it, and we need
            fear them no more than if they were gnats. Still, we stand in an awkward position, for
            the conservatives are against us on one side, and the Ezra group are against us on the
            other. It is only the kindly and outside public who admire us. But they do admire us and
            support us, and I think we are rapidly becoming the thing which is most influencing the
            younger generation. The main thing is that we should all keep together and push each
            other as much as possible, and above all, avoid schisms and differences – that is,
            stated differences – among ourselves. That six poets should have kept within the cover
            of one volume without fighting, for three years, is a remarkable thing, and I think we
            have all shown great generosity and self control. But the effect of this generosity and
            self-control is evident in the increasing consideration with which we are treated by the
            world at large.</p>
         <p>I have not seen your book yet, as it is not out, over here; but Fletcher writes it is
            very fine. I shall review it, either for "<title key="poetryReview">The Poetry Review</title>" or for <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>.</p>
         <p>My own book will be out in ten days or so, and I shall send you a copy at once. I shall
            be most grateful if you can review it as soon as possible for "The Egoist". There will
            be things in it that neither you nor Richard will like nor subscribe</pb> to. I cannot see
            Imagism quite within the boundaries that you do. But there will be other things in the
            book which I think you will like – some old friends which you have already said you
            liked.</p>
         <closer>With lots of love to Richard, Affectionately,</closer>
         <postscript>P.S. We have sold 700 copies of our 2nd Anthology to date.</postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
