<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1919-03-05">05 March 1919</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$91i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Nine pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington care of Mrs. Randall, 3
                     Christchurch Place Hampstead, <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, N.W.
                        <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1919-03-05">March 5, 1919.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Thank you a thousand times for your very nice letter of <date when="1919-02-01">February 1st</date>. I really was
            worried about you; I could not conceive where you were or what had happened to you, I
            had not heard for so long. I have already written to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> and asked him if he knew
            whether you ever got "<title key="canGrandesCastle">Can Grande’s Castle</title>," as I felt quite sure that it must have gone
            astray with your various moves.</p>
         <p>I am most sincerely grieved to hear of your <persName key="gilbert_doolittle">brother</persName>’s death in <placeName key="france">France</placeName>. What a terrible
            time this has been! I know how hard it must have been for you to be away from your
            family just now. <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Ellerman</persName> writes despairingly about passports, but I do not
            myself believe that there is any difficulty in getting them for any one situated as you
            have been, for I know my <persName key="elizabeth_putnam">sister</persName> has just come home from <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, where she has been for
            a year and a half staying with <persName>her daughter</persName><!--who?-->. An American wishing to return for a good
            reason can always get home. I think though, of course, that that would not apply to
            Winifred Ellerman.</p>
         <p><persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> writes me that you are expecting another baby, which is good news indeed. I
            should think that you would be perfectly delighted. I do trust that all will go well,
            dear Hilda, and I only wish that <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and I could be there to do anything we
            could for you.</p>
         <p>I am thankful that Winifred is proving stimulating and will induce you to write some
            more, for it is a wicked shame for you not to go on. My greatest satisfaction in regard
            to "<title key="tendencies">Tendencies</title>" is that it seems to have had the effect of bringing together various
            people who would not have known each other in any other way, and that is certainly a
            good thing.</p></pb>
         <p>You must be thankful to feel that Richard is out of danger. I am sure that ought to take
            a great load off your mind. I shall be extremely interested to see Mr. <persName key="clement_shorter">Shorter</persName>, but I do
            not know exactly when I shall go to England. My sister tells me, and <persName key="michael_sadler">Michael Sadler</persName>
            writes me, that it is too soon yet to think of making any impression with anything
            literary on the English public and that it would be better to wait for another summer. I
            am very anxious, if possible, to give some talks on poetry, as I have been doing here,
            when I get over, but I do not quite know how to go about that. At any rate, there is no
            use<add place="above"> in</add> thinking about it until demobilization is complete and things have settled down
            to a more or less normal condition. Also, my digestion is such a precarious thing that I
            cannot risk going over while there is any form of rationing still on.</p>
         <p>I am sending you your and Richard’s draft for<add place="above"> the</add> half-yearly royalties of our
            <title key="some_imagist_poets">anthology</title>, and I am also taking the liberty of enclosing <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>’s, for I have no idea
            what his address is. Now, will you forward it to him and tell him<add place="above"> that</add> if he will send
            me his address I will write to him. The account is as follows:</lb>
            By Sales:</lb>
            30 Imagist Poets, 1915 .36-1/4 10.88</lb>
            17 " " 1916 .36-1/4 6.16</lb>
            34 " " 1917 .36-1/4 13.32</lb>
            10 do 1916 to Eng. 37-1/2 less 15% 3.64</lb>
            10 do 1916 " " 37-1/2 less 15% 3.64</lb>
            1/6 of 37.64 is $6.27 or 1.5<gap quantity="2" unit="chars" reason="illegible"></gap> Flint’s draft is, therefore, <measure type="currency" num="£1.5.7">£ 1.5.7</measure> Yours and Richard’s <measure type="currency" num="£2.11.2">£ 2.11.2</measure></p>
         <p>Lawrence writes in very low spirits. He keeps harping on the fact that he wants to come
            to <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>. I do not know whether America would suit him at all. They have certainly had
            a very hard time to go through, he</pb> and <persName key="frieda_lawrence">Frieda</persName>.</p>
         <p>I have had a long letter from Richard apropos of this new translation series which he
            wishes to run, asking me if I will look after the American side of it. Of course I will
            do that or anything else which he wants, with pleasure, but as to making any
            translations myself, I hardly think that I will do that. There is so little time in the
            world, and I have not enough for my creative work. I cannot think that it is more
            important to translate than it is to write original things. Also I am embarked on a book
            of translations of Chinese poems with my friend Mrs. <persName key="florence_ayscough">Francis Ayscough</persName>. You will probably
            have seen some of our efforts in the February "<title key="poetry">Poetry</title>." I do not know when the book will
            come out, as it is a little difficult to work with anyone in <placeName key="china">China</placeName>, but it is, perhaps,
            an advantage to me to have the originals of these poems come so slowly, because, by this
            process, I get them done without really realizing that I am giving any time to them.</p>
         <p>Now here is something which I do not think that Richard realizes, and that is the entire
            difference in the market in England and America. Judging from the numbers of these
            translations which Richard wishes to issue, they are to<add place="above"> be</add> about the same little
            pamphlets about the same price that your last series was. Now I think it almost
            impossible to get anybody over here to handle such a series, the reason being that
            American booksellers want a large percentage for their trouble, and on a very low priced
            article, they cannot get a large percentage, and, therefore, they do not care at all
            about carrying such a thing. I know that was one of the difficulties, and always has
            been one of the difficulties, with our</pb> Anthologies. They were sold at seventy-five
            cents, and the booksellers’ commission was not enough to make it worth while for them to
            take much trouble. I feel sure that anything less than that in price would have no
            chance whatever. Also I do not think there is the same interest in translations that
            there is in England. A few of the poets, and a few scholarly people, might care for
            them, but I hardly think enough to make the project interest any publisher. However, I
            will try, and try my best, to get the things taken over here, and do everything I can,
            but I do think a great deal of water has run under the bridge since 1914, and I think
            that Richard would do better to concentrate on original work. It will not help us to be
            constantly booming poetry which is not our own. I do not mean for a moment that it would
            hurt us, and if we could make the translations and at the same time keep up our own
            output, that would be a different matter. That to me is an impossibility, although some
            other people may be more gifted in that line.</p>
         <p>I do not think that Richard realizes at all what an enormous effect we have made in this
            country, and how different the situation is here from what it was four years ago.
            England is slower, of course, and England has been much harder hit by the war, but I
            think with proper management England can also be won. I seem to have developed a
            business talent, which I had never suspected, in getting people to take an interest in
            things which they never cared anything about before, and I cannot help feeling that if
            Richard would listen to my advice, we could really make a large impression.</p>
         <p>I do not approve of doing things in an amateurish way any more. I</pb> think that puts us
            down as unsuccessful, and I think that Richard feels that too, since he wishes to have
            the new series taken up by a large firm. That, I think, is most important, and the most
            important thing of all is getting the original work put on the market properly. You
            know, in anything of this kind, one has to consider its effect on everything else one
            does. That is why I deprecated Richard’s selling <title>his last book</title><!--Which book?--> to <persName key="brown">Brown</persName>. It has not come
            out yet, and I do not know when it will. No amount of harrying Brown about it has any
            effect, and if Richard had made the changes then that he tells me he has now made for
            the English edition, I could have got it accepted by <orgName key="macmillan">The Macmillan Company</orgName>.</p>
         <p>I may be unnecessarily dampening – of course, I do not know the condition of things in
            England – but, if I were Richard, I should certainly not want to give so much time to
            working with other people’s things. I should want to devote my time to working on my
            own, and I think he should get off "<title key="egoist">The Egoist</title>" for good and all, for I do not believe
            in continuing to be tied up to a paper of that kind, a semi-amateurish thing, and one in
            which so many foolish things have appeared since <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> put his finger in.</p>
         <p>Richard writes and begs me to be broad-minded and not mind his asking Ezra to do some of
            the Spanish translations, even if I am associated with him nominally in the editorship,
            but I think that this would be exceedingly foolish, because none of Ezra’s things are
            translations at all; they are merely paraphrases. I can get you two excellent
            translators here. One is Mrs. <persName key="grace_conkling">Grace Hazard Conkling</persName>, an extremely good poet whose work
            you probably know, and who has done some <hi rend="underline">vers libre</hi> things about</pb> <placeName key="mexico">Mexico</placeName> that are most
            beautiful. She knows Spanish well enough to be teaching it at <placeName key="smithCollege">Smith College</placeName>, and
            although she has, so far as I know, never been to <placeName key="spain">Spain</placeName>, she has lived for years in
            Mexico. I know that she has already agreed to do some translations for a little paper
            here which purported to have both Spanish and American poetry. The war has caused it to
            cease publication for the moment, but I know she was enrolled as one of its band of
            translators before it momentarily stopped. The other is <persName key="salamonDeLaSelva">Salamón de la Selva</persName>, a
            Nicaraguan by birth, and a man absolutely devoted to poetry. He has published a very
            nice little volume of his own in English, and he has also written a good many poems in
            Spanish, which is his native tongue. Lately he has devoted himself to translating
            Spanish poets for America and American poets for Spain. He has a large clientele among
            South American papers and is a very intelligent fellow and an exceedingly good
            translator. At the moment, he is in the Canadian army and has not yet come home,
            but I think he shortly will. Either of these people would be infinitely better than
            Ezra.</p>
         <p>Now my feeling about Ezra is not in the least personal. I had as lief meet him as not,
            and I should be very glad indeed to have a nice pleasant talk with him, but I will not
            be associated with him in any literary enterprise, because I have discovered that to be
            known to be in collaboration with him at all is tantamount to writing one’s epitaph. The
            reputation which he once had has practically entirely gone, and it is absolutely
            suicidal to be associated with him in any public way.</p>
         <p>I do wish that Richard could get a wider outlook on the literary world in general. You
            see, you and he do not see a great many people, and they are mostly in one set, as far
            as the poets are concerned, and</pb> that gives Richard a warped idea of the attitude of the
            world at large. I firmly believe that it is time for us to get out of a clique, to cease
            to act as though we were struggling for a hearing, and to take our places boldly as
            voices of the new day. I have at least achieved this magnificent summit here in America.
            I think, however, that I am anathema in <placeName key="greenwichVillage">Greenwich Village</placeName>, for it is annoying when one
            is in an inlet one’s self to have any one else swim into the open sea. But for the past
            two years I have been trying to disengage myself from the amateur publishing ventures of
            the younger fry. I shall never desert certain old friends like "Poetry," but you
            remember that I decided not to publish in "<title key="others">Others</title>" long ago, and "<title key="littleReview">The Little Review</title>"
            lost my valuable services when they tied up with Ezra. You see, I think there must come
            a time in the life of every serious artist when he ceases to be a beginner, and has a
            right to expect and claim proper recognition from the world he lives in. I cannot help
            thinking that one’s own attitude affects that recognition considerably. You know the old
            saying, that the world takes one at one’s own valuation. I think, if one constantly puts
            one’s self in the position of being, as it were, on the threshold rather than in the
            parlour of success, one is apt to be kept all one’s life kicking one’s feet on the
            mat.</p>
         <p>I wish that Richard could write for some of the larger English papers. I think this
            could be done without any compromise whatever in his literary attitude; at least, I have
            found it possible here.</p>
         <p>Richard wrote and asked me the other day if I could get him a regular letter in any of
            the papers and magazines, but that is, of course,</pb> difficult, as most of the papers
            already established have their own correspondents, and there are no new ones being
            started just now, and a good many, such as the "<title key="sevenArts">Seven Arts</title>," had to stop on account of
            the war. I have written to <persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName> about it, and he is enthusiastic, as always,
            about Richard’s work, but I do not know that he will take any definite steps in the
            matter. Of course, "<title key="dial">The Dial</title>" has a very small circulation, and it is devoting more and
            more space to socialism and politics generally, which is most unfortunate, but there are
            a great many other papers here for which Richard might write, I think; if he would send
            me some essays, I might try and place them in the "<title key="northAmericanReview">North American Review</title>" or "<title key="bookman">The Bookman</title>" or somewhere. You see, I did sell a poem of his to the "North American Review,"
            last year, and then found that he had given it to that ridiculous little man in
            <placeName key="cleveland">Cleveland</placeName>, and, of course, it having been privately printed, the "North American" would
            not touch it. Richard’s attitude is very fine about giving all for art and not being
            paid for things, but really and truly, as a matter of fact, the world appreciates a good
            deal more a thing for which it has to pay than something which it gets for nothing, and
            it is the same with editors. I make a rule now not to give anything for nothing, except
            on the rarest occasions, and I have found this method to work very well.</p>
         <p>Perhaps Richard’s tastes are too scholarly for the American public. The Letters he is
            writing to Greek Ladies in "The Dial" I feel quite sure would not appeal to any other
            paper, but there are plenty of things which he could write about, and which would be
            interesting to write about, that the more enterprising papers would be glad to print. I
            do think that the best</pb> thing possible would be for you and Richard to come over here
            sometime and see how things are for yourself, for I am firmly convinced that the market
            now will be America and not England. I do not want Richard to feel dampened in any way
            by all this, there is certainly not the slightest need of that, only I do want him to
            spend more time on completely original work and not spend so much time with the works of
            other authors, be they ancient Greeks or modern Frenchmen. His work is immensely liked,
            and he stands a chance of having a large and flourishing clientele. To my mind the only
            excuse for devoting so much time to translation would be that one needed the money and
            this was a way to get it. When that is not the case, I think it is really in almost
            every instance a waste of time. Certainly it is, unless it is kept very much at a
            minimum in proportion to one’s original work.</p>
         <p>This is a long screed, but I thought that perhaps you could explain to Richard, a sort
            of supplement to what I am telling him, and as I said at the beginning, this does not
            mean that I will not do everything in my power to push the thing along, because of
            course I will.</p>
         <p>Do write and tell me how you are when you get this. I am sorry to bother you with
            Flint’s draft, but I have no idea how to reach him otherwise.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
