<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1918-06-15">15 June 1918</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$75i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington Bosigram, Pendeen,
                        <placeName key="cornwall">Cornwall</placeName>, <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned. Includes a postscript.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1918-06-15">June 15, 1918.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I have your letter of <date when="1918-05-09">May 9th</date>. You did not date it, but that is what the postmark says,
            so I suppose that is right.</p>
         <p>I am awfully glad that you agree with me about <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s poems. I was so afraid you
            would not, and I hated to seem disagreeable. I know that what I said about them is true,
            but I do not think that I can produce any effect on him. I am too far away, and he
            would probably think me too far removed from the life he is leading to understand his
            attitude. In fact, that is evidently what he does think, for I have had a letter from
            him written on <date when="1918-05-14">May 14th</date>. He says that he is quite willing to delete the dates in "Nights
            of Love" but he does not seem to want to make any other changes. He says, with reference
            to the other points: "I think the lines you quote should be clear to the unbiased mind."
            That seems to settle it, and I do not know what else I can do. It is very good of you to
            think that I have some influence over him and can help him, but I am afraid I have been
            away from him too long, and he knows too little about the march of my own work to have
            very much regard for my opinion. His letter was as nice as it could possibly be, most
            friendly and sympathetic, but he clings to his own opinion, which is natural, after
            all.</p>
         <p>I do understand how you feel about the criticism, and yet I cannot help thinking that as
            his guardian angel you would do well to put a veto on some of those poems. I think he
            will thank you later. But of course that must be for you to decide.</p>
         <p>In giving the poems to <persName key="brown">Brown</persName> over my head, he of course took away my authority, and
            Brown is not a man to stickle at printing anything. His chief business is printing books
            which other publishers do not want,</pb> and he regards himself as emancipated in
            consequence, and pioneers of emancipation seldom admit the law of taste, and as the
            publisher is willing to print them as they are, and Richard wants them so printed, I am
            afraid I have absolutely no authority. I wish I had. I wish I could have got <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>
            to take them, and I wish he could have made the changes. I am also very sorry that he
            gave them to Brown, for I doubt if they ever see the light of day. Brown has had a book
            of <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>’s for two years, and it is not out yet. Perhaps that last will be the saving
            of the situation, although now that he has signed the contract, I doubt whether he could
            get the book back from Brown if he wanted it. I will answer this letter of his of
            course, but I have no hope of there being any change in his attitude unless you can
            bring it about.</p>
         <p>Are you all alone in <placeName key="cornwall">Cornwall</placeName>, or have you some one with you? Do write often. It seems
            so long since I have seen you all, and now that we have no <title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title> to keep us
            together, there is of course a danger of our drifting apart unless we keep on
            writing.</p>
         <p>I am not surprised that Fletcher sets himself up, as you say. That is what I gathered
            from his letters. I am afraid his idiosyncrasies are growing on him, and that he has
            very little future. I will send you my new book when it comes out in the Autumn. I am
            calling it "Can Grande’s Castle," and I am using Richard’s poem, "At the British
            Museum," – that is, quotations from it – as my motto. I am not at all sure whether you
            will like the book as it is all in "polyphonic prose," but I hope you will.</p>
         <p>Much love from both <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and me, dear Hilda, and you can count on me always. I
            wish I could induce Richard to change some of those</pb> poems, but you see how it is.</p>
         <closer>Always affectionately,</closer>
         <postscript>P.S. Did you ever get the article on Richard, <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, and <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> that I
            sent?</postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
