<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1918-04-11">11 April 1918</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$73i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington 44 <placeName
                        key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>
                     <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1918-04-11">April 11, 1918.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:-</salute></opener>
         <p><persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s book did not come for weeks after the letter about it. It finally reached me
            in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> a week or two ago. I kept it until I came home for reasons which I have told
            Richard in my letter to him, and I am sending it to <persName key="brown">Brown</persName> to-day. I think it is splendid
            work, but I will not duplicate what I said about it in my letter to Richard, as I want
            you to read that letter and if you do not think I ought to have said anything that I
            did, or if you think that it will trouble him, please just tear the letter up, or keep
            it for yourself, or send it to him mutilated and play the censor did it. The letter is
            meant as much for you as for him, therefore, I am not enclosing it in a separate
            envelope, but putting it in with yours, so that you can read all my news before sending
            it on to Richard.</p>
         <p>Do write often again. I care so much to hear. You will probably be able to answer my
            questions about <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> better than Richard will. If you can find out anything without
            seeming to do so, I shall be eternally obliged.</p>
         <p>I think you will like what I said about Richard in my lecture. I hope so at any rate. I
            shall include this paper on Richard in a volume of lectures and essays which I shall get
            out before long. In the meanwhile, I am hard at work on a long poem which will come out
            in a book of poems that I am publishing this Autumn.</p>
         <p>Please send me a copy of "<title key="newPaths">New Paths</title>" when it comes out, as I shall be very glad to see
            it. You will be amused to know that one of the chapters of my "<title key="tendencies">Tendencies</title>" is to
            appear in the "<title key="revueDeParis">Revue de Paris</title>," and that a Spanish</pb> translation of my poems is to be
            issued in <placeName key="mexico">Mexico</placeName>. You see, my dear, the only thing to do is to hang on. I do believe
            that time brings recognition, if we do not let ourselves get kicked off the tree before
            it comes.</p>
         <p>This war is terribly hard. The hardest of all for you, I think. You cannot imagine how
            much <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and I think of you, and how often we speak of you, and how we wish we
            were there to give you the glad hand while Richard is away.</p>
         <closer>Ever so much from us both,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
