<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1920-10-27">27 October 1920</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$114i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Miss Winifred Ellerman
                     Carmel Highlands Inn Carmel by the sea <placeName key="monterey"
                        >Monterey</placeName>, <placeName key="california">California</placeName>.
                     Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1920-10-27">October 27, 1920.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Since writing a letter to <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> yesterday, I have had another communication from
            <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> of the <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin Company</orgName>. He says that he thinks <placeName key="england">England</placeName> is the
            best place to have the <title>book</title><!--not sure which. Translations? Hymen?--> set up in, and he will be perfectly willing to take a
            certain number of sheets for sale in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>. He thinks you have a larger audience
            in England still than you have in America, and perhaps that is true. He is going to
            England in February and he proposes to take the manuscript of the book with him,
            arranging for a publisher there – I imagine it will be <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> since he is their agent
            – and arranging to have the sheets brought back here.</p>
         <p>If I were you, I should accept this, for I am inclined to believe that this estimate of
            your popularity in England is correct, and I think Houghton Mifflin are a much better
            firm for this kind of thing than <orgName key="holt">Holt</orgName>, whom I mentioned to Winifred in my letter
            yesterday. I do not think the thing will go to pieces in any way if you leave it in
            Ferris’s hands and if you give me carte blanche to arrange with him as I would for
            myself, or, if you prefer, he will communicate with you directly. He was perfectly
            willing to do so, but I told him to wait before I was afraid to trouble you with
            business details.</p>
         <p>If this matter meets with your approval, I will tell Ferris to go ahead and see what
            arrangements he can make in England. If you would prefer to try America first, I will
            send it to Holt, as I proposed to do in my letter to Winifred, but of course, in that
            case, it will be difficult to go back again to Ferris Greenslet, supposing Holt should
            refuse. There are other publishers, but I think none as good as Houghton Mifflin or
            <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>. I doubt whether <orgName key="harcourtBraceHowe">Harcourt, Brace &amp; Howe</orgName>, who go in very much for the socialist
            radical books, would care for the book. <orgName key="knopf">Knopf</orgName> is feeling poor at the moment,</pb> and I am much averse to trying new upstarts
            like <orgName key="thomas_seltzer">Thomas Seltzer</orgName>, and there is simply no hope of the old fogy publishers like
            <orgName key="scribner">Scribner</orgName> and <orgName key="harper">Harper</orgName>. My advice would be to leave it in Ferris’s hands and see what he
            can do. He wants your name on his list, but he is a little afraid to risk entire
            publication in this country.</p>
         <p>Much love, dear Hilda, and I do trust that <placeName key="monterey">Monterey</placeName> will do as much good as it sounds as
            if it would. Winifred makes it out perfectly delightful, and I wish I were with you
            dabbling my feet in the ocean and looking at that lovely view which I remember so well.
            Instead of that, I go to bed on Friday and am cut into little pieces. Let me know what
            to do about Ferris, and believe me,</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
