<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1918-10-03">03 October 1918</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$84i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington care of Mrs. Randall, 3
                     Christchurch Place Hampstead, <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, N.W.
                        <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1918-10-03">October 3, 1918.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I have sent you my new book<!--which book?-->. Perhaps I should say <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s book, seeing as how he is
            the presiding deity over my volume. I trust that you will like it, but I am afraid that
            you will not. I seem to remember that Richard, after once having praised "polyphonic
            prose," went back on it, so possibly you will not care for the volume, considering its
            form. However, such as it is, here it is.</p>
         <p>To me came your good letter of what date I cannot say, since you never date them, but
            the one in which you tell me that <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Bryher</persName> is not Winifred Bryher. My dear, what
            a bomb shell! Who on earth is she? My mind does not run easily on the purlieus of
            "richest men." I have not the ghost of an idea who is rich in <placeName key="england">England</placeName> and who is poor. I
            had an idea that the Duke of Westminster was the richest man in England, but from what
            you say I can hardly suppose that Winifred is a young peeress. The only other things
            that I can think of are a cosmopolitan banker and a large, native, good-natured
            brewer.</p>
         <p>But, in either case, I cannot see what that has to do with Winifred, and I regard her
            self-consciousness on the subject as extremely foolish, and I would write and tell her
            so, only you tell me that I must not mention it to her.</p>
         <p>It is a handicap to be even well off. My father was not the "richest" anywhere, and yet
            I have had enough trouble as I am in getting people to realize that I may be a decent
            poet even if I am not starving in a garret. But it can be done I know, and I am happy to
            say that I think all the newspapers and the people who once regarded me as an</pb> amateur
            because necessity was not howling under my windows have now given up all thoughts of me
            as anything but a hard-working and serious writer.</p>
         <p>Winifred need not hide her name under a bushel. She ought really to rejoice on the added
            handicap, and as to thinking that anybody would like her<add place="above"> only</add> on account of her money –
            my but that is a snobbish thought! One has known even multi-millionaires and kept one’s
            head, and, after all, Winifred did not make the money any more than she made her nose.
            (In confidence, my dear, is she of the race that has a nose, and is that perhaps the
            difficulty?) She is no more to be courted for that fact than for anything else for which
            she is not responsible. Anyhow, I cannot help thinking that she would do better if she
            did not hide under a nom de plume, and anyhow I am quite sure that she should trust me
            with her real name – a secret which I will promise not to divulge if she does not wish
            it – and you can assure her that I do not care a button whether she is a charwoman or a
            princess of the blood royal. For God’s sake tell her that we are Americans, you and I,
            and these things do not matter.</p>
         <p>I think that she has a promise; I think that she needs sympathy and encouragement; I
            think that you can do her a lot of good. After all, to think that people will care for
            you anything except your essentials is a form of snobbishness, even if it is a
            backhanded snobbishness. And don’t let her be a snob. It is a mistake, and if she thinks
            that I am a snob – Oh Lord, she ought to meet me!</p>
         <p>Of course tell her that I will be as nice as possible when she comes to <placeName key="usa">America</placeName> and do
            everything to make her stay comfortable. I do not promise to ask her to spend the Winter
            with me in the fashion that</pb> the English love so well, (but that, perhaps, you need not
            say,) but she can count on me in every possible way. Certainly I owe her a great deal
            for her interest and all that she is doing for me over there, as she seems to have
            aroused Mr. <persName key="clement_shorter">Shorter</persName> to a violent partisanship on our side which, although it may annoy
            certain of the younger men, I think cannot fail to do us good. As to Mr. Shorter’s
            conservatism – what can you expect? The wonder to me is that he sees anything in us at
            all. He is, however, a kindly, cosmopolitan, well-read gentleman, and, not being <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>, I
            approve of not quenching his smoking flax. I am thankful for all the appreciation that
            we can get, and I never ask impossibilities of the middle aged, or of the conservative
            papers from which I have received some amusing clippings.</p>
         <p>I understand that he is going to write a paper on your Greek translations soon for "<title key="sphere">The Sphere</title>."</p>
         <p>I thought that Winifred’s little article on all of us in "<title key="saturdayReview">The Saturday Review</title>" was very
            interesting. I think that she should be a little more explicit as to what we have
            written, because I do not think that people know us well enough to jump right away at
            the knowledge that she assumes that they have, and I think she errs on the side of
            over-exuberance and praise – an unfortunate fault for the subjects of her articles, as
            over-praise always brings its own antidote in the reader’s mind, just as over-blame
            does. But these things are slight and few, compared with the many things that she does
            well and her genuine understanding and enthusiasm.</p>
         <p>As to <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>, I despair of him. I had a letter from him the day after I had yours,
            full of carping criticism and somewhat silly</pb> violence. He seems to have got it into his
            head that I am his enemy instead of his friend, I do not know why, but I know him well
            enough to know that there is never any use in remonstrating by letter. He makes such
            ridiculous statements, such as that he has not seen any of our crowd since the
            beginning of the year and then the following, "I feel that I must travel my own track
            and they theirs." As if one could not see any one who is not writing exactly as one is
            writing one’s self; In that case, dear Hilda, neither you nor I would see anybody at
            all. We would live in a charming but icy isolation, contemplating our own navels and
            gradually folding up inside out.</p>
         <p>I regard Fletcher as a purely pathological case. I am fond of him, but I think he is
            perfectly unsatisfactory, and I confess that this new manner of writing does not give me
            any pleasure, at least none of the poems that I have seen in this later style have. I
            did not care for his two contributions to <persName key="michael_sadler">Sadler</persName>’s "<title key="newPaths">New Paths</title>." And, by the way, why
            were you not represented in that volume. Richard said that he had asked you both to
            contribute. I am afraid that you are hypercritical of your own work. I wish that I were
            there to give you a jolt and tell you how frightfully good it is, and now that the war
            news is so good I cannot help thinking that some time or other we shall all meet again
            and resume the happy intercourse that we had before. Certainly those seven short weeks
            that we all passed together in 1914 have made all the difference in my life, and
            certainly you and Richard are among the best friends I have.</p>
         <p>It is splendid to know that Richard has such a good job and is out of danger. I have
            just received word that my nephew has been distin</pb><!--pb in middle of word-->>guishing himself on the firing line, so
            I feel quite happy. Richard asked me to tell him his name and address, so that in case
            they were ever together, he might look him up. Here it is:</lb> 
            Captain <persName key="james_roosevelt">James A. Roosevelt</persName>,</lb>
            302nd Ammunition Train,</lb>
            77th Division,</lb>
            American Expeditionary Force</p>
         <p>I have had a letter from <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> which tells me that he has dedicated <title key="newPoems">his last book of poems</title> to me. He seems frightfully blue, and I do not see how he can be otherwise. His
            prospects certainly are far from bright. It is no use telling him that it is his own
            fault. His principle is never to bow to the taste of the public, and although I think a
            certain amount of compromise is necessary, still his attitude is fine if suicidal.</p>
         <p>Please tell me all about your call on Winifred, which you said that you were going to
            make the afternoon you wrote. And please, oh please, dear Hilda, tell me the girl’s
            name! If you prefer I will not mention that you told it to me. I will keep it shut up in
            my heart, but I feel as if I must know it.</p>
         <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> sends her best love, and so do I, and please pass it on to Richard to whom
            I will write in a few days.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
