<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1924-12-16">16 December 1924</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$144i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Manager, Lloyd’s Bank, 67
                     Kingsway, <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W.C.2. <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1924-12-16">December 16, 1924.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>A delightful little Christmas card came from you this morning. I am so glad to get it.
            But how far ahead of me you have got! It never occurred to me to send my European
            Christmas cards until this week, and now you make me fear that mine to you will come
            after the day, which, although it may have become a habit, is nevertheless
            regrettable.</p>
         <p>My dear, your "<title key="heliodora">Heliodora</title>" is superb! I have not really been able to read it yet with the
            thoroughness that I want to, slim volume though it is, because I only finished the
            corrections of my "<title key="johnKeats">Keats</title>" yesterday, and nobody knows what a grind that book has been,
            but I have read enough of "Heliodora" to realize that it is no fall from "<title key="hymen">Hymen</title>," on the
            contrary, it is a magnificent thing. Mr. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Greenslet</persName> tells me what <orgName key="boniLiveright">Boni &amp; Liveright</orgName> are to
            publish a collected edition of your books, for which I am heartily thankful, although I
            wish it were not Boni &amp; Liveright but <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName>. But Houghton Mifflin are so slow
            to jump when they should. It will be a comfort to have your "<title key="seaGarden">Sea Garden</title>" in print again.
            People are always asking me where they can get it. I enc</p>
         <p>I am enclosing a little card which the publishers have printed for my book, which,
            between us, we did not get out for Christmas. It means that my real Christmas present to
            you, the book itself, will follow as soon as it is issued.</p>
         <p>I also enclose a draft for the last two royalty payments on the surviving "<title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title>." The account is as follows:</lb>
            3 Imagist Poets at .671/2 2.03</lb>
            10 " " 1916 at .67-1/2 6.75</lb>
            11 " " 1917 " " 7.43</lb>
            1/6 of 16.21 is <measure type="currency" num="$2.70">$2.70</measure></pb> This represents both the
            February 1924 and the August 1924 payments, which I am sending together as they are both
            so small. The two first anthologies went out of print with the August statement, and
            there are only six copies of the "1917" left, so we shall soon have done with them
            altogether.</p>
         <p>I have not heard a word from <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> for ever so long. It is entirely my fault. She
            wrote and told me that she was unable to do the article on me as she had planned, and
            what should she do with the manuscript I sent her. And I have never answered her, owing
            entirely to pressure of work. I have been grinding at this book so steadily that I have
            not been able to keep up with my mail at all. Four years and two months I have been at
            it, and I am so weary to the core, but I have a sort of colt-let-out-in-a-meadow kind of
            feeling now that it is all over.</p>
         <p>I am going to <placeName key="england">England</placeName> – think of it, after eleven years! We are sailing on the
            Berengaria for <placeName key="southampton">Southampton</placeName> on April fifteenth, and I expect to give some lectures and
            readings while I am there. I have quite a number booked. We shall stay until about the
            middle of July and then sail for home again without going on to <placeName key="europe">the continent</placeName> at all.
            Some other time I hope to go to <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName> again, but my initial trip, after all these many
            operations of mine, will not take me beyond England. I do hope you will manage to be in
            <placeName key="london">London</placeName> while we are there. It seems so long since we have met, and I am so anxious to
            see you again.</p>
         <p>I hope you will like my book. I shall be dreadfully disappointed if you do not, but I
            hope you will like still better the poetry volume which I expect to bring out a year
            from now. After all, poetry is my real job.</p>
         <p>What happened to your book of essays on Greek subjects, the one which I read the
            manuscript of and spoke to Ferris Greenslet about? Is that coming out with Boni &amp;
            Liveright’s collected edition or not? There are so many people I should like to give it
            to.</p></pb> 
         <p>Drop us a line, dear Hilda, and tell us your news. I got a
            little breath of you from <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> in the Summer, but it seems a long time since
            I have heard from you yourself, and that made the Christmas card particularly
            welcome.</p>
         <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> sends her love, and so do I, both to you and your <persName key="helen_doolittle">mother</persName>, if she is with
            you.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
