<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1918-08-13">13 August 1918</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$78i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington 44 <placeName
                        key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>
                     <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1918-08-13">August 13, 1918.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am perfectly delighted with this photograph of <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> which <persName key="helen_doolittle">your mother</persName> sent to me. I
            think it is the best one of him that I have ever seen. Personally, I like him better
            without the beard which appeared after I left, and which showed in the only other
            photograph of him which I had. He looks well, which is good to see, and brings him up
            before me so vividly that it makes me more homesick than ever.</p>
         <p>I have not heard from you for ages. I rather thought that I should get a letter after
            you got my article, and that you got it I know, for <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> wrote me that you had sent
            it to him. Perhaps your letter went down, but I am tormented with the fact that perhaps
            you did not like the article, and hence your silence. That would really grieve me very
            much, so that I hope it is merely my hyper-sensitive desire to get a little on paper of
            my great admiration for Richard’s work, I was so sorry not to be able to include him in
            my book that I specially wanted you to like this article. But I try to console myself by
            feeling that probably your letter is sitting at the bottom of the broad <placeName key="atlanticOcean">Atlantic</placeName>.</p>
         <p>Here are our half-yearly royalties:</lb> 
            <hi rend="underline">SALES</hi></lb>
            34 <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title>, 1915 at .36-1/4 12.33</lb> 
            24 " " 1916 at .36-1/4 8.70</lb> 
            71 " " 1917 at .36-1/4 25.74</lb>
            $46.77</lb>
            $46,77 divided by 6-$7.76 or 1.11.9</lb>
            They are not, as you see, of a very magnificent figure, but that can hardly be
            expected. The War has cut into everybody’s sales – everybody who is not writing war
            books, that is.</p></pb>
         <p>As I wrote you last year, I am now letting the Anthologies go slowly, but surely, out of
            print. I wrote to all of you and asked your advice on the subject, <add place="above">last year</add> and all of
            you that deigned to reply agreed. I do not remember whether <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> gave his opinion, and
            I am quite sure that Lawrence never gave his, but the price of reprinting now is so
            great and the sales so inconsiderable, and the fact that most of the poems in those
            books have been reprinted in our own various books makes me feel that we had better let
            them lapse. If you have changed your mind since you agreed, let me know, because, of
            course, I want to be quite fair on the subject. But I do think it is probably better for
            all of us to have people now forced to buy our individual books rather than getting us
            this way.</p>
         <p>There are now on hand:</lb>
            4 Copies of "Some Imagist Poets – 1915."</lb>
            147 " " "Some Imagist Poets – 1916."</lb>
            94 " " "Some Imagist Poets – 1917."</lb>
            So you see that it will not be a great while before they are unobtainable. Then they will probably be greatly desired by
            collectors and bought at enormous figures at auctions, and we shall gain nothing
            thereby. But such is the way of fame!</p>
         <p>I wonder if you have come across a little pamphlet on me written by an unknown admirer,
            Miss <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Bryher</persName>. I know nothing whatever about the girl; perhaps you do. She is a
            great admirer of yours, and writes really extremely good poetry. But this pamphlet is
            the first of her published works, I believe. I judge that she has been very much
            protected and cared for by Mr. <persName key="clement_shorter">Clement K. Shorter</persName>, the editor of "<title key="sphere">The Sphere</title>", and other
            gentlemen of good standing, since her pamphlet has been sent not</pb> only to all the English
            newspapers, but to all the American periodicals as well, and I can hardly think that a
            new writer would have thought of doing this without advice.</p>
         <p>Her book has been reviewed most favourably by Mr. Shorter in "The Sphere" and by some
            one in "<title key="tatler">The Tatler</title>," and by some one else in the Literary Supplement of the "<title key="times">Times</title>." But
            it has been fearfully slammed by an oaf named <persName key="james_douglas">James Douglas</persName> in "<title key="star">The Star</title>." The
            papers here are principally amused that she should consider me unknown, which is
            flattering as far as it goes.</p>
         <p>Seriously, the girl has insight and a good deal of critical faculty, but she expresses
            herself with such extreme admiration that I am afraid<add place="above"> that</add> perhaps her very words cause
            their own reaction.</p>
         <p>I have had a very characteristic letter from <persName key="michael_sadler">Michael Sadler</persName>, asking me if it did not
            embarrass me to have a pamphlet written about me. Perhaps it does a little, considering
            the terms she uses, but I am very grateful to her just the same. There is still too much
            misunderstanding for one not to be glad to find such whole-hearted sympathy, and the
            fact that I have never seen the girl, and know no one whom she knows, shows that it came
            entirely through the poems.</p>
         <p>I wish that I could send you a copy. Unfortunately it is not to be bought on this side
            of the ocean. It is published by the <orgName key="eyreSpottiswoode">Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode</orgName>, and probably your circulating
            library could produce it if you care to see it.</p>
         <p>I feel quite sure that the <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> crowd will get hold of it and</pb> make awful fun of it in
            "<title key="egoist">The Egoist</title>," but possibly that will not do a great deal of harm, even if they do. What
            does Ezra mean in his ultimatum in the last number of "<title key="littleReview">The Little Review</title>"? It sounds
            almost as if he were going to withdraw from that Paper. It has made not hit on this side
            of the ocean at all. I do not know what Ezra’s particular crowd may think of it since he
            undertook so much of the management, but here it is unknown and unconsidered, and <persName key="james_joyce">James Joyce</persName>’s pornographic obscenities have not even caused a ripple of interest outside of
            <placeName key="greenwichVillage">Greenwich Village</placeName>, where, I suppose, they are considered even as the Bible.</p>
         <p>Do you remember my writing to you last year telling you what a gratuitous insult <persName key="wc_williams">William Carlos Williams</persName> had thrown at me in a series of letters? Well, by way of making things
            too funny, here comes a very pleasant note from him in praise of "Appuldurocombe Park,"
            which came out in the August number of "<title key="poetry">Poetry</title>." Oh, Hilda, things are odd!</p>
         <p>You cannot think how hungry and thirsty I am for a sight of you and Richard. So many
            poets here have gone to the war, and the travelling expenses are now so high, that we
            meet each other very seldom in this vast country; and as there are none settled here in
            <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>, with the exception of <persName key="conrad_aiken">Conrad Aiken</persName> with whom I have a continued and to me quite
            unintelligible feud, it is lonely in the extreme.</p>
         <p>I find, as the war goes on, that it is increasingly difficult to take things out of
            one’s brain when one never has any stimulus of other poets to put things in. Luckily, I
            have a good deal to run on, but somehow I feel that if the war does not end soon we
            shall all be done, all</pb> people would be in prison cells.</p>
         <p>My health, too, is so precarious and so rotten that it makes all travelling an added
            burden. However, I do not mean to croak, as I am very much better off than most
            people.</p>
         <p>I sent to Sadler for some copies of "<title key="newPaths">New Paths</title>," and he said that he was sending it to
            me, but it has not come yet. I am most anxious to see all the things that you have been
            doing.</p>
         <p>I cannot get Richard’s proofs out of <persName key="brown">Brown</persName>. He has asked me to read them for him, but he
            never sends me any, and whether he is going to get along without my intervention, or
            whether he is just as usual procrastinating, I do not know.</p>
         <p>Your mother says that I had better send my letters to <placeName key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>, as you may
            not stay in <placeName key="cornwall">Cornwall</placeName> very long, so I am sending this there and hope that it will be
            promptly forwarded. Do tell me how yours and Richard’s work is getting on.</p>
         <closer>Always affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
