<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1920-02-03">03 February 1920</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$106i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington care of Sir <persName
                        key="john_ellerman">John Ellerman</persName> 1 South Audley Street
                        <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W. 1, <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1920-02-03">February 3, 1920.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Thank you ever so much for your letter of <date when="1920-01-01">January 1st</date>, which came just as I was starting
            out on a lecture trip, so I have waited until now to answer it. Now I am going to have
            an operation this week, and I do not know when I shall be up to writing again.</p>
         <p>It was awfully nice of you to be so interested in the <orgName key="contemporaryClub">Contemporary Club</orgName> row. I was only
            annoyed with them because I had especially stipulated that there should be no
            discussion. I think that the time for discussing the new poetry has gone by. I am
            willing to talk about it, explain it, anything, but I will not stand up to be badgered
            even with the result, as always happens, of my beating my opponents. But at the
            Contemporary Club there was no possibility of discussion, since all they did was to call
            me names. I had used some of your work and some of <persName key="carl_sandburg">Sandburg</persName>’s to illustrate my points,
            so you and Sandburg came in for a round robin of diatribes, and I personally was called
            every name you possibly can think of which was insulting. As there was no way of
            answering these gentlemen, except by saying "You’re another," I refused to answer at
            all, merely telling the Club that I had made this stipulation about there being no
            discussion, that it had been agreed to by their secretary, and that I did not think they
            were keeping faith with me. On the whole I think my silence scored as well as any
            eloquence would have done. But I realized after that meeting more than I had ever
            realized before how impossible it was for you to live in <placeName key="philadelphia">Philadelphia</placeName>.</p>
         <p>I am happy to say that Philadelphia is now in the last century, and that in other places
            there is a very different attitude. New York is</pb> most anxious to hear everything. I had 921 people to hear me read at 
            <placeName key="stMarksBouwerie">St. Mark’s in-the-Bouwerie</placeName> in November, and 720 at <placeName key="columbiaU">Columbia University</placeName> a few days later, so
            you can see that there is an interest, and even those in the high places are taking
            things up. I am to give the Phi Beta Kappa poem at Columbia University in June, and what
            is still funnier, so funny that it causes me to smile, I am to receive the degree of
            Doctor of Literature from <placeName key="BaylorU">a Western University</placeName> this Commencement. Oh, Hilda, but the
            world is a funny place!</p>
         <p>I sold "The Islands" to the "<title key="northAmericanReview">North American Review</title>," and it has already appeared, so I
            suppose you have the cheque by this time. "Thetis" is at the moment being considered by
            "<title key="bookman">The Bookman</title>," and I certainly hope they will take it. When may we expect another book
            from you, my dear? Before long, I hope. But certainly I have been too ill to think of
            books. <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> writes that she hopes you are going to <placeName key="greece">Greece</placeName> with her. I wonder if you
            do. Personally, I think that the charms of your baby will keep you where you are, and I
            imagine that travelling with Winifred is a bit strenuous. Soon an eager child must
            require a dragon of strength to keep up with her it seems to me. I do hope that she will
            come to <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>. I think that it will do her good and open her eyes, and I believe that
            she stands much more chance of getting an audience here than she does at home.</p>
         <p>Of course I should be delighted to write the Preface to her book. I only did not say so
            in loud tones because I did not want to make her feel obliged to have me. She is such a
            queer child that I am always afraid of treading on her toes, and I did not want to seem
            to push myself in where she did not want me to be. It is unfortunate that her
            knowledge of business</pb> is so slight for
            instead of giving <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>’s letter to me to <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> and letting them decide what
            they would do, and then letting me decide what I would do about the Preface, she
            returned the letter to me, which means that the whole transaction is to do over again,
            and now she tells me that Constable is printing her book over there, which changes the
            proposition entirely. However, I saw Mr. <persName key="ec_marsh">Marsh</persName> when I was in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>, and he says that
            he thinks they will be perfectly willing to take sheets on condition that I write the
            Preface for the book, so I have sent the letter back to Winifred and told her this, and
            possibly something will happen now.</p>
         <p>You asked me what I thought of your little friend <persName key="viola_jordan">Viola Jordan</persName>. She was a little fresh,
            but rather pleasantly so, and she was so genuinely enthusiastic that I enjoyed seeing
            her. Her <persName key="virgil_jordan">husband</persName> is a very nice fellow; he seemed very quiet and dependable. She is what
            the French call<foreign xml:lang="fr"><add place="above"> une</add> <hi rend="underline">fausse naïve</hi></foreign>. She poses as if she were very
            simple and innocent, but I think myself that she is far more developed mentally and far
            shrewder than she would give the impression of being. I do not personally care for poses
            and should have preferred her to be natural, but, nevertheless, I enjoyed them both.
            They have been playing with the <placeName key="greenwichVillage">Greenwich Village</placeName> crowd a good deal, and she has got
            rather tired of it, as, indeed, has every one else. It amuses me to observe as we go on
            how those of us who are sincere and whose work is a part of ourselves, our very flesh
            and blood, rise to the top, while those who wrote with the surface or shell go gradually
            under.</p>
         <p>The "<title key="littleReview">Little Review</title>" has got queerer and queerer until now it is really almost crazy, and
            nobody has any respect for it at all. I never think of writing for it, and I think
            nobody else of any standing does. The "<title key="dial">Dial</title>"</pb> has been sold to a young <orgName key="harvard">Harvard</orgName> man named <persName key="schofield_thayer">Schofield Thayer</persName> and they are trying to
            make it into a sort of "<title key="sevenArts">Seven Arts</title>." Only one number of the revised magazine has
            appeared as yet. They have turned it into a monthly and may do something with it, but I
            have my doubts, as I think their probably object is to make an organ in which the
            recently graduated Harvard man can air his views and his work, and there do not seem to
            be any such of any great talent at present. They have not asked me to contribute which I
            take is a sign that they are keeping it more or less in a ring. I wanted to go to see
            them when I was in New York, but did not have the time. They have every reason to
            succeed. The owner is a rich man, and this is his hobby, but I doubt whether they
            do.</p>
         <p><title key="poetry"><persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>’s magazine</title> goes along in its own way. It has its own clientele, but it has no
            influence whatever outside of a small group. It is exceedingly funny to me that a woman
            could have had a magazine running for six years and never increase its circulation to
            any amount that counts as a circulation and have no influence on the growth of poetry in
            any way. It would horrify her if she knew this was the case, but it is, and it is
            surprising and shows Harriet’s glorious ineptness better than anything else could
            possibly do. Poetry is a power over here. People are avid for it. Poets have no
            difficulty in getting published. The public is large; the editors eager. And to conduct
            a poetry magazine which has not counted at all is really a bit singular.</p>
         <p>My own books are selling more all the time, which pleases me, and even the poor, dear,
            old <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthologies</title>, which we are letting go out of print, still have a sale for
            their remainder as you will see by the enclosed <measure type="currency">money order</measure><!--not sure what to do with this because no amount-->. The sale is not brilliant,
            but it still shows a</pb> demand, although not
            enough to keep the books in print.</p>
         <p>Do write to me again and cheer up my convalescence and tell me all your plans. Do let me
            know whether or not you did go with Winifred or where you are. <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> wrote me that you
            were with the Ellermans so I am sending this letter here.</p>
         <closer><persName key="ada_russell">Ada</persName> joins me in much love, 
            Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
