<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1917-02-16">16 February 1917</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$49i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1917-02-16">February 16, 1917.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Our half-yearly statement has come in, showing the sales of our two volumes of <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title> up to <date when="1917-02-01">February 1st</date>, from which you will see that we made <measure type="currency" num="$167.66">$167.66</measure>. The <measure type="currency" num="$1.50">$1.50</measure> refers
            to a copy which was bound especially for a subscriber and which they charged me for on
            the last bill by accident. Yours and <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s shares, therefore, are each <measure type="currency" num="$27.94">$27.94</measure>.
            Besides which there is <measure type="currency" num="$10.00">$10.00</measure> which "<title key="sevenArts">The Seven Arts</title>" paid him for the poems "On the
            March" and "Leave Taking", and <measure type="currency" num="$5.00">$5.00</measure> from <persName key="brown">Brown</persName> on that original contract. I have added
            all this together in one draft for 16+16+4, which I enclose. Brown now has only $5.00
            more to pay on that contract. I think in a former letter I told you that he had nothing
            more to pay, but I misunderstood it. I have since looked up the receipts, and found
            there is still $5.00 more due.</p>
         <p>To my great distress <persName key="james_oppenheim">James Oppenheim</persName> found that he could not publish "On the March" and
            "Leave Taking" in time for them to appear in our Anthology, and I thought it was more
            important for Richard to keep them in "The Seven Arts", partly because of getting more
            money for them, and partly because it is well to appear in different places. As I have
            so few of Richard’s things to choose from, and no time to do it in, the manuscript being
            already at the printers, I had no time to communicate with you, I substituted "Dawn" and
            "Images" for the poems left out. I hope this will meet with your approval. At any rate,
            I did what I thought would be the best thing.</p>
         <p>I am correcting the proofs of the book today. You will be glad to know that our first
            volume is in the third edition, and our second volume is in the second edition, and that
            <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName> sent for more</pb> sheets of the first volume no longer ago than last month,
            showing that it is still selling in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. I think that the renewed interest that the
            press in your country is showing in us is a very encouraging thing. Did you see poor Mr.
            <persName key="bourdillon">Bourdillon</persName>’s letter in <title key="times">The Times</title>? How the stand-patters do fight and how surely they are
            being pushed aside!</p>
         <p>I got your letter saying that you had no anecdote. I had already taken the liberty of
            writing to <persName key="helen_doolittle">your mother</persName> for certain data such as where you were born, where you were
            educated, etc. She replied that you were so reticent yourself that she could give me the
            barest details, but I have done the best I can, and I hope you will like book when it
            comes out.</p>
         <p>Now I want a photograph for the volume. It is to be like my "<title key="sixFrenchPoets">Six French Poets</title>" with
            photographs and signatures of each of the poets. I have a little photograph of you that
            you sent me last summer, but, in one of his letters to me, Richard said that you were
            sending me an "Art" photograph of yourself, but this has never come. Now I am a very
            selfish person, and I do not want to sacrifice this one photograph that I have to the
            lithographers because they invariably dirty and generally spoil everything that they
            touch. Not only do I want this photograph, but Mr. <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> wants it for the <title key="bostonTranscript">Boston Transcript</title>, and he wants it P.D.Q., for he wants to put in a review of you. Therefore,
            will you please send it by return mail. Even return mail will be dreadfully slow.</p>
         <p>I enclose a very nice little mention of your book from "<title key="outlook">The Outlook</title>". Really that book
            of yours was a perfect gem. I don’t know anything that gave me a greater pleasure than
            minutely studying your work for my lecture. It taught me a great many thing. Your
            perfection in</pb> your own medium is something to make every poet proud for you and
            despairing for himself.</p>
         <p>While I was in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>, I had a very interesting time with Mr. <persName key="patterson">Patterson</persName> of the
            Department of English of <placeName key="columbiaU">Columbia University</placeName>, who has written a book on prose rhythm. He
            announced, in his book, that vers libre was only prose. I met him one afternoon and told
            him that I thought he was mistaken, and on that account he invited me to his laboratory
            where for an hour and a half I read your "Oread" into a sound machine, with the result
            that he has written me that he is now willing to admit what he was not willing to admit
            before, that the cadences of vers libre are not the cadences of prose. He was very sad
            when I left New York, for it is hard for him to work without me, as he knows very little
            about the aesthetic side of the free forms; but I think, through correspondence, and
            through seeing him occasionally, we may be able to make some interesting experiments,
            which will end by proving conclusively to the doubters that vers libre is by no means
            the chopped prose they think. At any rate it is a very interesting experiment.</p>
         <p>I have not time to write any more now, as I am starting out on a lecture tour in the
            West and things are pressing.</p>
         <p>Send the photograph instanter, and please send your full signature on a separate piece
            of paper so that I can reproduce it beneath the photograph for the book.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
