<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1921-01-13">13 January 1921</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$116i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Four pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington Mrs. Richard Aldington ‘Leven
                     Oaks Hotel Monrovia <placeName key="california">California</placeName>. On the
                     first page, the date was originally given as 13 January 20; "20" was crossed
                     out in pencil, and "21" was written in its place. Subsequent pages read "13
                     January 21." Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1921-01-13">January 13, 1921.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Thank you very much for your letter of <date when="1920-12-22">December 22nd</date>. I should have answered it sooner,
            but really, my dear, you can understand how difficult it is to catch up with things, I
            have been ill so long; and then <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> insist upon my <title key="legends">legend book</title> coming out
            in April, which means that the manuscript must be in in March, and one of the legends
            which I have been mulling over during my illness suddenly came to a head and had to be
            written and I had to drop everything and get at it. It is queerer than Dick’s hat-band,
            but I think it will make a good contrast to the others.</p>
         <p>Then <orgName key="yale">Yale</orgName>, who has never smiled either upon new poets or upon women, was suddenly seized
            with a desire to have me come down there and give one of the lectures of the <orgName key="francisBergenFoundation">Francis
            Bergen Foundation</orgName>. This time it is to be on the centenary of <persName key="john_keats">Keats</persName>’s death, and means a
            lecture on Keats; and as a kind of <foreign xml:lang="fr">bonne bouche</foreign>, to make up for asking me to talk on
            some other poet, they have added a reading of my own poems at the <orgName key="elizabethanClub">Elizabethan Club</orgName> the
            day before. As Yale is the only one of the larger colleges at which I have not yet
            spoken, and as they are so sadly in need of a little proselytizing, I thought I had
            better do it. Luckily, I have finished my legend, or virtually so; and therefore I am
            able to start on the Keats lecture; but all this coming so soon after my operation has
            put rather a strain upon me, and my mail has got jiggled off into a corner,
            perforce.</p>
         <p>Please tell <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> that I shall write to her in a day or two, but as your letter
            precedes those of hers which I have not answered, I feel that you come first on the list
            this time. Please tell her that I delight in her letters; they have been the brightest
            star of my illness. She is such a good and faithful correspondent.</p></pb>
         <p>Now, my dear, I have some news for you. Mr. <persName key="robert_holliday">Holliday</persName> of <orgName key="holt">Henry Holt &amp; Company</orgName> wrote
            most enthusiastically welcoming my suggestion that they look over the manuscript of your
            book, "<title key="hymen">Hymen</title>," with a view to publication. I told them all about <persName key="harold_monro">Monro</persName>, but they were
            willing to read the volume as it was, and I sent it to them at once. I have not heard
            anything as yet, but I suppose I shall soon, and I will let you know as soon as I do. I
            have told them that they would have to make arrangements through Monro as he owns the
            copyright, but it is possible that he is not copyrighting it in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>, in which case
            of course it cannot be copyrighted here as it would not be able to come out
            simultaneously with the English edition. I do not think that matters much, as it is not
            like a best seller novel. Lots of English books here are published here that are not
            copyrighted. There the matter is at present, and I will let you or Winifred know as soon
            as a new phase opens.</p>
         <p>Winifred’s accounts of your adventures with your <persName>nurse</persName><!--should this person be tagged?--> fill me with joy. That woman is
            as good as a penny dreadful all by herself, and I am afraid you young things do not hold
            a strong enough hand over her. English servants always have to be held down very
            tightly. They get out of hand if they are allowed the least leeway, at least that is the
            experience of an old housekeeper. I have been keeping house for twenty years with
            various nationalities, and I could write a book on the different ways each has to be
            treated. What between the nurse and the <persName>chauffeur</persName><!--should this person be tagged?--> when you went to <placeName key="sanDiego">San Diego</placeName> I must say
            you are having an exciting time. What I do regret is that we are no nearer together. It
            would be such fun to be able to talk. Now that I am getting back to normal again, I feel
            very much in need of a good talk.</p>
         <p>Winifred says that you want to know somewhere to spend the Summer, but of course you
            must realize that there are so many places that one cannot give you any advice. What
            between East, and West, and mountains, and seas, you</pb> have a variety of
            choice which is simply bewildering. I think if I wanted the sea, I should take the <placeName key="maine">Maine</placeName>
            coast, if I were you. If you wanted sea bathing, I should try the Cape – <placeName key="capeCod">Cape Cod</placeName>, that
            is – or <placeName key="longIsland">Long Island</placeName>. If you want mountains or woods, there is all of <placeName key="newHampshire">New Hampshire</placeName> and
            much of Maine. <placeName key="peterborough">Peterborough</placeName> has the <orgName key="macdowellColony">MacDowell Colony</orgName> of artists and is a lovely country.
            There are lots of places that are not over-fashionable, plenty, I think, of the type you
            want; but what grieves me is that I shall be in none of them. I hope to get over to
            <placeName key="england">England</placeName> this Spring, but the doctor seems to think that May is too soon for me to
            attempt a sea voyage, and I think June would be too late, which would put my going off
            until the Autumn. I distinctly do not want that as I am afraid of the English cold in
            the Autumn. At present I am merely getting well and doing my work.</p>
         <p>I have another month quietly here, and then I start to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> to lecture at the
            <orgName key="brooklynInstitute">Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences</orgName>; from there to Yale for my two lectures, and
            back again to New York for a lecture at <orgName key="columbiaU">Columbia</orgName>. Then I come home for a brief space,
            and dash off for a <orgName key="universityExtensionSociety">University Extension Society</orgName> lecture in <placeName key="philadelphia">Philadelphia</placeName>; and somewhere
            in the offing, <orgName key="brownU">Brown University</orgName>, <orgName key="dartmouth">Dartmouth</orgName>, and <orgName key="smithCollege">Smith College</orgName>, with a plethora of proof
            stuck into the interstices, and, I hope, another legend which cries to be written down.
            You see there is not much time, and I think for a lady who has had two operations in
            eight months, it is not perhaps a bad record.</p>
         <p>Winifred suggests that your book of Greek essays be submitted to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> to
            take abroad with him, but it would be too late for that just now as he sails almost
            immediately; but I would not hurry it, just let it simmer and digest, and next year will
            be quite as good as this year for its publication. Art is long, and the more I see of
            things, the more I am convinced that it is a mistake to hurry anything; and the farther
            away we get</pb> from the war, the better will be the selling possibilities, I
            think. The sales market has been completely knocked out in the general slump of business
            lately, and the publishers are looking very unhappy, so I really think that some months
            hence would be a better time to submit any manuscripts you have than the present would
            be.</p>
         <p>If Holt does take this book of yours, they are a very good firm and much interested in
            modern poetry, more interested, I think, than Houghton Mifflin. In fact, I am inclined
            to think that if I were not with Houghton Mifflin, I should be with Holt. With me, it is
            scarcely a matter of choice as Ferris Greenslet is such an old and tired friend of mine,
            but Holt has got younger and more energetic blood in the firm, and if this book is
            published by them, I do not know why they would not make a good firm to continue to
            publish your American editions. However, we can decide that later when you have a volume
            ready.</p>
         <p>I cannot write any more now as I have a perfect stack of letters to answer, but this
            takes lots of love from <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and me to you both, and most kind rememberances to
            your mother. Winifred’s picture of <persName key="perdita_aldington">Perdita</persName> and her Christmas Presents, which came this
            morning, is absolutely delightful. What a healthy looking little creature she is! Tell
            Winifred to take some snap shots of you and herself, and send them to me.</p>
         <closer>Much love,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
