<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1921-07-06">06 July 1921</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$122i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Manager, Lloyd’s Bank 67
                     Kingsway <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W.C.2, <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned. Includes a postscript.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1921-07-06">July 6, 1921.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I have just received a letter from <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> from <placeName key="zermatt">Zermatt</placeName> in which she speaks of having
            just received "<title key="legends">Legends</title>" which had been following her round from place to place. As I
            sent your copy to <placeName key="audleyStreet">1 South Audley Street</placeName> at the same time I sent hers, in her care, I
            wonder whether by any chance your copy is travelling round after Winifred and she has
            not received it to forward to you. That would only matter because I should not like you
            to think that I did not send you off one of the first copies I received. My allowance
            from the publisher all came at once, and I sent off my presentation copies together, so,
            if you have not received yours and it does not appear on the hall table at 1 South
            Audley Street, let me know and I will forward another.</p>
         <p>From Winifred’s letter, I should imagine that she was having an exact but belated
            honeymoon. She gives me no news whatever about anybody or anything except <persName key="robert_mcalmon">Robert</persName>, which
            is quite as it should be. That does not leave me thoroughly up to date as to your plans
            and adventures. Where are you, my dear, and what are you doing, and when is <orgName key="holt">Holt</orgName>
            bringing out your <title key="hymen">book</title>? I have heard nothing more of that either. <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> tells me
            that she wrote you telling you that I had had to have a fourth operation and that she
            also sent the letter to 1 South Audley Street, but, as we have had no answer to that
            either, I imagine you have not received any of these things.</p>
         <p>My news is of the meagrest description. The surgeons informed me in April that I
            had to have another operation at once. It was set for the <date when="1921-05-17">17th of May</date>, as my friend Mrs. <persName key="florence_ayscough">Ayscough</persName>, with whom I am collaborating in my Chinese poems you will remember, arrived
            from <placeName key="shanghai">Shanghai</placeName> with a batch of poems</pb> to be fixed, and <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName>
            decided to print the <title key="firFlowerTablets">book</title> in the Autumn, so that meant a great rush to get everything
            done before my operation. However, we finished it, and I then had the operation from
            which I am now slowly and rather discouragingly recovering. Since then I have done
            nothing but try and get well, and, as I have seen nobody, I have absolutely no news, but
            that makes me all the more avid to hear some of yours, so do write as soon as you can
            and tell me how you and <persName key="perdita_aldington">Perdita</persName> are and what you are doing and everything. I will not
            write any more now, partly because I am tired and partly because there is really nothing
            to say.</p>
         <closer>Much love, my dear, from us both.</lb>
            Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
