<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1922-03-20">20 March 1922</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$130i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Manager, Lloyd’s Bank 67
                     Kingsway <placeName key="london">London</placeName> W.C.2 <placeName
                        key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned. Includes a postscript with
                     royalties for Some Imagist Poets.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1922-03-20">March 20, 1922.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Thank you very much for your letter about "<title key="firFlowerTablets">Fir-Flower Tablets</title>." It was splendid to get. The book seems to be making friends. Even
            <persName key="arthur_waley">Arthur Waley</persName>, who is not, I think, inclined to be very agreeable to other translators
            calls it "an admirable book."</p>
         <p>I wonder how your "<title key="hymen">Hymen</title>" is doing. I reviewed it for the "<title key="nyEveningPost">Post</title>." I wonder if you saw
            the review. If you did not, I shall be very glad to send you a copy. I saw a
            ridiculously ignorant one of it in the "<title key="londonSpectator">London Spectator</title>" and a superb one by <persName key="may_sinclair">May Sinclair</persName> in the "<title key="dial">Dial</title>."</p>
         <p>I am delighted that you are included in the "<title key="miscellany">Miscellany</title>" this year. You should have been
            in the first one. I have not seen your contributions, but <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> tells me they
            are very fine. From those contributions to the book which I have seen (I have not seen
            those of all the poets), I should say that it is going to be a better volume than the
            last one.</p>
         <p>Meanwhile I peg away at my <title key="johnKeats">book on <persName key="john_keats">Keats</persName></title> and, although I find it interesting, I cuss and
            swear at ever having undertaken such an enormous task. On the whole, I think Keats was
            more interesting as a man with potentialities than as a finished poet, although certain
            of his things still delight me – rather lines and expressions than whole poems, however.
            He ought to have lived in our age; I think he agreed with it a great deal in his point
            of view. Of course, when I say that in print, everybody will come out with a howl and
            say I am writing propaganda again; but that will not be true, so I need not care. I have
            found enough new material to make the book worth doing, I think.</p>
         <p>I am just starting off on another lecture trip which will carry me to <placeName key="charleston">Charleston</placeName>. It
            should be lovely there. I was there once sixteen years ago. There is a beautiful old
            place there laid out by <persName key="michaud">Michaud</persName>, a famous landscape</pb> gardener, in the
            eighteenth century. The place is abandoned, has been, I think, since the Civil War, but
            the grounds remain all laid out with azaleas and paths running between them, and the
            azaleas are as high as small trees, and their blossoms drop on paths, and you walk
            softly upon the colours of the rainbow. How you would delight in it!</p>
         <p>I am very much worried about <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName>’s poems which she sent me. They cannot be used,
            Hilda, it is impossible. They have that curious malodorous touch which permeates the
            freak poetry that the "<title key="littleReview">Little Review</title>" likes. She did better when she followed you and
            me. <persName key="robert_mcalmon">Robert McAlmon</persName> is not a good model for her. I have not dared write to her for some
            time because I hate to tell her that nothing can be done with the book, but it cannot
            be. If it is published it will simply hurt her, and it will not be published by any
            reputable firm. What a child of phases she is, and how important, therefore, that the
            influences surrounding her should be the right ones! I do not suppose that either you or
            I can do anything about it. Husbands take precedence over friends even when the friends
            are past literary flames. I woke her up, you pointed her to beautiful perfection, and
            Robert McAlmon is engaged in toppling her over. I wonder what the next phase will be.
            She seems greatly enamoured of sexual problems at present, which is, I suppose, partly
            the trend of our most youthful youth of to-day, and partly the effect of marriage. Poor
            little girl; where will it end.</p>
         <p>Well, I must stop this letter as I have a hundred things to do and I am leaving on
            Monday. Write again soon. <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> joins me in much love, and please remember us
            both to your mother.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer></pb>
         <postscript>P.S. Oh, the draft! It gets smaller and smaller and some day will stop altogether, since we are not reprinting, but
            so long as there is half a two cent stamp to send, you shall have it. The account is as
            follows.</lb>
            By Sales:</lb>
            11 <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title> .67-1/2 $7.42</lb>
            7 " 1916 .67-1/2 4.73</lb>
            8 " 1917 .67-1/2  4.05</lb>
            1/6 of 16.20 is <measure type="currency" num="$2.70">$2.70</measure> or 12s 5d</postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
