<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1917-10-16">16 October 1917</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$61i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of the first page. 44 <placeName key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburg Square</placeName> <placeName key="london"
                        >London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england">England</placeName> is
                     the typed address given for H. D. in the top left corner of the first page.
                     Unsigned. Includes a postscript.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1917-10-16">October 16, 1917.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:-</salute></opener>
         <p>Thank you ever so much for your nice letter from <placeName key="">Litchfield</placeName> (I saw that by the
            postmark). I am awfully glad that you and <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> liked that review in "<title key="poetryJournal">The Poetry Journal</title>." I hope you will like the part about you in my new book, "<title key="tendencies">Tendencies in Modern American Poetry</title>," as well. The review was merely a condensation of the essay.</p>
         <p>By the way, out of a blue sky comes a letter from <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra Pound</persName>. I enclose it and my
            answer. They need no comment. I think your method of being on perfectly good terms with
            them all is a good one, and it is the one I should certainly pursue in regard to Ezra
            Pound were I in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>. I do not bear him a bit of a grudge for what he did, but I do
            not want to be mixed up with him publicly, as I think he has queered himself all over
            the shop. It is for that reason I will not contribute to "<title key="littleReview">The Little Review</title>." I am
            afraid <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> is a little sore about it, but I really cannot do it while Ezra
            is so much in evidence there.</p>
         <p><persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> writes me very blue letters. Poor boy! He does not know how to get on with the
            world. I think it owes him a better position than he has yet attained. I do hope that my
            remarks about him in the new book may do him some good.</p>
         <p>I was sorry to say that "<title key="sevenArts">The Seven Arts</title>" has been obliged to cease publication. That is
            a real calamity for all of us, as it was rapidly becoming the best paper for the younger
            writers in this country. <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName> is keeping on, of course, but we know what she is. They
            ("The Seven Arts") have a promise of a subside after the war is over, so we may hope
            that they will resume in time.</pb> Meanwhile, we have no organ-none of us younger writers,
            but just have to put things round wherever we can.</p>
         <p><persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> writes me that none of the publishers will take his new book and he seems
            awfully down on his luck. He wants me to get some essays of his into "<title key="newRepublic">The New Republic</title>,"
            or "<title key="yaleReview">The Yale Review</title>." But as a matter of fact, the editors of those papers are both
            conservatives, and do not love me very dearly, and I think he would do better to send
            the articles direct, rather than to trust to any intervention of mine. Do they need any
            more money, do you think? I wish you would let me know from time to time if you think
            they do.</p>
         <p>It is good news to know that Richard is again in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. "<title key="dial">The Dial</title>" says he is in a
            training camp for officers. I hope that means he is going to be an officer himself.</p>
         <p>I wish you would tell him that I think his "Fatigues" one of the most beautiful poems I
            have read for a long time. I have asked "The Seven Arts" to return to him the poem of
            his which they had not yet published.</p>
         <p>I am afraid the times are going to be rather difficult for us not until the war is over,
            but we must all keep on, and you above all must not let yourself get discouraged,
            because we need you.</p>
         <p>Give my love to Richard, and keep a great deal for yourself. In both of these measures
            <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> would join, but she is away for a few weeks with her family in <placeName key="saltLakeCity">Salt Lake City</placeName>.</p>
         <closer>Lovingly,</closer>
         <postscript>P.S. I am to deliver a lecture on the English <orgName key="imagists">Imagists</orgName> in February, so will you
            please give me all the dates you can about Richard’s life; about the</pb> things that have
            influenced him, and all the little thousand and one things which go to make a good
            personal memoir. You will see the kind of thing I want from the essays in the new book,
            but do not be as sketchy as you were about yourself. If it had not been for <persName key="helen_doolittle">your mother</persName>,
            I should have been up a tree about you. As it was I did not have half
            enough.</postscript>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
