<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1919-09-24">24 September 1919</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$104i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page: Mrs. Richard Aldington c/o Miss Winifred Ellerman, 1
                     South Audley Street, <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.1,
                        <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1919-09-24">September 24, 1919.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I enclose you cheque for our half yearly royalties from <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName>. They are
            getting very slim, for, as you know, we are letting the editions run out, so that there
            will be less and less from this source until finally there is none at all. The
            bookkeeping is as follows:</lb>
            By sales</lb>
            24 <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title>, 1915 .43 ½ $10.44</lb>
            20 " " 1916 .43 ½ 8.70</lb>
            24 " " 1917 .43 ½ 10.44</lb>
                              $29.58 </lb>
            One-sixth of $29.58 is <measure type="currency" num="$4.93">$4.93</measure></p>
         <p>Now as to your poems, I have already placed "The Islands" in the "<title key="northAmericanReview">North American Review</title>." The shorter one I Have not been able to place yet, but I hope to before long. I
            shall be in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> the last week in October and the first week in November lecturing
            at <placeName key="columbiaU">Columbia University</placeName>, and while I am there I can run round and see editors, and I hope
            to be able to get some one to take this poem of yours.</p>
         <p>Now I want to ask you an interesting question: Was <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred Ellerman</persName> hurt by my letter
            to her about her book "<title key="development">Development</title>"? She seems a very queer, uncertain child and one
            upon whose toes one is always treading unconsciously. She sent me the book and asked my
            opinion on it, and I wrote her exactly what my opinion was, some of it favourable, some
            of it more moderate in tone. I do not really think the book was ready for publication,
            but I told her as she was publishing it not to worry about that. As I think she will
            probably have shown you my letter, I will not go at all into the details of what I said,
            but certainly I did not couch it in a way to hurt any one’s feelings, and equally
            certainly, when one is asked for a criticism, one should not be huffed when it is
            given.</p></pb>
         <p>I do not understand the girl nor her attitude toward her art. If she is the serious
            artist I suppose, she would be willing to accept criticism even if she did not want to
            follow it. There is no necessity whatever for any one to follow criticism, but one
            should not be annoyed at receiving it. Does she think she is the genius of the world who
            can arrive at success spontaneously, as it were? I hope I have not hurt her feelings for
            I like the girl from her letters, and value her youthful and exuberant attitude toward
            poetry, but she seems inclined to squabble with people rather.</p>
         <p>What I am really afraid of is that she will think that <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName>’s remarks about
            her book came from me. As a matter of fact, I gave Ferris Greenslet no opinion whatever
            about the book before he read it, and I had no idea what he had written to her until
            after he wrote it. It was rather funny, therefore, that our opinions should more or less
            coincide. If Winifred chooses to be offended I suppose it cannot be helped, but I am
            very sorry if such is the case. However, possibly you can straighten things out. I am
            afraid she will find the pathway to success very hard if she is going to take the
            remarks made about her work in this way.</p>
         <p>Do write me from time to time and tell me how you are. Since I do not know if you are
            still in <placeName key="cornwall">Cornwall</placeName> I am sending <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s cheque to his <placeName key="london">London</placeName> address, and yours to you
            at the address you have given me. I wonder how it will be when I go to <placeName key="england">England</placeName> and when
            I can come. <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> joins me in much love. You will shortly receive my new book
            which I hope will be out next week.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
