<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1916-08-22">22 August 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$23i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Five pages typewritten in black ink. Archival notes read "Aldington" in pencil
                     at the top of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-08-22">August 22, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I was delighted to get your letter. In fact, I am sorry to say that I am in debt to you
            for two since I wrote. I was even more delighted to get yours and <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>’s photographs.
            They will be the greatest pleasure and comfort to me, and I shall have them where I can
            see them constantly.</p>
         <p>I had already made up my mind to write to Richard all the time, whether I received
            letters from him or not. I can imagine what it must be like to get news from the outside
            world, and you need not fear that I shall not keep you informed as to the situation
            here, to the best of my ability.</p>
         <p>I wish I could go over and see you. It has been on my mind to take a steamer and go over
            for a few weeks, just to show my interest and friendship for you and Richard, before he
            goes to the front. After considering this, I have decided not to go, for reasons which I
            hope you will consider conclusive. In the first place, I do not think the sea is very
            safe at the moment; and although I have a right to risk my own life, I do not think I
            have a right to risk anyone else’s, and <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> absolutely refuses to let me go
            over without going with me. In the second place, now that <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> has gone away, I
            think it extremely important to stay here and keep all our names before the public. This
            I am wearing myself to skin and bones to do. And I know that is what Richard would care
            to have me do, more than to see him personally. As soon as the war is over, I shall go
            across at once. But just now, you must regard me as staying here to help along the
            cause.</p>
         <p>I have sold two of Richard’s poems to the "<title key="poetryReview">Poetry Review</title>" – "Images" and "Inarticulate
            Grief." The rest of the poems I have sent to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName></pb> for consideration. She is not as
            enthusiastic about them as she ought to be, but she has asked to keep them awhile longer
            before answering.</p>
         <p>I have also sold Richard’s essay on Mallarmé to the "Poetry Review." The poems appear in
            the August issue, as you will see. How soon they will print the essay, I do not know.
            They are supposed to pay on acceptance, but they do not – they pay on publication, and
            not very promptly then; so I am afraid I shall not have any money to send Richard for
            about a month.</p>
         <p>I have also sold his article on "<persName key="henri_deRegnier">Henri de Régnier</persName>" to "<title key="dial">The Dial</title>." They have agreed to
            pay <measure type="currency" num="$5.00">$5.00</measure> for it. This is not high, and I fear <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> will not pay more, if as
            much; but it is quite impossible to get these slight, exquisite things into the regular,
            stodgy, high-pay magazines. "The Dial" has a very large circulation, and I thought it
            better to accept it.</p>
         <p>I am trying to get the editor of "<title key="drama">The Drama</title>" to pay Richard what he owes him, but
            without a power-of-attorney it is a little difficult; however, I do not yet despair.</p>
         <p>His article on "<persName key="pierre_louys">Pierre Louys</persName>" I do not think I can sell. Louys’ writing is not the kind
            of thing that takes the American public, and Braithwaite, the editor of "The Dial," and
            Harriet have all refused it; and I do not think there is any use in expecting it to be
            printed in any of the paying magazines. Of course, <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> will take it for
            the "<title key="littleReview">Little Review</title>," if you would like me to send it to her, only of course she does not
            pay.</p>
         <p>"The Dial" printed an attack upon us by a man named <persName key="he_warner">H. E. Warner</persName> in their Correspondence
            Column, in which he foolishly and idiotically</pb> criticized the part of your poem about the
            heat blunting the pears. I make a rule of never answering attacks, but I have answered
            this letter only, however, to repudiate a misquotation he gives from me. I think it
            always wiser for us not to answer attacks personally, and it seems quite impossible to
            explain to such an unimaginative man why your poem is beautiful. Also, being one of the
            group, things of that sort do not have the same effect from us that they do from other
            people. But I have asked a very good friend of mine, a man of a great deal of
            scholarship and of interest in our work, who has already written a long and interesting
            article on the <orgName key="imagists">Imagists</orgName> which he is trying to have published, to answer it; and I hope
            he will do so.</p>
         <p>"The Dial" has changed hands, having been bought by a man named <persName key="martyn_johnson">Martyn Johnson</persName> who,
            although not quite so radical as we could wish, is nevertheless thoroughly in sympathy
            with our work. He has asked me to write critical essays for him and, as you see, he has
            accepted Richard’s article on Régnier. "The Dial" has hitherto been the most reactionary
            paper we have. His object is to change it gradually until it becomes sympathetic to the
            new movements. He must do this slowly, and I think he has begun very well by making Dr.
            <persName key="cj_masseck">C. J. Masseck</persName> the editor. I do not know Dr. Masseck, but everyone tells me that he is in
            favour of all that we are trying to do. The ball is rolling steadily and constantly, and
            I do not think we need have any fear for the future.</p>
         <p>As I wrote Richard sometime ago, I am to give a series of four lectures on modern
            American poets this Winter in various cities. The poets I am dealing with are <persName key="ea_robinson">Edwin Arlington Robinson</persName>, <persName key="robert_frost">Robert Frost</persName>, <persName key="el_masters">Masters</persName>,</pb> <persName key="carl_sandburg">Carl Sandburg</persName>, and the Imagists. Of course,
            as they are American poets, I cannot say as much as I wish I could about Richard and
            <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName> and <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, but I shall run them in in the Imagist lecture, although it will be
            chiefly about you and Fletcher.</p>
         <p>Can you send me a little biographical detail about yourself and about Richard? I should
            like to have Richard’s for future use, and I want yours for these lectures. I want to
            know where you were born, and when; where you were educated, and more or less what your
            life was like; where you travelled; what you thought; what you read; what interested
            you. I am going to publish these lectures afterwards in a book, and the arrangement will
            be about like that of my "<title key="sixFrenchPoets">French Poets</title>" – some biography, a great deal of criticism, and
            a lot of quotation. In spite of all these poets being alive, I think I can take a leaf
            out of the French practice, and write about them now. I am giving these lectures in
            <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>, at the <placeName key="brooklynInstitute">Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences</placeName><add place="above"> in <placeName key="brooklyn">Brooklyn</placeName></add>, at the <placeName key="littleTheatre">Little Theatre</placeName> in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, and possibly in <placeName key="stLouis">St. Louis</placeName> and <placeName key="philadelphia">Philadelphia</placeName>; and <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> has
            already agreed to publish them a year from now. All of which is very satisfactory.</p>
         <p>Please tell Richard that his going to the war will only be an interlude, and an
            interlude which I have no doubt will be an interesting experience, that he will not in
            any way get out of the running here, and that I shall keep his name alive, and do my
            best to place his things, until he comes back.</p>
         <p>Keep your courage up, Dear Girl, and I really do believe this war will soon be over. I
            think <placeName key="germany">Germany</placeName> is on her last legs. Richard writes that your courage and self-sacrifice
            have helped him inconceivably, and that is</pb> a glorious thing for you to feel. We believe
            that poetry is virile, not decadent and weak, and things such as you are going through
            can only deepen and broaden your poetry, and that is what I know you both live for.</p>
         <p>Mrs. Russell send her love, and you know you have mine. I am not writing to Richard by
            this mail; this is to him as well as to you.</p>
         <p>Please find out if Lawrence is in want because, if so, I should like to send you some
            money to send him, or send it to him direct, as you may think best. He is proud, and one
            has to go carefully.</p>
         <closer>With a great deal of love,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
