<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1918-03-12">12 March 1918</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$70i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington 44 <placeName
                        key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>
                     <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1918-03-12">March 12, 1918.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am sending two money orders, one for <measure type="currency" num="$25.48">$25.48</measure> for you and <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>, and one for
            <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>’s share which is <measure type="currency" num="12.74">$12.74</measure>, plus this little gift of <measure type="currency" num="$200.00">$200.00</measure>. Here is the account:</lb>
            SALES</lb> 26 <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Poets</title>, 1915 at .36-1/4 $ 9.43</lb> 43 Imagist Poets, 1916 at .36-1/4 15.59</lb>
            142 Imagist Poets, 1917 at .38-1/4 51.47</lb> $ 76.49 $76.49 divided by 6 - $12.74 – 2.14.0</lb> I
            am also writing a letter to Lawrence in care of you. </p>
         <p>Do you know Richard is the only one of my three English <orgName key="imagists">Imagists</orgName> who took the trouble to
            answer my requests for a biography. This makes the writing for <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> and Lawrence very
            difficult. The body of Flint’s work is so extremely slight that it will be hard to give
            him enough space when I have nothing to say about him personally. As to Lawrence, I
            suppose he has been much too worried and upset to think anything about it. But I think
            it is unfortunate.</p>
         <p>Do you know, Hilda, the more I read Richard’s work, the more deeply I admire it, and, by
            the same token, the more I read Flint’s and Lawrence’s the less I like them.</p>
         <p>Richard wrote me a charming letter the other day and said that he was sending me the
            manuscript of his poems and would I look after it. You may certainly rely on me to do my
            best. I am having a perfectly fearful time here with <persName key="brown">Brown</persName>. I do not think that Brown
            means to be dishonest, but he is very unbusinesslike, and he bites off more than he can
            chew. The result</pb> is that he is in a constant mess financially, and as Richard never gave
            me that power of attorney, I have no real hold over him. Just now I have been trying my
            best to get a number of copies of Richard’s "<title key="images">Images</title>" to send with the poetry libraries I
            am sending to the thirty-four training camps in this country. He says he has sheets of
            "Images," but they are not yet bound, and he keeps promising them for next week, and
            they never come, and I do not think they ever will come. He has had the manuscript
            of <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>’s <title key="japanesePrints">Japanese Poems</title> for a year and a half, and has not published it yet. I am
            afraid if he takes this manuscript of Richard’s, he will just hold on to it and not
            publish it. He has moved into new and rather splendid quarters, and I imagine has done
            so by borrowing the money and therefore has no ready cash. I have asked him to send me
            an accounting of the sales of Richard’s books so that I may see if the fifteen dollars
            already paid covers the royalties due. I do not suppose it shall even be able to get the
            accounting out of him for a long time, however.</p>
         <p>I do, therefore, sincerely advise not having him print Richard’s new book. The only
            trouble with that is the more businesslike publishers have got dreadfully cold feet
            about publishing poetry just now. They do not want to spend any money on it, and they
            are all cutting down. Still, <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> has asked to see the manuscript, but I
            have no real hope there, nor have I with <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>, although I shall sound Mr. <persName key="gp_brett">Brett</persName> on
            the subject when I go to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> next week. There is a possibility that Mr. <persName key="alfred_harcourt">Harcourt</persName> of
            <orgName key="holt">Holt</orgName>’s might be induced to take it. At any rate, I shall try all these people before
            ceding the manuscript to Brown, but if Richard should have changed his mind and sent the
            manuscript direct to Brown (for I have not yet received it) the matter ill be more
            difficult. In a way</pb> I do not blame Brown, for I know he is struggling very hard against
            dreadful odds. I do blame him for his eternal lying, however. He seems to think that it
            would be bad policy to say that he is stuck for the moment, whereas I think every one
            would respect him more, and the good will of his business would be saved if he told the
            truth.</p>
         <p>I will let you know after I have been to New York what the outlook is, and I do hope
            that Richard’s manuscript will come in time for me to take it with me.</p>
         <p>I am sorry to say that your "<title key="seaGarden">Sea Garden</title>" is out of print over here, and <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton-Mifflin</orgName>
            tell me that it is so difficult to import anything that they are not going to import any
            more sheets. If you can send me thirty-three copies, I can send them after the libraries
            which have already gone out to be included in them. I cannot bear to have your work not
            represented, but I took the very last copy that Houghton-Mifflin had.</p>
         <p>I am up to my eyes in work, not only on my <placeName key="brooklyn">Brooklyn</placeName> lectures, but on some poems of my
            own. I have been doing a long series called "Phantasms of War" for "<title key="independent">The Independent</title>,"
            and I also have some polyphonic, semi-historical things that Macmillan is very anxious
            to print in a book next Autumn, if I can get enough done. I have them all mapped out,
            but they take a long time to write, and I am rather discouraged at the way time fleets
            away. I think I shall gather my miscellaneous essays and lectures into a volume of prose
            a year from now, in which case my present appreciation of Richard will have a permanent
            form.</p>
         <closer>Lots of love,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
