<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1922-09-12">12 September 1922</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$133i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1922-09-12">September 12, 1922.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Here is our bi-yearly pittance from the <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthologies</title>. They have still a few
            copies left of each year’s issue, and I suppose we shall continue to get five-cent
            pieces until they are all exhausted.</lb>
            By sales:</lb>
            13 Imagist Poets .67-1/2 8.78</lb>
            4 " " 1916 .67-1/2 2.70</lb>
            8 " " 1917 .67-1/2 5.40</lb>
            1/6 of 16.88 is <measure type="currency" num="$2.82">$2.82</measure></p>
         <p>I heard somewhere or other that your book of essays was refused by <orgName key="holt">Holt</orgName>. Is this true? I
            think that I can place it for you with <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> if you care to send it to me. I
            was so immensely struck with those essays which I saw last year, and I think there
            should be no difficulty in placing them. I spoke to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> about them last
            year, but naturally you preferred to send them where "<title key="hymen">Hymen</title>" was published. However, if
            Holt does not want them, do send them to me, for I am quite sure I can land them with
            Houghton Mifflin.</p>
         <p>I had a letter from <persName key="winifred_bryher">Winifred</persName> the other day. She seems to have rushed all over <placeName key="europe">Europe</placeName> and
            <placeName key="asia">Asia</placeName> with a suit-case. I was afraid she was very much offended with me because I told
            her she would have to change certain things in her book of poems if she wanted them
            published over here. Since then she has sent me a portion of the manuscript in this
            little pamphlet "<title key="arrowMusic">Arrow Music</title>," and she has done practically what I suggested she do, and
            I think this little book is very charming.</p>
         <p>Are you still in <placeName key="switzerland">Switzerland</placeName>, and what are your plans? I have been reading your
            selections in the "<title key="miscellany">Miscellany</title>" with great interest. I particularly</pb> like
            "Holy Satyr." How you think of the words you use, I do not know; it is a perfect marvel
            to me, and a perfect delight. "Heliodora" is a very strange thing, but a very
            interesting one, but rather unlike you, I think. "Toward the Piraeus" is the best thing
            you have done in rhyme. I like your method of rhyming or not as you happen to feel like,
            rhyming in some sentences and not in others. The series, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, with which your
            selection ends, is, I believe, the best of this collection, and No. 3 in hers is so
            charmingly rhymed. Your work with rhyme, which appears all through these selections, is
            very interesting to me. You certainly can write, Hilda, and nobody knows it better than
            I.</p>
         <p>I do not think the "Miscellany" on the whole is bad. <persName key="conrad_aiken">Conrad Aiken</persName> is too long-winded,
            one cannot even read him, and I am not a great admirer of <persName key="sara_teasdale">Sara Teasdale</persName>, and I think
            <persName key="alfred_kreymborg">Alfred Kreymborg</persName> falls down in his selections far below his best self, and <persName key="james_oppenheim">Oppenheim</persName> is
            negligible, but on the whole I think the book looks pretty well. The truth of the matter
            is that we American poets of to-day are so diverse in the way we write that I do not
            think we fit together in a book very well. For that reason I think we are less
            homogenous than the <title key="georgianPoetry">Georgian Anthology</title>, but personally I think so much better that even
            if the reader gets a jar going from one selection to another, he nevertheless gets a
            feeling of variety and profusion which is very effective.</p>
         <p>Do write me and tell me what you are doing and what your plans for the Winter are. I
            suppose there is no hope of your coming over here; I wish there were. And, as I said
            before, do send me your essays and see if I cannot land them with Houghton Mifflin. With
            a great deal of love in which <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> joins,</p>
         <closer>Always affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
