<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda Doolittle (Aldington)</persName>, <date
                  when="1917-12-07">07 December 1917</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sl">Samantha Lepak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425539886$58i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Two pages typewritten in black ink. Mrs. Richard Aldington 44 <placeName key="mechlenburghSquare">Mechlenburgh Square</placeName>
                        <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, W.C. <placeName key="england"
                        >England</placeName> is the typed address given for H. D. in the top left
                     corner of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1917-12-07">December 7, 1917.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>:-</salute></opener>
         <p>I was very glad indeed to get your letter of <date when="1917-11-14">November 14th</date>, and to know that you liked
            the essay on yourself in "<title key="tendencies">Tendencies</title>." I think none of the essays in the book has been
            so well taken as that one, and I hope that it will stimulate interest in your poetry. A
            good many people have told me that after reading my book they felt they wanted to go and
            read the authors themselves, and I only trust that this laudable desire will bear
            fruit.</p>
         <p><persName key="helen_doolittle">Your mother</persName> wrote me how much she liked it, and she said something else that gave me
            even greater pleasure which was that it seemed like you; it almost startled her she felt
            it was so true a description of your personality. To my mind, nothing could be higher
            praise than that, except that Richard, who knows you better than anybody, liked the
            account of your work. I do not suppose that no matter what I said about you as a person
            I could satisfy him, and quite rightly, but I like to think that it has been my
            privilege to be the first person to represent you to the world in toto your work and
            yourself.</p>
         <p>Your letter came two or three days ago, and Richard’s of the <date when="1917-11-18">18th</date> came just now. I am
            answering his letter on a separate sheet enclosed. It is really for both of you, of
            course, but he said so many things I wanted to answer that I thought I would do it this
            way. What you may say about the Lawrences is perfectly horrible. I feel very sorry for
            them, and I will send you some money for them in a little while. I think it better to
            send to you for various reasons, among others, that as they cannot forever live in your
            room, I shall not know their address until you send it to me. I want</pb> to think it over
            for a few days and see what I can send them, and then I will send you a draft, which you
            can turn over to them. I am still addressing you at <placeName key="mechlenburgSquare">Mechlenburg Square</placeName>, as I suppose it
            will be forwarded to you at <placeName key="litchfield">Litchfield</placeName>, and I do not know your address there, and
            Richard says that he will be through with the training school in a couple of weeks and
            then I suppose you will have to move.</p>
         <p>This is not much of a letter. I am just sending it off to acknowledge yours, but it
            takes a great deal of love from both <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and me.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
