<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1914-11-25">25
                  November 1914</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$1i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages typewritten in black ink. It is typed on Amy Lowell’s stationary,
                     with the engraved heading "Miss A. Lowell, Heath Street, Brookline, Mass." The
                     words "John Gould" are written in pencil across the top of the first page.
                     Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1914-11-25">November 25, 1914.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am very glad you have landed on these shores and I hope to see you before long. I am
            going on to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> next Monday to attend to some business and I want you to dine with
            me on Tuesday evening at the <placeName key="hotelStRegis">Hotel St. Regis</placeName>, <placeName key="fifthAvenue">Fifth Avenue</placeName>, and we can have a good
            old-fashioned talk about everything in general and the state of things in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName> in
            particular.</p>
         <p>Now I have a little blow for you and a little of what I hope is going to be good news.
            In the first place Mr. <persName key="thomas_mosher">Mosher</persName> has returned your <title key="irradiations">book</title> to me with a very kind note saying
            that he has given up the publication of any new poetry on his own hook and will only
            publish for authors at their own expense. They tell me he is getting very tired and is
            not well. He is also giving up the "<title key="bibelot">Bibelot</title>," a magazine which he has run for twenty
            years, so I think his remarks are bona fide. I will tell you all my tentative efforts
            with your book when I see you. I could not bear to write to you of a complete break-down
            of your hopes for its publication, but I think I have landed it with a publisher at last
            and with a most excellent publisher, namely Messrs. <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin &amp; Company</orgName>. Mr.
            <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Greenslet</persName> is extremely enthusiastic over it and it is in his hands now, and although I
            have not been told definitely that they have accepted it, still from what he says I
            think that is practically the case. As soon as he lets me know definitely I will drop
            you a line.</p>
         <p>I am having a hard time with the publication of our <title key="some_imagist_poets">anthology</title> over here. The publishers
            shy away from <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>’s "Heaven" like a plague and what I am going to succeed in doing I
            cannot imagine, however I guess it will all come out right in the end.</p>
         <p>Let me know your address in New York and let me be sure to see you on Tuesday night as I
            am going home on Wednesday. I sent you a copy of my <title key="swordBladesAndPoppySeed">book</title>. Did you ever get it, I wonder?
            If not I will bring one to New York with me because I want you to have it from me.</p>
         <closer>Very sincerely yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
