<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1915-10-11"
               >11 October 1915</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref=""> <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here --> </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as"> Anthony Shoplik </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm"> Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm"> Prakruti Maniar </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno type="URI"> https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$40i </idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>
                     This letter is 7 pages long (seq. 40-46). It is typed on something like notebook paper which has holepunches in it in 
                     different places. The words “John Gould” are written in pencil across the top of the first page. Much of the letter 
                     is difficult to read because the left 
                     margin is partially cut off.</p>  
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            &personography;
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1915-10-11">October 11, 1915</date></dateline>
            <salute>My dear<persName key="john_fletcher">Mr. Fletcher</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Your Friday letter reached me yesterday morning. Please forgive me for not having answered
            the last one I received, but the truth is I have been almost frantic getting <title key="sixFrenchPoets">these translations</title>
         off to the press.</p>
         <p>I am thankful to say <title key="sixFrenchPoets">they</title> went off on Saturday night, and I have nothing left now
         but proof, which I hope will soon be over. I am a month late with <title key="sixFrenchPoets">the book</title>, owing
         to the state of my health this summer, which prevented me from working as many hours a day as usual, but I still hope
         it will be out in time for the Christmas trade.</p>
         <p>
            As soon as I got your letter about the <title>Monroe-Anderson "Anthology"</title>, and incidentally 
            <persName key="ac_henderson">Alice Henderson</persName>'s journey to <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>
            and <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>, I pondered what to do. Luckily, in the same mail came a letter
            from <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, also telling me of <persName key="ac_henderson">Alice Henderson
            </persName>'s journey, which enabled me to send a wire at once, asking them to be sure and let me know when she was in 
            <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>, but not a whisper did <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>have of
            the <title>"Anthology"</title>, so very possibly you are right, and <persName>they</persName> are not going to ask me to contribute.
            Now as to your contributing, my dear <persName key="john_fletcher">Boy</persName>, it is very sweet of you to wish to hold
            back on account of their not asking me, and I appreciate this proof of your friendship very much, but I do not want you ever
            to feel that way. You and I will always help each other all we can, I trust, but I think we must be perfectly free agents,
            and at liberty to use our things to the best advantage.</p>
         <p>
            I have just appeared in a <title>little Anthology</title>published by <orgName>the Bonis</orgName>, called
            <title>"Fifty Best Poems of America"</title>, along with my revered cousin, <persName>James Russell</persName>,
            <persName>Longfellow</persName>, <persName>Bryant</persName>, <persName>Poe</persName>, <persName>Edwin Markham</persName>,
            <persName>Bliss Carman</persName>, <persName>Moody</persName>, and of all the astounding things - <persName>
               Arturo Giovanitti</persName>. I think with the exception of <persName>Poe's</persName><title>"Helen"</title>
            and <persName>Giovanitti's</persName><title>"Walker"</title> we may consider that <title>the book</title> easily
            contains fifty of the worst poems ever written in this country. I am represented by <title>"A Winter Ride"</title>,
            a little gem which I should like to see burn in the fire. So please do not hesitate to go into the <title><persName key="ac_henderson">Alice Henderson</persName>Anthology</title>
            , if you want to, even if <persName key="ac_henderson">she</persName>pointedly leaves me out. She doesn't like me,
            and I think would find a slap agreeable to administer.</p>
         <p>What you mean by <title>"The Trimmed Lamp Prize"</title> I do not know, but I never go in for any prizes, so I shall 
            certainly not compete for it, whatever it may be. </p>
         <p>I am glad you are staying with <persName>the Aldises</persName>. They are quite interesting people. I only
         know them very slightly but they are most pleasant to meet and talk to and have always been most extremely nice
         to me.</p>
         <p>As far as <persName>Richard</persName>and <persName>his young hopefuls</persName>are concerned, personally I 
         feel no desire whatever to include anybody else in our <title>Anthology</title>. I quite agree with you that there is
         nobody whose work wouldadd to the quality of <title>the book</title>as a whole. <persName>Elliot</persName>'s <title>
         "Windy Night"</title>I have not seen. I think his three in the <title>October "Poetry"</title> amusing, but not 
         very great. That sort of satire is not very difficult to do, if you only do it moderately so-so which is, I think,
         all he attained in these poems, and he is clearly with the <persName>Exra group</persName>, from his inclusion in
         <title>"Blast"</title> it would be the height of folly for us to make advances to him. I am writing <persName>Richard</persName>
         to the effect that I do not at all agree with his suggestion of one poem each from a lot of small fry, and that I think for the
         next two years we had better just remain ourselves, unless some very remarkable person shows up on the horizon, and I do not
         believe any very remarkable person is going to come for another long time, seven or eight years, or possibly longer. I think
         <persName>Harriet</persName> has pretty well combed England and America for promising poets, and I think everyone with a 
         degree of talent in them has been picked up, and until the next set grow up and get old enough to write I do not believe we
         shall see any new and considerable names. It will merely be the perfecting and maturing of the people now writing for some
         little time to come. <persName>Clara Shanafelt</persName> has written one or two nice things, but <persName>Richar</persName>
         himself says she has not seven good ones. Now the poet who cannot scrape together seven good poems, certainly is no great
         shakes, and in spite of the rather nice things I have seen I do not think she would in any way add to <title>our book</title>
         , and as to <persName>Marianne Moore</persName>, I really see nothing in her whatever. I quite agree with you that
         <persName>Stevens's</persName><title>"Peter Quince"</title> was excellent, but can see that it is quite on the cards
         that his other things may not be. At any rate, he does not belong to our group, and there is no necessity that I can see
         for hunting for people to include. I do not at all know what sort of contributions the others will send. I should think
         that neither <persName>Laurence</persName> nor <persName>Flint</persName> would have very brilliant ones, but there is 
         no use worrying about that until we see them. I think that your ideas of having "Ghosts in an Old House" as one of your
         contributions is excellent, but we won't decide any of those things definitely until we need. As far as I am concerned, I think two
         moderately long poems will be my best contribution. There have been <title>two Anthologies</title>now with little things 
         of mine in them, and I think it would be better to vary it. I think myself "A Spring Day" and a new poem "Off the Turnpike"
         would be best, but again, as I say, we will decide that when we meet.</p>
        <p>I rather think that I shall not get this book off my hands for another two or three weeks, which will bring me
        to the <date when="1915-11-01">first of November</date>. Then I think I shall go on to <placeName key='nyc'>New York</placeName>
        and see <orgName>the publishers</orgName>, and be gone a week or so, but I imagine I shall be back here, settled, by the second
        week in November anyway, so if you arrange to be here somewhere about then we can get right to work on the<title>Anthology</title>
        . Of course I cannot say for certain, as I want to take a month's vacation if I can, but I do not expect to travel my whole month.
        It is just barely possible I might go to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>for a few days, but I do not think there 
        is much chance of that until later in the winter. Anyway, there are my plans as far as I can know them now. The sooner you
        get here the better I shall like it, but I wish you could plan to be here about the middle of November anyway, as that seems 
        to me about the latest that we leave it about the <title>Anthology</title>. If I am held up again with <title>the book</title>
        , or things go slowly or anything, I will let you know.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>