<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1915-01-25">25
                  November 1915</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$10i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is four pages long (seq. 10-13). It is typed on something like
                     notebook paper with hole punches in it on all four pages. The words "John Gould
                     Fletcher" are written in pencil across the top of the first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1915-01-25">January 25, 1915.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">Boy</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I have got a lot of letters to write; but as you most thoughtfully and kindly say, I am
            so busy that it is almost impossible to write.</p>
         <p>Your poem "Chicago" was forwarded to me in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>, and I meant to sit right down and
            tell you how much I liked it, and how exceedingly swirling and windy I think it is.
            Where in the Devil you got such a nice expression as "smoky-blue pipes" from I wish I
            knew, and I would go and pick some like it. I have not time to go through it in detail
            and tell you all I think of it; I will reserve that until we meet.</p>
         <p>I am rehearsing our operettas for eight hours a day; and before the rehearsals begin and
            after they end, I am too done to sit down and write. I am dictating this letter now
            while I am dressing, because I cannot let any longer time elapse before sending you a
            word, and also because I have been having a terrible time about the title of the
            <title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title>.</p>
         <p>I won’t tell you all my tribulations; it would take too long. Suffice it to say that
            <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> was very much averse to changing the name, feeling that Imagiste had
            come to mean a certain kind of poetry, and had therefore a certain mercantile value. He
            accepted us under that title and advertised us so and, although he was very nice about
            it, he was a good deal upset by the proposal of a change. I, too, felt that a change was
            the greatest mistake in the world. Even if <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> had invented the name, it is we who have
            given the name value; for all the good work that Ezra has done since he announced
            himself an Imagiste could be crowded in a couple of pages, if it took as much room as
            that. I did not like</pb> to be downed either; and if Ezra published me without my permission
            in the first Anthology as an Imagiste, I have a great objection to backing down at his
            bidding when he decides that he does not want me to be one.</p>
         <p>I sent a cable to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName>, which it hurt me very much to do, explaining this as well as
            I could. And to-day comes a letter from him, enclosing one from <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>. Flint’s letter
            says that he remembers that Ezra did not invent the name "Imagiste," that it started in
            their talks at a little club where they used to meet, called "<orgName key="poetsClub">The Poets’ Club</orgName>," of which
            <persName key="te_hulme">Hulme</persName> was the founder, when they were always talking about the image. He adds: "Of
            course, at the back of my head I have known this all the time, but I never took the
            thing seriously. However, if Ezra is going to make it a part of his strategie litteraire
            to our hurt, then I think that it and he should be put in their place." He also suggests
            putting this in a preface. But I know that a fighting preface is a mistake. The fighting
            should come afterwards, in the "<egoist>Egoist</egoist>" and elsewhere, if we need to fight.</p>
         <p>Richard writes as follows: "I enclose a note from Flint to me which came five minutes
            after your wires. That letter and our great desire to play square all round influenced
            us to say that, if you and <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton, Mifflin</orgName> consider the Imagiste title absolutely
            necessary, why we will acquiesce. You know how much we want the Anthology. And though we
            really do not want the Imagiste title, we won't stand in the way of its coming out. So
            go ahead in the name of God and St. George." Under these circumstances, Mr. Greenslet
            and I have decided that really it is much easier to keep the name "Imagiste."</p>
         <p>At first we thought of calling it "Quintessentialist;" but that is too long, and I am
            sure the public is tired of "ists" and we had better hold to what we have got. If Ezra
            turns stuffy, we will burst into print and tell something closely approaching the whole
            story. As it is, I really think that to allow Ezra to take us up to ornament his career
            with when he chooses and drop</pb> us when he thinks we sparkle a little too brightly is a
            very foolish position for us to be in. Also our work is so much superior to his, and so
            much better than any work which he can get his new satellites to do, that I think
            whether or not they call themselves <orgName key="imagists">Imagistes</orgName> will matter not at all. The public will
            soon be able to tell the false from the true. Therefore, I am taking the liberty of
            going ahead on this plan with Flint's and Richard's and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName>'s consent, in spite of
            what you wrote to me, as I feel sure that, if you were here and I could explain
            everything to you in detail by word of mouth, you would agree with me that it was the
            best thing to do; in fact I am assuming so much on my friendship as to take your
            permission for granted.</p>
         <p>It has not been any easy business running this Anthology, and I feel quite sure that,
            had I known what it meant, I should never have proposed it. But I do not want to back
            down now. I only want you to help me fight Ezra if necessary, and help us make the name
            "Imagiste" which was forced upon us against our will into something so worth while that
            its connection with Ezra and his littlenesses will be forgotten.</p>
         <p>It is a horrible thing, working with so many people, so many miles apart. I want to
            please everybody; and I want to be fair to the publisher, who has been awfully square
            with us and most patient over all these suggested changes; and I hope that in the end
            what I do will please you too. At any rate, the book is Imagiste now, and Imagiste it
            must remain; and with Flint’s and Richard’s agreeing, I am sure you won’t be the one to
            stand out.</p>
         <p>We cannot get a poem of <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>’s in, as Richard does not like to ask him; and there is
            no time now to write, as the book has gone to press, I believe. Otherwise it will come
            out after the</pb> others of the series, which would be a great mistake. I do hope you are
            coming here soon; I want very much to see you. It is always more satisfactory to talk
            than to write, particularly when you are rehearsing eight hours a day. I wish you could
            be here for our operettas next week; but I fear it is too late for that now, and I don’t
            know whether you would enjoy them very much.</p>
         <p><persName key="herbert_croly">Croly</persName> of "<title key="newRepublic">The New Republic</title>" was very much interested in your Indian poem and took the
            whole thing to consider, saying that he would let me know if he could get it to pass the
            other editors; and whether he will take it all or in part, I do not know. I left it with
            him and have heard nothing more. I will you know as soon as I do. Forgive haste, but I
            wanted to put you <foreign xml:lang="fr">au courant</foreign> as soon as possible.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
