<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
               key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-12-20">20 December 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$78i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 4 pages long (seq. 78
                     -
                     81). It is typed on good quality typing paper (neither
                     notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). The words “John
                     Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-12-20">December 20, 1916</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
        
         <p>
            I have so many things to thank you for, that I hardly know where to begin. 
            <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> will have written you that I have been very ill, and 
            I am only just allowed to begin work again, a few hours a day. 
            And things have piled up so terribly, particularly my lectures, that I do not know where to begin. 
         </p>
         <p>
            But first of all let me thank you for your letter about “<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>”, 
            which was so unexpected and so beautiful that I burst into tears. 
            It did a lot to help me get well, I assure you. I kept it on my bed and 
            read it again and again. Such letters as that make up even for illness. 
            The book is doing very well, having gone through its first edition in a month, 
            and they now tell me that they think a third edition will be called for before long. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Our <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthology, 1916</title>, has just had, or is going to have, a second edition, so that we are all to the good over here. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I fear you may be disappointed at <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet’s</persName> having refused the manuscript you sent him. 
            I did my best to make him take it, but without success. They have lost so much money on 
            “<title key="newPoetrySeries">The New Poetry Series</title>” (owing to their own stupidity) that they are getting very 
            wary as to what they take – and we know already that Ferris Greenslet has no judgement. 
            I think you will stand more chance with your book of war poems, as Ferris 
            has a partiality for war poems. So I advise you to send it over as soon as you get it done. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I was sorry you felt the way you did about <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName>. 
            His article is not worthy of being taken seriously. 
            He told me himself that it was written in the “<title key="transcript">Transcript</title>” office a half hour before it had to go to press. 
            He has included your “<title>Lincoln</title>” in his <title key="magazineVerse">Anthology</title> – at least he had the last time 
            I saw the manuscript – and his not putting it among those five poems was entirely a matter of space. He told me that himself. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
           Braithwaite is going down hill rapidly. He has so many irons in the fire that 
           he pays less attention than ever to each one. “<title key="poetryReview">The Poetry Review</title>”, 
           as you have doubtless seen, is perfectly rotten, and he has now become 
           the editor of another paper, a quarterly, called “<title key="stratfordJournal">The Stratford Journal</title>”, 
           which bids fair to be worse than any of them. It does not deal particularly 
           with poetry, and the only number I have seen was really shockingly poor. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            Still, naturally, I do want that article on me to be printed, 
            and it was a bit tough on me to have you refuse to let Braithwaite have it, 
            because it is not he who would get the benefit, it would be I. 
            However, I have sent it to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>. But I have no real hope of her taking it. 
            She will not like me to receive so much praise, I fear. 
            Have you any objection to my giving it to <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName>, if Harriet refuses it? 
            I really do want it to appear in print. At least, Braithwaite would pay you something, 
            and Margaret Anderson won’t pay you anything. I will do just as you think best, 
            only let me know soon, so that I may get some benefit from it. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I am going to give you a great send-off in my lectures, 
            and Mr. <persName key="george_brett">Brett</persName> is delighted over the volume and seems to think he is going 
            to push it personally. So it ought to have some sale, and do you good. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            Now about your contributions to the Anthology. <persName key="hilda_doolittle"></persName>Hilda has given me permission to use the “Lincoln”, 
            and my selection for you would be: 
            
            <l><title>Lincoln</title></l>
            
            <l><title>Blackberry Harvest</title></l> 
            
            <l><title>Moonlight</title></l> 
            
            <l><title>Dawn</title></l> 
            
            and if you want one of the war poems – <title>“Armies”</title>. But your contribution will be about 
            ten pages as it stands, which is about our usual, so that, 
            unless you particularly want “Armies”, I do not advise putting it in. 
            In fact, <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard’s</persName> poems deal almost entirely with the war, and as 
            the ones that I could get that were any good of <persName key="fs_flint">Flint’s</persName> had war themes, 
            I rather advise you not to put this in, particularly if you are going to 
            publish a volume of war poems shortly. But personally I am quite willing, 
            you understand, to take it. I think it the best of the three war poems. 
         </p>
         <p>
            As we are including the “Lincoln”, and there are so 
            few war poems to be put in this selection, 
            I advise dropping the title, “War and Peace”, merely 
            letting the poems stand on their own titles. 
            Also, there is another thing that I would suggest, 
            and that is leaving out the opus numbers of your early books 
            in the bibliography. Also, I think I must put down who published them, 
            although I can put “out of print” in brackets after them, if you prefer. 
            But are they out of print? I should doubt it. Let me know what you want 
            me to do about this, so that I can get the bibliography as you want.  
         </p>
         <p>
            I will not write any more now, as it is important to get this off. 
            I wish you were here. Mrs. Russell and I constantly say how we wish 
            you were coming out to dinner. And you can’t think how much I miss the stimulus of our talks! 
         </p>
         <p>
            Answer by return mail, if possible. 
         </p>  
         <closer>Affectionately, </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
