<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
               key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-06-28">28
                  June 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$51i  </idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 5 pages long (seq. 51-55). It is typed on good quality typing paper (neither notebook paper 
                     nor Lowell’s nice cardstock). The words “John Gould” are written in pencil across the top of the first page. </p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-06-28">June 28, 1916.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Your two letters came day before yesterday, and I was thankful to get them. 
            You do not mention having been to <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName>'s, so I suppose you have forgotten that 
            you gave me that as an address before you knew where you would be. If you have not been there yet, there must 
            be a letter waiting for you. </p> 
         <p>You told me just what I wanted to know about the conditions in <placeName>England</placeName>. 
            That placard in <placeName>Trafalgar Square</placeName> must be supremely ridiculous. In fact, I have 
            been told by an English friend that somebody got up in the House of Parliament and said that it was 
            making them a laughing-stock before the nations. But their earnestness and sobriety in pursuing this 
            war is magnificent, and the fact that you feel it, is not at all surprising to me, for I am sure 
            it is there. </p>
         <p>Here things are moving much the same – creaking along rather than flowing, as usual at this season 
            of the year. <persName>Richard</persName> has written that he cannot undertake to do <title>the chronicle</title> 
            for <persName>Braithwaite</persName>, as he finds he will not be able to get any books or have any leisure 
            for reading, and that <persName>Hilda</persName>, having taken on “<title>The Egoist</title>,” will not have time for 
            it either. This is unfortunate, considering how hard I had to work to get 
            <persName>Braithwaite</persName> to actually authorize me to ask him. Not that 
            <persName>Braithwaite</persName> did not want to, but he is so procrastinating. However, I naturally have not 
            done any complaining about this difficulty to <persName>Richard</persName>, as I do not want to make him feel that anything he does has 
            put me out at all. He needs all his courage now, and all the affection and understanding we can 
            all of us give him. <persName>Braithwaite</persName> behaved like a trump about it. That 
         </pb>
            man is the most loyal thing, barring yourself, I have yet struck! He instantly asked me to tell <persName>Richard</persName> that he 
            should hold the position open for him when he returned from the war, and should get 
            no one else to take it in the interval. But if I were you, I should take it informally 
            while you are in <placeName>England</placeName>. I think an article on the state of poetry in <placeName>England</placeName> at this 
            moment would be very acceptable to <persName>Braithwaite</persName>. However, please understand that I have not 
            spoken to him about it and am not writing with his authority. They sold 2600 copies 
            on the newsstands alone of <title>the second number</title>, which is pretty fine I think. I am going 
            to ask <persName>Braithwaite</persName> if you subscribed, and if you did not, I shall subscribe for you, 
            so that you may get <title>the paper</title> while you are abroad. They have got what I think 
            is a really fine <title>poem </title>by <persName>Bodenheim</persName> in the next number.</p>
         <p>
            I had a letter from <persName>William Carlos Williams</persName> this morning, asking me to send a 
            poem for the August number of “<title>Others</title>,” which he is editing “pro tem.”  
            I do not know whether <persName>Kreymborg</persName> is ill or away. I wrote and told <persName>him</persName> about 
            our conversation with <persName>Kreymborg</persName> in <placeName>New York</placeName>, and said that, although I 
            thought my original objections to “<title>Others</title>” had been more or less done 
            away with by their more recent publications, nevertheless that you and I had made 
            this agreement that we would stay out together, and that I could not therefore change. 
            I like <persName>Williams</persName>, and I do not want him to be angry, and I wrote the 
            letter as nicely as I could. “<title>Others</title>” comes out most uncertainly 
            now that <orgName>Marshall</orgName> is publishing it, and I think there must be some hitch 
            in <persName>Kreymborg</persName>’s “<title>Mushrooms</title>,” for I received a letter from 
            <persName>Marshall</persName> – a personal letter signed with his name – two or three days ago, 
            saying that he was enclosing a circular, and might he send me a few <title>copies</title>; 
            and as I had already had a circular, without any letter, when <title>the book</title> first appeared, 
            I can only assume that things are not going well there. 
         </p>
         <p>
            What is more important, I fear that <persName>Sandburg</persName>’s <title>book</title> is not selling very well 
            either. They have entirely ceased to advertise it, and I have seen very few 
            references to it in any paper. Of course, I do not get his 
            </pb>
            reviews, but there is 
            nothing like the furor there was over “<title>Spoon River</title>” last year or over <persName>Frost</persName>’s books.   
         </p>
         <p>
            My own affairs are going remarkably smoothly. <persName>Lebowich</persName> tells me that they had a 
            quantity of letters for and against the “<title>Docket</title>,” and he told 
            Mr. <persName>Braithwaite</persName> he wished he could get another poem that produced so much 
            of a sensation. A good many of the letters, I fear, were hostile, but I 
            take all that in the day’s work now. 
         </p>
         <p>
            “<title>Sword Blades</title>” has just gone into another edition, to my intense satisfaction. 
            I have agreed to speak before the <orgName>Washington University Association</orgName> 
            in <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> on the <date>7th of November</date>, giving the same lecture that 
            I gave in <placeName>Chicago</placeName> last year; and they tell me that they may ask me later to 
            repeat my four <placeName>Chicago</placeName> lectures in the Spring. I am also to repeat 
            these four lectures at the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, 
            and I think I shall hire the Vendome and give them here on my own 
            recognizances after my return from St. Louis. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Mrs. “Jack” <persName>Gardner</persName> has just caught on to us. I read her some of my things 
            the other day at <persName>Bessie Perkin</persName>’s, and she has been raving about those 
            Napoleonic pieces ever since. Now she is all agog – evidently thinks she 
            has got hold of a new thing which it is very well worth while for her to know. 
            You know she always likes to be in the swim. I am sending her your 
            two <title>books</title> to-day. She will make an excellent advertising agent for us; 
            nothing could be better. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I have sent “<title>Malmaison</title>” to <persName>Margaret Anderson</persName>, but I have not 
            had a word in return. I do not know whether the duns have got her, or whether she is a little slow, 
            or whether she does not like the poem. I sent five poems to “<title>The Independent</title>” 
            the other day, and to my intense aston-
            </pb>
            ishment they took them all, and said 
            they would like a sketch of me by <persName>Frost</persName> on the opposite page. I do not think 
            that <persName>Frost</persName> does this sort of thing, and I suggested <persName>Louis Untermeyer</persName>. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName>Richard</persName> writes me that <persName>Miss Weaver</persName> positively refused to print 
            <persName>Jean Untermeyer</persName>’s “<title>Clothes</title>.” That is awfully embarrassing, as 
            <persName>Richard</persName> accepted it, and I told her so. But the good <persName>Braithwaite</persName> 
            instantly helped me out of the hole by accepting it himself. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I am enclosing a little clipping about you which came the other day. 
            There are no reviews of any account yet. I have sent all I have got to 
            <persName>Richard</persName>, so you can get them. The best one so far is by 
            <persName>William Lyon Phelps</persName> and will appear in the July number of 
            the “<title>Poetry Review</title>.” If <persName>Braithwaite</persName> only had some idea of choosing poetry, 
            he could make that a good paper, for he has got a wonderful 
            business hustler in <persName>that Jew</persName>. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I do hope you will come back in the Autumn, because I think the fruit 
            is ripe, and you don’t want it to tumble to the ground and rot, 
            because there is no one here to pick it. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I wish you would send me a sketch of your early life – of all your life, up to 
            date – with anecdotes and things, for I am preparing my lectures 
            along the line of my French lectures, and I want some biographical material 
         </p>
         <p>
            I suppose by the time you get this you will be married, in which case please 
            remember me most kindly to <persName>your wife</persName>, and tell her that I hope we shall be 
            great friends always and that I am very anxious to see her and welcome her into 
            our little circle. <persName>Mrs. Russell</persName> has not yet come back, but I expect her 
            a week from Sunday. It is beautiful here now, but very hot for the first time, 
            and up to now it has done nothing but rain, day in and day out. I envy you being 
            in <placeName>England</placeName> again, even in war time. One gets rather stale staying in the same place.
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName>Bodenheim</persName> has departed, I think stealing his way to <placeName>California</placeName> on 
            freight cars – that is the way he intended to go. He came round 
            and told me a marvelous story of wishing to be there on <date>June 15th</date>, 
            to stretch him-
            </pb>
            self upon the grave of his beloved and vow to lead a 
            better life. For this purpose, he needed <!--transaction-->$150.00, and he wished to 
            sell two <title>plays</title>, with all the rights – “movie” and otherwise – 
            for cash down, in order to get there; and he wanted to know if I knew 
            anybody who would take the plays on these terms. Needless to remark, 
            I did not, and I was not such a fool as to be “touched” for the 
            hundred and fifty. But I gave him a <!--transaction -->cheque to cover the damage<persName>Mary</persName> 
            inflicted upon his overcoat, and I am sure that cheque will never go 
            into a new coat; it will go into food and drink as long as it lasts. 
            He was to let me know if he didn’t start, and as he has not let me know, 
            I suppose he has gone. He read me an excellent poem, the best he has done I 
            think, and I instantly told him to take it to <persName>Braithwaite</persName>; and then I rang 
            up Braithwaite and told him how good the poem was, with the result that 
            he accepted it; and it appears in <title>the July number</title>. I am afraid he did not 
            get paid in advance, however; but they do pay on <title>that paper</title>, some months 
            late, so he will get the money in the end. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I guess that is all my news, except that I miss our Sunday 
            chats very much. Write again and often! 
         </p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>