<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
               key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-10-11">11 October 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$69i  </idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 6 pages long (seq. 69-74). It is typed on good quality typing 
                     paper (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). 
                     The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page. </p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-10-11">October 11, 1916</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>Your letter of <date when="1916-09-25">September 25th</date> has this minute come, and I was awfully interested to see 
            what you said about the state of mind of our little group. My feeling is exactly yours. 
            The “<title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title>” has done exactly what I hoped it would do – in fact, it has done more than in my wildest 
            dreams/ever dared to hope. But I think the moment for its usefulness has gone by. 
            I don’t believe there is much point in having another. 
            I think that another would sell about as well as this one has, which, I imagine, is not bad, 
            that is, judging from their statement on the <date when="1916-08-01">first of August.</date> 
            Since getting your letter I telephoned in to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName>, and 
            he is to tell me the exact sale on Friday (to-morrow being a holiday) and I will add it as a 
            postscript to this letter before sending it off. </p>
         
         <p>I don’t, personally, think there is any real getting together 
            between you and me and the other members of the group. I don’t count <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>, 
            because he never was an Imagist and never cared a snap about the tenets. 
            <persName key="hilda_doolittle">H.D.</persName> is, as you say, excessively narrow. I was awfully annoyed with her articles on 
            <persName key="marianne_moore">Mary Anne Moore</persName><!-- spelled incorrectely in the letter - ppm --> and a woman named <persName>Mew</persName>, 
            in the August and September “<title key="egoist">Egoist</title>”;they are so jejune and so over-praised. 
            In fact, I have written her a letter objecting 
            to that form of criticism coming from any one of our group, 
            but I don't think I shall send the letter – at least, not in its present form, 
            for I think that Hilda is pretty well overwrought. 
            She is trying to do a job on that paper for which she is by no means fitted, 
            and they have not seen me for so many years that I don’t believe they are very inclined to 
            take my criticism on anything.</p>
         
         <p>Personally, I should much rather not have any “Anthology” this year. 
            I think the anthology business is run into the ground anyhow, with 
            <title key="magazineVerse">Braithwaite’s</title>, and <title key="poetry">Harriet’s</title>, and all the others, and I think the time has 
            come when we have got to go it on our own. If we ever develop individually; it is quite plain that 
            we cannot hold to the narrow tenets that please Hilda. But still, you know my sense of honour, 
            and I said I would do it for three years, and I will.</p>
         
         <p>Greenslet says that they are still going to print the “<title key="newPoetrySeries">New Poetry Series</title>,” 
            but maybe they won’t call it that, and they are going to vary the 
            covers of the individual volumes, which I think is a good idea. 
            Our contract said nothing about the series anyway, and he is quite willing 
            to carry it (the Anthology) on again this year; although he agrees with me that it has done its job. </p>
         
         <p>
            Now from the letters that I have had from Richard and Hilda, 
            I feel quite sure that they will both feel it a good deal if we 
            abandon this year’s “Anthology”. I am afraid Hilda’s book is not 
            going to sell at all over here, I don't know how it has done in 
            <placeName key="england">England</placeName> – do you? Maybe we are quits, because my books do not sell in England. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I had already made up my mind to send “<title>Lacquer Prints</title>” as my contribution. 
            Whether they will make a full contribution or not I don’t know. I have not counted yet. 
            If they do not, I will add something to them. </p>
         <p>
            Your “<title>Lincoln</title>” is a superb poem. I was reading it again only yesterday, and I think you 
            certainly must have it for one of your three. I see from <persName key="edmund_brown"></persName>Brown’s list that he is 
            publishing your “<title>Japanese Prints</title>” as one of his little booklets. 
            Evidently you have not instructed him to send me a copy, so I shall just go and get one. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <title key="menWomenGhosts">My book</title> is not out yet. I shall certainly send it to you as soon as it is. 
            <orgName>They</orgName> hope to publish it a week from to-day, but I do not think they will get it out until 
            the week after that. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I told Hilda to have the contributions here to me by the <date when="1916-12-01">first of December</date>, and that I would have 
            mine over there by that date. I don’t know how to sound <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard </persName>and Hilda about this year’s “Anthology”, 
            and as I am quite convinced from their letters that they want it, I guess we had better go ahead and 
            round the thing up squarely.  
         </p>
         <p>
            Mr. <persName key="ec_marsh">Marsh</persName> tells me that the advance sale on "<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men, Women, and Ghosts</title>” 
            is the best I have had for any book so far, even “<title key="sexFrenchPoets">Six French Poets</title>,” which is hopeful. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I am fearfully tired, for I have just finished a <title>long poem</title> on 
            Lord Nelson and Lady Hamilton, in polyphonic, a sort of companion piece to 
            "<title>Malmaison</title>". <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> thinks it is the strongest thing I have done, 
            but she is the only person who has seen it so far – she and my secretary, 
            and I guess they are both prejudiced. Anyhow, I am not going to do any more 
            until I come back from <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> and <placeName key="stLouis">St. Louis</placeName>, 
            whither I am going in about ten days. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            There is, to my mind, a chance that Richard may grow. 
            You say he is already altered. But I don’t believe there is any hope of H.D.’s 
            changing materially in any way, and I am quite sure that <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> is absolutely done. 
            I am just as sick of being bound up in a group as you are. I still think that Imagism, 
            as you and I interpret it, is a splendid movement, but narrowed, as H.D. would have 
            us narrow it, I think means death. It does to me, anyhow. We should go ahead with this 
            “Anthology’, however, as if it were all right, because I have already hinted to 
            Richard and Hilda that I thought its usefulness was over, and as they have not taken the hint, 
            I feel we had better finish up brown. Of course there is no question of there ever being another after this. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I still hope that you will change your mind about staying over there too long, 
            because I believe distinctly that your future is here, although, of course, 
            you must do as you think best. But from everything I hear about England, 
            it is all war over there now. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            People are pretty well wrought up here, with the German 
            submarine exploits off <placeName key="nantucket">Nantucket</placeName>. I hope it will have a good effect at 
            the election and bring <persName key="charles_evan_hughes">Hughes</persName> in triumphantly. 
            <persName key="woodrow_wilson">Wilson</persName>’s policy has been a disgrace to the country. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            I wish I had been with you all at your meeting the other day. 
            It is jolly homesick here without anybody. However, some day the <rs key="ww1" type="theme">war</rs> will end, 
            and if you don’t come home, I can go over there. 
         </p>
         
         <closer>Affectionately yours, </closer>
         
         <postscript>P.S.
            <p>
                  Ferris Greenslet has just telephoned that we have sold 700 copies up to date – 
                  somewhat over 500 here, and 160 sent to England. That, you will see, 
                  is a little over 300 copies since the first of August, which I think is not bad at all. 
            </p>
            <p>
               I have just had rather an unpleasant passage of arms with 
               <persName key="wc_williams">William Carlos Williams</persName>. I am sending you the correspondence. 
               The first letter I took as half a joke, and answered accordingly. 
               It was either a joke or an insult – I preferred to take it as the former. 
               The second letter admitted of no question. I enclose a copy of my answer. 
               You were quite right in suspecting that "<title key="others">Others</title>" had gone to the wall, 
               and it proves to me more conclusively than anything else could, that art which is not sincere 
               has no chance. It may make a splash for five minutes, but it counts 
               for nothing in the long run. You will see from Williams’s letter how active our friend 
               <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> is in distributing lies. To be sure, he lied to me about Hilda before I knew her, 
               and about Lawrence before I knew him, and in neither case had he the same motive for 
               falsifying facts that he has now.  I like Williams, and I believe him to be sincere. 
               He is evidently terribly bitter over the failure of “Others”, and utterly bamboozled by 
               Ezra. I feel sure that he will not come to see me when I am in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName>. I think he is 
               too upset to desire to be just. It is as well to know how matters stand with that group, 
               although they can’t hurt us in any way. 
            </p>
            <p>
               But this letter of Williams’s, and the failure of 
               “Others” makes me feel a little differently about the publication of the 
               1917 "Anthology”. I think now that it is well to print it, in order to show them 
               and the public at large that we have not gone under in the “Others” crash, 
               that our movement is still flourishing. 
            </p>
            <p>
               I have sent copies of the Williams correspondence to Hilda, 
               and I suppose she will show it to Richard. And I have also told her just what I think about the 
               "Anthology", and that I think it is well to keep it up through this year, as we planned. 
            </p>
            <p>
               I don’t believe in five years anything will be heard of the 
               Ezra group. I am sorry for Ezra, he had such an overwhelming 
               conceit that it must be hard to find himself kicking about in a backwater. But he has only himself to thank. 
            </p>
         </postscript>
         
    
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
