<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="../../ALLP_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                    key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1917-02-16">16 February 1917</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="">
                    <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="">
                        <!-- insert name -->
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="">
                    <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$98i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>This letter is 2 pages long (seq. 98-99). It is typed on good quality typing paper (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, 
                            but somewhere in between). The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page.  </p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following:
                    <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </x>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1917-02-16">February 16, 1917</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>
                Here is our February account from <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton-Mifflin</orgName>, from which you will see that we made $167.65 <!--transaction-->. 
                The $1.50 refers to a copy which was bound up especially for a subscriber and which they charged me for on the last bill by accident. 
                Your share, or one-sixth of this amount, is <add place ="left">£</add><!--the addition is vague and done in pencil--><del rend="strikethrough">5.6.2</del>, for which I am enclosing draft.  
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be glad to hear that <title>our first volume</title> is in its third edition, <title>our second volume</title> in its second and that I am correcting the proofs of the 
                third volume today. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I took <title key="underTheGuns">your book</title> in to <persName key="roger_scaife">Mr. Scaife</persName> the other day and read him “Lincoln” and some other poems from it, 
                and did everything in my power to make him feel that it as a remarkable book and that he should not fail to publish it, 
                but the truth is they are dreadfully wary just now about accepting books with war hanging over us and the uncertainty of the market. 
                I am going off on my Western lecture trip tomorrow, so I telephoned in to him to know if he had made any decision 
                about your book. He says that he is rather doubtful about publishing it. I urged and urged him to do so, said everything I could, 
                but the best I could get out of him was that he would make no decision himself, which I think is wise, 
                considering how little he knows about literature, but would wait for <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Feris Greenslet</persName> to decide upon it and would hold 
                the manuscript over until Feris got home or until you saw Feris in <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, which I advise you to do immediately, 
                and do everything in your power to interest him in the book and not to antagonize him, because I think 
                Feris Greenslet is genuinely interested in you and you stand much more chance with him than with Scaife. 
            </p>
            <pb/>
            <p>
                I also asked Scaife if he would give your “<title>Washington</title>” to <persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sedgwick</persName>, as I felt that I was the last person 
                to whom Ellery would listen, and he promised to have it typewritten and sent in to Ellery. I will remind him of this, 
                but I have not much hope there, as Ellery is such a stand-patter.
            </p>
            <p>
                I dare not send the other poems around for fear Houghton-Mifflin will accept the book after all, 
                and then we shall have to take them out of the hands of the magazines in order to get them in time for the book. 
                This is all terribly disturbing, and I trust you realize that I am doing my best with a most difficult state of affairs. 
                Do let me know if you see Feris and what he says. 
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be glad to know that “<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>” has gone into a third edition, 
                so I think we are all looking up, but I do think the publishers are more and more chary of publishing books on their own responsibility. 
                Personally, I believe that if we knew the truth, we should find that a great many of the books of verse were published by the authors or kind friends of the authors. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I should think the closeness of <placeName key="usa">America</placeName> to war would make your book more valuable, 
                and I am sure that if you work Feris right that you can get your point with him, and Scaife says that he will take Feris’s opinion absolutely. 
            </p>
            <p>I am in a great hurry finishing up last things, so I shall not write any more now. </p>
          
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>,
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
