<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1914-11-27">27
                  November 1914</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$4i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is six pages long (seq. 4-9). It is typed on what seems to be
                     notebook paper, which is torn in the bottom right-hand corner of the first
                     page, and on the left side of the paper for the rest of the pages. There are
                     several places where the text runs off the page on the right margin. The words
                     "John Gould" are written in pencil across the top of the first page.
                     Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1914-11-25">November 27, 1914.</date></dateline>
            <salute>My dear Mr. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>After I wrote to you yesterday I had a telephone message from Mr. <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Greenslet</persName> of <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin Company</orgName> to say that they have definitely accepted your <title key="irradiations">book</title>. I hurriedly added
            the thing in a postscript and sent off the letter but did enter into details. Now here
            is the arrangement I have made for you which I hope you will approve. Ferris Greenslet
            has conceived the idea, pushed thereto largely by many criticisms against the way
            publishers treat modern poetry, to issue a series of small books in paper covers at the
            price of fifty cents each <gap reason="illegible" quantity="2"
               unit="character"/> that they may reach everybody. He intends to
            be very careful and only have the very best poetry in this series. Of course his <gap reason="illegible" quantity="9" unit="character"/><!--my best guess is "intention" here--> may not always agree with ours, as I think it is possible he may not always
            consider best poetry what we consider so, <gap reason="illegible" quantity="5"
               unit="character"/></pb> for one volume and <title key="some_imagist_poets">our anthology</title> for another. I believe he intends to have something of <persName key="lawrence_binyon">Lawrence Binyon</persName>’s for
            another volume, and whatever we may personally think of Lawrence Binyon he has
            sufficient good standing to have his name carry weight and dignity. I think another
            volume is going to be a collection of all the translations which <persName key="lafcadio_hearn">Lafcadio Hearn</persName> made
            from Japanese poetry which are scattered through his writings and have never been
            collected before. You will see therefore from the start it is going to be rather an
            unusual and interesting series. I think I know enough of the situation to feel that any
            book issued in this series will stand just about as much chance of succeeding with the
            public as any book issued separately. I think therefore it is the best possible way for
            your book and our anthology to appear.</p>
         <p>The terms I have agreed to are that he shall publish the book at his own expense but he
            will then keep the proceeds up to the amount of what he spent in publishing, and</pb> give
            you ten percent of the proceeds of all the sales. This is not a very brilliant
            arrangement, monetarily, but considering the great difficulty in persuading any
            publisher to take poetry and the utter indifference of the public, which I must say
            largely justifies the publisher, and the almost complete lack of sale for books of any
            kind except war books at the moment, I am sure that this is as good an arrangement as
            any one could have made for your book. Of course if you do not like any of this the
            contract is not yet signed (naturally, as I have not signed it) and you can withdraw
            from the transaction if you want to, but I can assure you that the Houghton Mifflin
            Company are the most honest publishers that you will find in <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>.</p>
         <p>I did not offer your book to <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> as I knew they were over stocked with poetry but
            as you know I did offer it to <persName key="thomas_mosher">Mosher</persName> and also put out a feeler in that regard to</pb> <gap reason="illegible" quantity="9" unit="character"/> it was refused. Macmillans turned down our anthology largely, I
            think, on account of <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> writing them an insulting letter about the advertisement of my
            book, and they told me with great vigor that they did not wish to be connected with the
            "<orgName key="imagists">group</orgName>." Houghton Mifflin, on the other hand are anxious to be connected with the group
            as you see from their being willing to print your book and the anthology. I think it is
            the best publishing proposition for poetry I have heard of for a long time and I believe
            that with books at fifty cents and a big publishing house like Houghton Mifflin Company
            behind it will have a very great chance to gain the popular ear.</p>
         <p>They kick at <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>’s "Heaven" for the anthology. In fact their acceptance of that
            book depends upon the removal of that poem and something else substituted less alien to
            the puritan susceptibilities of most of the partners. I will talk to you about this on
            Tuesday. In the mean time I have written to <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> and asked him what he thinks of it
            and to tell him that I think the only chance</pb> of publishing in a first class house is
            this one. I think it is better to sacrifice one poem than to have to take the book to a
            small firm like <orgName key="boniLiveright">Boni</orgName>’s. I have not put your preface in the book. I am afraid that it
            would not get people to read the book, I think it would antagonize them to start with. I
            think some sort of preface is an excellent thing, but I think you should assume that
            your readers are in sympathy with you. They must be in some sort of sympathy, if only
            curiosity, or they would never have bought the book, and I do not think it is good
            policy to kick the <gap reason="illegible" quantity="5" unit="character"/> in the preface, but again we can talk this over on
            Tuesday.</p>
         <p>I am only writing you this that you may know just where you stand. Of course you know
            that this whole series will be handled by <orgName key="constable">Constable</orgName>’s in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. I believe it to be a
            very excellent publishing venture.</p>
         <p>I am terribly doubtful whether these letters will ever reach you. I am sending them to the main <orgName key="americanExpress">American Express</orgName> office as I have not the slightest idea where else to send
            them and you said American Express in your letter. I do hope you will give me a more
            definite address before long because I feel quite at sea as to your whereabouts. I leave
            here on Monday as I wrote you Tuesday and go to the <placeName key="hotelStRegis">Hotel St. Regis</placeName>, <placeName key="fifthAvenue">Fifth Avenue</placeName>, where
            you can get me either by letter or telephone. Looking forward very much to Tuesday
            night, believe me.</p>
         <closer>Yours very sincerely,</closer>



      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
