<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1915-06-23">23
                  June 1915</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$15i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 4 pages long (seq. 15-18). It is typed on something like
                     notebook paper and words are printed on the page in a slanted manner. The words
                     "John Gould " are written in pencil across the top of the first page.
                     Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1915-06-23">June 23, 1915.</date></dateline>
            <salute>My dear Mr. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I feel as though you had died, and I wonder where you are and what you are doing.</p>
         <p>I send you <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName>’s article on us in "<title key="newRepublic">The New Republic</title>," which I think is really
            very good, and also his review of your <title key="irradiations">book</title>, which is not so good; but still it has good
            space, and I think he meant it well. He says he is not satisfied with it, because he
            wrote it in a hurry, as he wanted to get it in; he felt no more time ought to elapse,
            and he was right there.</p>
         <p><persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> tells me excellent things. He says that in a review in "<title key="townAndCountry">Town and Country</title>" about another book, they said that three things of importance had happened this
            year: the European war, "The New Republic," and Imagist poetry. And he tells me that the
            <title key="some_imagist_poets">Anthology</title> is selling about five copies a day.</p>
         <p><persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> wrote me a <foreign xml:lang="fr">cri du coeur</foreign> and said that Miss <persName key="harriet_weaver">Weaver</persName> had cut out his note on us for
            the June number. That was a shame; but he says you wrote him you did not want to be
            defended</pb> anyway, so you won’t be disappointed.</p>
         <p><persName key="may_sinclair">May Sinclair</persName>'s article is very good. I am sending you an "<title key="egoist">Egoist</title>."</p>
         <p>I went in and saw <persName key="brown">Brown</persName> about "<persName key="poetryJournal">The Poetry Journal</persName>," and I think you are all right to
            send him something. I believe they mean to do well. He asked me for something, and I
            sent him an old poem of mine I do not care much about; but it is less modern than some
            things, and I do not believe he would take the very modern ones.</p>
         <p><persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery</persName> refused my polyphonic "Windmill," as I might have known he would; and I sent it
            off to <persName key="william_benet">William Rose Benet</persName>, who is on the editorial staff of "<title key="century">The Century</title>." He wrote back
            a tremendously enthusiastic letter, and said he had recommended it for publication to
            the <persName>head editor</persName><!--not sure who this is. Doty? (based on letter to H. D.). XEH-->; but, of course, I do not know whether said head editor will smile or
            not.</p>
         <p>I wish you would send me a copy of the "Clipper Ships," and let me try "The New Republic" with it.</p>
         <p>What has Greenslet done about your book? He told me that he thought it was too soon to
            bring it out at once, but he seemed to have distinct leanings toward keeping it and
            bringing it</pb> out later.</p>
         <p>Did you go to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, and did you see <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>? She wrote Ferris a letter, pitching into
            us for not having mentioned her in the preface, and I have written her an answer,
            mentioning that she conducts a <title key="poetry">magazine</title>, and that she was treated as all magazine
            editors always are; but I think we had better put in a paragraph in the preface of the
            1916 Anthology, giving her a send-off.</p>
         <p>We have put Mrs. <persName key="grace_conkling">Conkling</persName> into your place on the Executive Committee of the <orgName key="poetsClub">Poetry Club</orgName>,
            and I really think that little society may be amusing in the end.</p>
         <p>I have been slaving at my French poets, and they are now being typewritten. The
            translations I have not yet tackled. I have not written any poetry since you left, but I
            have got a couple of ideas which I shall tackle when I get settled in <placeName key="dublin">Dublin</placeName>. I think I
            shall go up just about the Fourth.</p>
         <p>Do write and tell me what you are doing</pb> and if you have written anything. After having
            seen you practically daily for four months, it seems awfully funny not to know anything
            about you.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
