<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1915-07-27">27
                  July 1915</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$22i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 3 pages long (seq. 22-24). It is typed on something like
                     notebook paper and words are printed on the page in a slanted manner at
                     times,.The words "John Gould " are written in pencil across the top of the
                     first page. Unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1915-07-27">July 27, 1915.</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear Mr. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>I am enclosing two reviews which <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> sent me. <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName>’s, as you see, is a very nasty
            attack upon us three, no one of us being willing to kowtow to him. It seems that he
            tried to persuade Richard to leave us in the lurch last winter and have nothing more to
            do with us. I think Richard has behaved awfully well, as he absolutely refused to
            listen. Of course, the violent praise of <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> is by way of putting us still farther in
            the background. I do not mind the article in the least, and I hope you won’t; and I
            think the dignified thing for us to do is to pretend we have not seen it or, if we have,
            that it is not worthy of attention. That is what Richard is going to do, and that is
            what I am going to do. Hueffer is a beastly German cad. Richard says that he and <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>
            are thick again. He is just sore about <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> not being willing to print his
            "Heaven." We are quitting him for good, and I am not sorry.</p></pb>
         <p>The other article is by <persName key="edward_storer">Edward Storer</persName> in the "<title key="britishReview">British Review</title>," and, as Richard says, it
            means to be nice. But Richard says he greatly prefers the Greek things, so that he likes
            Richard and <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> best. I am sorry he understands you so little, but the review just
            shows how different the American and the English types of mind are. The Americans have
            some comprehension of the imaginative, and the English not a rag.</p>
         <p>I was not overcome with joy at <persName key="padraic_colum">Padraic Colum</persName>’s article on us. But then, what can you
            expect? He has his way to make, and he obviously is not one of us; so he thinks the best
            rôle to pursue is that of the superior critic.</p>
         <p>I do not think it is worth while your writing to "<title key="transcript">The Transcript</title>" about the preface. We
            all agree with your preface absolutely and, though it did not happen to be the preface
            to "<title key="some_imagist_poets">Some Imagist Poets</title>," it might have been; and in slamming it, they are slamming their
            point of view just as much as yours.</p>
         <p>A ridiculous paper here called "<title key="zionsHerald">Zion’s Herald</title>" put in a piece to the effect that I was
            the editor of the <title key="newPoetrySeries">New Poetry Series</title>. I wrote to them at</pb> once, because I am certainly not
            going to be made responsible for Greenslet’s taste.</p>
         <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> is much. better, I am thankful to say, and she leaves day after to-morrow
            for the West, and I go up to <placeName key="dublin">Dublin</placeName> on Friday. So send your next letter there.</p>
         <p>I trust the baby is better, and that your sister’s<!--not sure which baby or which sister--> trip to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> will do her good.</p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
