<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
               key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-10-25">25 October 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$75i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 2 pages long (seq. 75-76). It is typed on good quality typing paper 
                     (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). 
                     The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page. </p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-10-25">October 25, 1916</date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
         
         <p>I got your generous letter of <date when="1916-10-07">October 7th</date>. 
            I am awfully glad you liked “<title>Thompson’s Restaurant</title>” and “<title>Opera House</title>”, 
            but as to my going you one better, that’s a matter of opinion. 
            You must not depreciate yourself. It is more important to invent a thing than to 
            elaborate it, and there is no living poet out of whom I have got so much inspiration as out of yourself. 
            Think what “<title>ondon Excursion</title>L” taught me! And I don’t feel that I have got 
            to the end of its possibilities yet. So strongly do I feel this debt, 
            that I have acknowledged it with thanks, in the Preface of “<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men,  Women and Ghosts</title>”. 
            As a matter of fact, you can do lots of things that I can’t do. 
            For instance, your "<title>Lincoln</title>” is a very fine thing; and the “<title>Clipper-Ships</title>” and “<title>The Old South</title>”. 
            If you envy me at times, I envy you more times. Much of your work has been my despair, 
            and I have no doubt it is because of the prick it gave me that I have 
            forced myself to do better and always better, striving to out-do you. </p>
         
         <p>
            I have just completed <title>a poem</title> on Nelson and Lady Hamilton, 
            which various people who have seen it think is the best 
            thing I have done – better even than "<title>Malmaison</title>" or "<title>The Hammers</title>". 
            It is about as long as "The Hammers", and I don't 
            believe will get into any magazine, therefor. So when it will see the light of day, Goodness only knows. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            You can’t think how I miss our Sunday evening talks, and all our alliance, offensive and defensive. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            The <title key="menWomenGhosts">new book</title> has had two excellent reviews, one by <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName>, 
            and, strangely enough, an even more complimentary one by <persName key="william_reedy"></persName>William Marion Reedy, in “The Mirror”. 
            I won’t send them along, because they are just about my book, and not about the Imagists. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            Meanwhile, however, jealousy goes on apace. I send you the last letter in 
            my correspondence with <persName key="wc_williams">Williams</persName>. I have not answered it, nor shall I. 
            I think that incident is closed – not with flying colours on the part 
            of the <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> section. I knew that Williams preferred to hide behind vague generalities, 
            to coming to see me and making his charges specific. Now I have proved it. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            <persName key="josephine_peabody">Josephine</persName> has turned nasty too, but I suppose that was to be expected. 
            She has written me a beastly letter, all full of hypocritical commiserations, 
            because she “finds this book less good than ‘<title key="swordBlades">Sword Blades</title>’.” 
            As she is the only person who has hitherto said so – the verdict being, 
            as a rule, the other way – I do not worry. Of course I knew last Winter that she was turning sour, 
            but this year she is hopelessly curdled. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            <persName key="odell_shepard"></persName>Odell Shepard has got a doctor’s degree, and is Dr. Shepard – annoying things! 
            The magazines simply bristle with his opinions about poetry, which makes me sick. 
            But my edition is very nearly sold out, a week after publication, and 
            <persName>Mr. Marsh</persName> thinks we shall have to have a new one before Christmas. I hope to Goodness that is true. 
         </p>
         
         <p>
            So things go here. No more at this present writing, as our ancestors used to say. 
         </p>
         
         <closer>Always your affectionate old friend, </closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
