<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
               key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-08-05">05 August 1916</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="">
               <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
            </editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$56i </idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>This letter is 5 pages long (seq. 56-60). It is typed on good quality typing paper 
                     (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, buy somewhere in between). 
                     The words “John Gould” are written in pencil across the top of the first page. </p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:
               <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
            </p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <opener><dateline><date when="1916-08-05">August 5, 1916 </date></dateline>
            <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
         <p>
            I feel very guilty when I think I have two letters from you to answer. 
            I do not know where time goes to, but it certainly goes, and I wake up to find 
            that more of it has elapsed between letters than I intended.  
         </p>
         <p>
            I think you are quite right about our being independent in sending to magazines, 
            now that you are so far away. I was not at all surprised that you sent to “<title>Others</title>,” 
            I was only surprised that you did not tell me; but it does not make the 
            slightest difference, and as you will see, I send a poem to <title>that number</title> after 
            being told by <persName>Williams</persName> that you had done so. I do not think much of it as a number, 
            I am bound to confess, and as it had my two horrors, <persName>Jeanne d’Orge</persName> and 
            <persName>Minna Loy</persName> in it, 
            I was not too pleased to think I had contributed. However, that is all over now. 
            I refused to send another poem to <persName>Helen Hoyt</persName>’s <title>Women’s Number,</title> as I thought that with 
            Helen Hoyt for editor the contributions would be of the most lively. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName>Braithwaite</persName> tells me that he owes you <measure>$1.50 </measure>(large sum) for your poem in 
            <title>“The Poetry Review,”</title> and he asked where he should send it. 
            I told him he had better send it to me, as I was writing to you 
            all the time; but it has not appeared, and I am writing by this mail 
            direct to <persName>Lebowich</persName> to dun him for it. 
         </p>
         <p>
            There is a new magazine being got up here, or rather in 
            New York, called “<title>The Seven Arts</title>.” An unknown donor is giving the money, 
            and they are to carry it on for a year. If at the end of that time the 
            anonymous donor does not like the results, he will withdraw his support, 
            and they will have to do the best they can on the reputation 
            they have made during that year. If on the other hand he does 
            like it, he will continue to pay the bills. They are to pay on 
            acceptance, but whether their pay is large or small I do not know. 
            The editor is <persName>James Oppenheim</persName>, and there are about eight sub-editors, 
            two of whom are <persName>Louis Untermeyer</persName> and <persName>Robert Frost</persName>. They say they 
            represent no school and have no propaganda, but are going to publish 
            everything that is good. It is to contain not only poetry but critical work 
            and everything pertaining to the arts. I am a little doubtful whether 
            it is to include fiction or not. It sounds well. They have already 
            solicited contributions from me, and I imagine that they would like 
            you to contribute also. The first number is to be out in October 
            I think. This seems to be the only bit of real news I have. 
         </p>
         <p>
            The sale of the <title>Imagist 1916 Anthology</title> is only 
            35 volumes short of the 1915 volume at this date, 
            although they have not yet sent any to <placeName>England</placeName>. 
            With their usual policy of letting things slide, the book was 
            not forced upon the English house. I had a talk with <persName>Greenslet</persName> 
            about this before I left <placeName>Boston</placeName>, and he regretted extremely 
            the stupidity of their office in not having seen to this, 
            but said it was when he was away on his vacation, that he had 
            now written, and that their contracts with Constable were such 
            that they could not refuse to take the book. I have written 
            him again about it, having received his statement as follows: 
            <measure>
            249 Imagist Poets,  1915.      .36 ¼    $90.26 
            389   “         ”   1916.      .36 ¼    141.01 
            </measure>                                        231.27 
         </p>
         <p>
            I enclose a draft for b8-1-7 , your share of the 
            gross profits of the two volumes. There are three <measure>(3) undivided 
            cents</measure>, which I was keeping on commission!!! We inserted a new 
            advertisement, embodying a paragraph from Mrs. <persName>Aldis</persName>’s review 
            of some of <persName>Phelps</persName>’s, two weeks ago, and I think I shall 
            advertise it again in about a month. That I think will be sufficient. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I have asked <persName>Lebowich</persName> to send you all the copies 
            of “<title>The Poetry Review</title>” from the beginning of the year. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I suppose you see "<title>The Little Review</title>" or can get it at the 
            <placeName>Poetry Bookshop</placeName>. <persName>Margaret Anderson</persName> has moved to 
            <placeName>California</placeName> for the 
            Summer.  Her address is: <placeName>P. O. Box 696, Mill Valley, California</placeName>. 
            She expects to be back in <placeName>Chicago</placeName> for two months in the Autumn, 
            then to move the Review bodily to <placeName>New York</placeName>. It is not very easy to 
            get copies of it now, as she is so far away. I am sending you a 
            copy of the June-July number, however, because it contains Mrs. Aldis’s 
            review of us, which I think is extremely nice. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Thank you very much for your biographical notes, which I shall use 
            with great interest. I have not begun to write my lectures yet, but I expect to very soon. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I do hope you will write some English literary notes for 
            <persName>Braithwaite</persName>, as I think he needs the foreign element in his paper. 
            I had your poems typewritten, and have sent them to <persName>Benét</persName>, 
            but have heard nothing about them yet. Benét is always as slow 
            as cold molasses, so don’t expect to hear for some time. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I rather think you are right about “Others” breaking up.  
            This handing it over to a new editor every month looks to me 
            like the last gasp. As to “Poetry,” I think it is 
            disintegrating since <persName>Alice Henderson</persName> left. <persName>Harriet</persName>’s one desire 
            seems to be to get in new people, whether they are good for anything or not.  
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName>Mr. Bridges</persName> treated me as white as snow about 
            “<title>Battledore and Shuttlecock</title>” which appears in the August number of 
            “<title>Scribner</title>’s” with the most charming woodcuts. I am beginning to 
            think that the rowing I gave the old gentleman had a good effect. 
         </p>
         <p>
            You seem to have handed a lot of things to 
            “<title>The Poetry Journal</title>” before you left, but why 
            you gave <persName>Aiken</persName> such high praise is beyond my comprehension. 
            However, "chacun à con goût." 
         </p>
         <p>
            I suppose from your letter that you have no 
            intention of returning this Autumn. That will be a terrible blow for 
            me. However, I cannot but feel that the war will not last much 
            longer, and we can all meet again. I wish it would stop before Richard 
            gets there. I had a letter from him from the camp the other day, 
            and I must say it sounded to me more healthy in tone and happier 
            than anything I have had from him for some time. There is nothing 
            like having a thing settled, one way or the other, to give one peace 
            of mind, and I think he suffered terribly from indecision, feeling 
            that he ought to go and yet did not want to. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName>Lawrence</persName> writes us, “we are gaily ringing our last shilling.” 
            Whether that means he and his wife, or England, I do not know. 
            Even if his books are being published, I suppose it will be a long 
            time before he gets any royalties. Do let me know if he needs 
            anything, for I am worried about him. I am sending him his share 
            of the Imagist royalties, which, at the rate they live, will help a little.  
         </p>
         <p>
            <placeName>Hilda</placeName> writes that she is moving, to be near Richard at the camp, 
            and that she will send me her address. So far she has not done so, 
            and if you have it, I wish you would send it. 
         </p>
         <p>
            I have not written much since I have been up here – 
            a few shortish poems and a longish one that I rather like, 
            and an article or two, among them a criticism of Mrs. Aldis’s 
            book for Harriet. The Summer is never my best time. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Reedy tells me that he is writing an article for the "<title>Mirror</title>” 
            on my work, which I am anxious to see. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Richard writes, urging me to go out West and give some 
            talks, as he has heard that people are interested in us there. And 
            I think I may do that next Spring. <persName>Margaret Wilkinson</persName> of 
            the “<title>Los Angeles Graphic</title>” appeared the other day, 
            just before I left town. She is a nice little woman, 
            and extremely enthusiastic over us. She has a poem in this month’s 
            “Poetry” but it is not any great shakes. It seems that <persName>John Vance Cheney</persName> 
            and a man who writes under the name of "<persName>Yorick</persName>" in a <title>San Diego paper, 
            </title>are down on us and have done a lot to prejudice people against us. 
            <persName>Mrs. Howard</persName> writes from <placeName>San Diego</placeName> that she thinks she has done a little 
            to counterbalance their influence. I sincerely hope so. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Remember me to your wife, and with much love in which <persName>Mrs. Russell</persName> joins, 
         </p>
         <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>