<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="../../ALLP_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                    key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1916-12-26">26 December 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="">
                    <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="">
                        <!-- insert name -->
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="">
                    <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$83i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>This letter is 8 pages long (seq. 83-90). It is typed on good quality typing paper 
                            (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). 
                            The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page.  </p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following:
                    <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1916-12-26">December 26, 1916</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
                
            <p>Your letter of <date when ="1916-12-07">December 7th</date> came yesterday, Christmas Day, and you can imagine how unhappy it made me feel. 
                In the first place, I have really been very ill, and am far from well yet, and it is discouraging to feel that you 
                apparently think that I could not have been as ill as <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> represented, 
                because I could send you a cable. As a matter of fact, naturally the cable was only sent in my name, and at my request. 
                I was four days under morphine, and five weeks in bed with a trained nurse, and am only just beginning to get round a little. 
                One of the few things I forced myself to do during my convalescence was to read the manuscript of <title key="lovesTragedy">that book</title> of yours, 
                a labour which I now heartily regret having undertaken. It is a question of “fools rushing in”. </p>
            
            <p>
                But certainly I never expected that, whatever occurred, you would accuse me of disloyalty. 
                Certainly nothing in our association together for the last three years points that way. 
                You know quite well that I have done everything in my power to forward your work, 
                in the eyes of the public and in the eyes of individuals. I have mentioned you again and again in print, 
                I have even put my indebtedness to you in the Preface of “<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>”, and 
                I am now preparing my lecture upon you, which will be delivered in <placeName key="brooklyn">Brooklyn</placeName> and in 
                <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, and which is to appear in book form next Autumn. 
                You are perfectly aware that I have always considered you the poet with the greatest amount of genius living to-day; 
                you work has given me inspiration and interest beyond that of any contemporary poet. 
                Personally, I <pb/>care more for it all the time – that is, I care more for the style of work which attracted me at 
                first, -- and in praising you I have not acted simply for the ties of friendship, 
                (although I should have done my best to praise you had I not liked your work and still was your friend) 
                but I have praised your poetry con amore, because I felt it to be worthy of praise, 
                and because I was heartily in sympathy with it and anxious to have the world appreciate its merits. 
            </p>
            <p>
                As you yourself say in this letter, we have not always seen eye to eye, 
                and I do not like all of your poems as well as I do some of them. 
                This may be a fault in my critical faculty or it may be a fault in yours. 
                You must, of course, write as you feel. But I must, of course, speak as I feel. 
                My word would be of very little value in the eyes of the public if it were not known that 
                I had an artistic conscience, a conscience which will not permit me to lie in 
                stating my opinions upon anybody’s work. Wholesale praise, merely because one likes the 
                person is the kind of thing that has ruined Braithwaite; and it not only ruins the perpetrator, but it ruins the 
                effect of the praise on the author praised. I should certainly never go out of my way to say disagreeable 
                things about anything of yours, I should prefer to be silent; but if asked a point-blank question, 
                I should reply as I thought, as I hope you would always do in a similar case. 
            </p>
            
            <p>
                I am quite aware that you defended “<title key="patterns">Patterns</title>” magnificently last year, but I thought that you 
                really believed “Patterns” to be a good poem. I should prefer to think that than to feel you merely praised me out of friendship. 
                I want your friendship; I value it as <pb/>I do that of few people; I need it; but I do not wish your 
                friendship ever to force you into an equivocal position in regard to my work, and I do not want to feel that 
                I can only hold your friendship on the terms of artistic insincerity. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I am sorry to say that I do not think these poems in “<title key="lovesTragedy">Love’s Tragedy</title>” are as good as some of the 
                others you have done – for instance, your “<title>Lincoln</title>”, “<title>Clipper-Ships</title>”, some of “<title key="irradiations">Irradiations</title>”, 
                “<title>The Old House</title>”, the “<title>Green Symphony</title>”, the “<title>Blue Symphony</title>”, “<title>The Old South</title>”, 
                and a number of others. I am quite aware that they are different, and intended to be different, 
                but I cannot feel that they are as good of their kind as these other poems that I have mentioned are of theirs. 
            </p>
            <p>
                What happened in regard to <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet </persName>was this: Ferris telephoned me and 
                said that he had this manuscript, and that he would like to have my frank opinion upon it. 
                In other words, he was asking me to act as an expert, in the same way that <persName key="george_brett">Mr. Brett</persName> sent my 
                “<title key="sixFrenchPoets">Six French Poets</title>” to some one before deciding to accept it. 
                I could, of course, have refused the position, and I sincerely wish that I had done so. 
                I should have done so had I realized that these poems were some of the ones which I had seen three years ago, 
                and which I had told you at that time I did not entirely appreciate. As it was, I thought I might help you by urging 
                Ferris Greenslet to take the book, if I read over the manuscript; and although I was only just getting over 
                the acute stage of my illness – hardly over it, in fact – I told Ferris he might send me the manuscript. 
                When I read it I was confronted with the awful difficulty of realizing that I could not <pb/>endorse it as enthusiastically as I 
                had “Irradiations” and “<title key="goblinsAndPagodas">Goblins and Pagodas</title>”. I can tell you I suffered in this thought, for I knew perfectly well that you must 
                think highly of these poems. Love poems are always peculiarly personal to the author, and it is especially hard to have 
                them meet with a cold reception. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Now I do not say that my judgement is infallible – I only say that it is my personal judgment. 
                You had asked me to act as your agent, but you had not sent these poems through me. 
                Ferris has been very kind to me – I will tell you more about that in a minute – and he had asked me to read the 
                manuscript as a favour to him. What was I to do? He has already lost a <measure>couple of hundred dollars</measure>, or more, on each of 
                <title>your volumes</title>. Should I be just to him if I told him that I thought these poems were among the best you 
                had done when I don’t? What I did do was to sit on the fence. When he asked me point-blank exactly what I thought of these poems, 
                I told him that I did not think they were quite up to your best standard, but that I thought the public would 
                very likely enjoy them better than the poems that I preferred, and I begged him to publish them. I can do no more. 
            </p>
            <p>
                The truth is, that Ferris has got “cold feet”, he has lost so much money in poetry. 
                His decisions have been ridiculous, and the poems he has published have, many of them, been abominable, as you know. 
                I have frankly told him what I thought of such men as <persName key="shivell">Shivell</persName> and <persName key="pulsifier">Pulsifier</persName>. 
                I have even told him that he has ruined his "<title key="newPoetrySeries">New Poetry Series</title>” by the inclusion of a lot of trash. 
                I suspect it was on account of these criticisms that he asked my opinion of “Love’s <pb/>Tragedy”. 
                Had I had the slightest idea that the volume contained poems I had already seen, I should not have permitted him to send it to me. 
                But I was in an awkward position in regard to him, as you will hear: 
            </p>
            <p>
                I have had a little trouble lately with Mr. Brett in regard to my advertising. I was very much annoyed at the way they treated me, 
                because they refused to let me advertise my book as much as I thought that it ought to be advertised, even though I paid for it. 
                I felt that Mr. Brett was keeping me back to push people like <persName key="el_masters"    >Masters</persName> and <persName key="tagore">Tagore</persName>, 
                in whom he was more greatly interested. At one time I felt that I should be obliged to take my books away from <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName>. 
                In order to find out where I stood, I asked Ferris Greenslet whether he would be willing to have me return to him, 
                and he replied that they would accept me with open arms. Since then, things have been more or less straightened out with 
                Mr. Brett. Mr. Brett has expressed his belief in me, and his willingness to push me to every extent. 
                He is particularly interested in <title key="tendencies">my book on the American Poets</title>, which is coming out next year. 
                Therefore, after having received Ferris’s assurance that he would take me back, I was obliged to go and tell him that 
                once more I had decided to remain for the present with Macmillan. 
                This is not the first time this sort of thing has occurred, and all this makes it very difficult for me to refuse to do Ferris a favour. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Now here is my proposition for you; which I make purely in order to prove to you what should require no proof, viz., that I am loyal to 
                you in every possible way, as I conceive loyalty. (I do not conceive <pb/>loyalty to be the denying of one’s artistic impulses, 
                and I never wish you to say in print or in private anything which you do not believe about my work.)  
            </p>
            <p>
                If you will return to me the manuscript of “Love’s Tragedy”, I will pay for its publication, and Ferris Greenslet will 
                accept it if I take the risk, because I have already spoken to him about that. In order to save your pride, which I know well 
                and which I admire, I will only agree to print a first edition of 750 copies, and to advertise it to the price of <measure>$250</measure>, 
                which I think is more than the advertising of your other books has come to. And I will pay you no royalties whatsoever until after I have 
                been reimbursed for the manufacturing of the book and for the advertising, and you shall receive an accurate account twice a year, 
                when Ferris sends it to me. After I have been reimbursed, any royalties that come in shall go entirely to you, as I naturally have no 
                wish to make a penny out of the transaction. Should the book go into a second edition, it will at least prove its value, 
                and I shall stand corrected, but I do not feel that I should print a second edition at my expense; that will have to be paid for either 
                by you or by Ferris Greenslet. Hitherto none of your books has gone into a second edition, and if this should do so, it will prove 
                that you were right as to the book’s value, and I was wrong. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I think you can accept this offer without feeling that it in any way injures your pride, 
                as I should merely be acting as a publisher, and merely assume the risks, supposing there should be any risks, 
                of getting the book before the public. <pb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                Meanwhile, I have already told Ferris Greenslet that I thought your <title>volume of war poems</title>, 
                from the specimens I had seen, were good, and he has asked me to write you and request you to send him the volume. 
                And I rather think, in view of the present unfortunate situation, he will accept it.  
            </p>
            <p>
                I think you will see from this, that, far from being disloyal to you, I am one of your truest friends. 
                Anyhow, if your heart does not tell you that, and if all my efforts for you in the past do not tell you that, 
                I despair of your ever realizing it. But, again, I want you to understand, that fond of you as I am as a friend, 
                it is as a poet that I admire you; and it is because I do admire you so heartily and unreservedly that I have 
                pushed your work and done all that I have been able to do to get you the position which in my opinion you deserve. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I am prepared to accept whatever you choose for the <title>Imagist Anthology</title>. If you do not like the suggestions made in my 
                last letter, you are quite at liberty to abrogate them, and I will put in whatever you please and as you please it. 
                At the same time, I do feel that you have made some mistakes in getting yourself before the public, in the past. 
                I think had you taken my advice on what is, after all, a business proposition, you would have done better. I think “<title>Goblins and Pagodas</title>” 
                would have sold better had there been fewer symphonies, and had those American poems been left in. I have told Ferris so, again and again, 
                I think that, as far as the public is concerned, you make the mistake of printing too long a series of poems together, of subject too closely 
                allied, which causes the average reader to lose interest on account of <pb/>the want of variety. This I felt strongly in “Love’s Tragedy”. 
                I also think that the Preface of your last book overweighted the volume; but you did not see fit to consult me at the time of 
                its publication, and you were right here to arrange things with the publishers yourself. Of course, you must do as you think best about 
                your own poems always. This is merely my opinion. But you will notice that even my enemies, like <persName key="wc_williams">Williams</persName>, admit to my having sound business sense. 
            </p>
            <p>
                As to acting as your agent, what I intended was that I would send round such poems of yours as you chose to send me, 
                to such magazines as you designated, and that I would make myself responsible for collecting the payments for them and remitting it to you. 
                I am not in the least anxious to act as anyone’s agent, as I have more work of my own than I can attend to properly. 
                I only thought it would be a convenience, as you are so far away. But you must do exactly as you think best about that. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I trust, <persName key="john_fletcher">Dear Boy</persName>, that I have made it clear that whatever my feeling for your individual 
                poems may be, my feeling for your work as a whole is that of the very highest admiration and delight, and that I am always, 
                
            </p>
                <closer>Your most sincere and affectionate friend</closer>,
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
