<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="../../ALLP_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                    key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1917-03-29">29 March 1917</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="">
                    <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="">
                        <!-- insert name -->
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="">
                    <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$100i  </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>This letter is 9 pages long (seq. 100-108). It is typed on good quality typing paper 
                            (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). 
                            The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page.  </p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following:
                    <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
                </x>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1917-03-29">March 29, 1917</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>
                I was delighted to get your letter of <date when="1917-03-06">March 6th</date> yesterday morning, 
                for, to tell the truth, I was somewhat upset by the one of <date key="1917-02-12">February 12th</date>, which came a couple 
                of weeks ago; upset because I did not quite agree with your point of view in it, and I hate to disagree with you always, 
                and particularly when you are so far away, but this new letter, in which you have changed your mind, agrees with me exactly.   
            </p>
            <p>
                You see the point is this: – As you say, possibly <persName key="harriet_weaver">Miss Weaver</persName> would not sell 
                <title>her paper</title>, particularly as you planned to leave her as editor. In that case she would go around and tell everybody that she had been approached – 
                she might even call it “bribed” – to run her paper a certain way, and she could make a very nasty 
                story about that. Also, suppose she did consent to leave <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> out of the paper for a consideration, 
                it would give Ezra a splendid handle to beat us with, because he would know perfectly well where the 
                money came from, and he would not only be able to enlist the sympathy of the outside world and pose 
                as a martyr to capital, and I think he might be able to hurt us very seriously by leaving the impression 
                with the public at large that our success was largely due to methods of this kind. I do not believe that 
                any good is to be gained by trying to muzzle one's enemies. That is the action of weakness, and is sure 
                to come back on the perpetrator like a boomerang. The only thing for us to do is to write more and 
                better until Ezra is acknowledged by the world at large to be out of the running with us. 
                I think it only needs time for that to be a fact; besides, Ezra is so curiously constituted that if you 
                only give him rope enough, he will hang himself. If he is permitted to say pretty much what he 
                wants in <pb/>“<title key="egoist">The Egoist</title>”, he will soon disgust people so thoroughly that he will have no chance at all. 
                The only reason he has any influence still is because his remarks are so carefully edited 
                before they are allowed to appear. <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName> told me, when I was in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, that she had to 
                blue pencil all his articles so as to make them possible at all, which does not mean that Harriet is 
                getting tired of him, because I think she is peculiarly loyal, as far as he is concerned. 
                This was just a statement of fact. 
            </p>   
            <p>
                Personally, I hate “<title>The Egoist</title>”, and if it were not a seeming disloyalty to the others of the group, 
                I would discontinue my subscription at once. The thing has practically no circulation; even in <placeName key="england">England </placeName>
                it is almost unknown, outside of a small group, and to be in it or out of it makes not the slightest difference in any way. 
                I have not observed that writing in it has helped any one to a wider public, nor has it gained 
                for any of its contributors the entrance to any other magazine; therefore, I would not worry about it at all or let 
                Ezra’s being in it or out of it give you a moment’s discomfort. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I am awfully sorry you are so blue. I do not wonder at it at all, and I assure you that your being away 
                this winter has added very materially to the difficulties of writing for me. I got so much inspiration 
                out of our Sunday talks, and talking to you did so much to clear my ideas and to show me what I really thought; 
                also, I think the contact of our two minds whetted us both to make discoveries, which we should not have made alone, 
                (at least that was the case with me) and I have missed you terribly. <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> and I have often 
                said what would we not <pb/> give to see you again. I think you are quite right, however, not to make the voyage or subject <persName key="florence_emily_arbuthnot">your wife</persName> 
                to it with this submarine menace going on. Think how foolish you would feel as you sank beneath the waves to realize that you had cut
                your life short, and deprived the world of what you will write in the future, for a mere caprice!  
            </p>
            <p>
                Now that we are certainly going to enter the war, I think a great strain is off the people in this part of the country. 
                We have always been pro Ally, and to be able to be so with all our might and main is a relief. 
                I think there is going to be some difficulty between the English elements and the German elements in our population, 
                and I suspect that many friendships of long duration will be snapped, but, on the whole, I believe that 
                this will have the effect of making America more homogenous, more truly a nation, than it has been for many years – 
                since this vast tide of immigration has done so much to change the temper of her people, in fact.  
            </p>
            <p>
                I enclose a poem which I wrote a few weeks ago and put in the “<title key="transcript">Transcript</title>”, 
                as it seemed to me a daily paper was the place for it. It has been very well liked. 
                Many people, including <persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sedgwick </persName>(which is a joke), think it is one of the best things I have done. 
                Anyhow, it came from my heart. I rather wish it could be printed in an English 
                daily paper, but I have no way of knowing how that could be done. Perhaps the “<title key="observer">Observer</title>” 
                would print it. If you feel like taking it round to them, I should be very glad. 
                Of course the fact that it appeared in the <title>Boston “Transcript”</title> should be mentioned.
            </p>
            <p>
                I was perfectly wild over your poems for the <title>new Anthology</title>. <pb/>I think “Moonlight” and “Dawn” are two of the 
                most beautiful things you have done, and they fill me with envy, malice, and all uncharitableness. 
                I do not believe you need worry about whether or not you have retrograded or advanced as a poet. 
                There are always “ups and downs” periods in every poet’s creative life, and being so near the active 
                seat of war makes it very difficult to write, naturally. It will be after the war is over, as 
                a recollected experience, that you will find what you have gained. 
            </p>
            <p>
                As to our fellow Imagists, I quite agree with you that <persName key="richard_aldington">Aldington</persName> is far and 
                away the best of the lot. I have full belief in him, as a poet possibly more than as an essay writer, 
                and as to his character, it is “<foreign xml:lang="fr">sans peur et sans reproche</foreign>”. <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> 
                has always been an exceedingly conceited fellow. The amount of swelled head he has managed to acquire, with very 
                little reason therefor, is unique in my experience. <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> is faded – so faded physically, 
                that I think it affects her mentally. I do not wonder that Miss Weaver got discouraged with her; as an editor 
                she must be absolutely useless. In regard to <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>, he has always been primarily a novelist, 
                and only a poet as a side show. As such, he need not seriously concern us.  
            </p>
            <p>
                Still, I do not know whether we are wise to discontinue the <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthology</title>, 
                just at this point, or not. <placeName key="england">England</placeName> seems to be waking up to us. 
                The English are a queer people. If you hammer, hammer, hammer, bye and bye they will pay attention. 
                It always takes years before they realize that anything has anything in it. Now they have just begun to see 
                that we amount to something, and whether or not it <pb/> is wise to discontinue our collective publication at 
                the very moment that it is beginning to be noticed over there, I cannot quite make up my mind. 
                Of course the production of the individual poets has something to do with it. 
                I do not know what <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> will be able to produce in the trenches. 
                The <persName>other three</persName> seem to be hopeless, but there are always you and I. 
                Anyway, I am going to talk the matter over with <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Feris Greenslet</persName> when he 
                comes back. We do not want to lose any of the ground we have gained either by inadequate production or by 
                ceasing any publication just as soon as it is beginning to be noticed.  
            </p>
            <p>
                As far as <placeName key="usa">America</placeName> is concerned, I do not think there is any advantage in 
                keeping on the Anthology. It has done its business with the American public. The word “Imagist” and the kind of poetry for 
                which we stand is now thoroughly recognized, and I think we can do quite as well on our own hooks, as we can together, 
                but the situation is so different in England that I do not feel in a position to form an opinion at present. 
                At any rate, I shall form none without first consulting you, after I have seen Ferris Greenslet. He has not come home, and <persName key="roger_scaife">Mr. Scaife</persName> 
                does not know when he will come. Nobody knows whether he is on the water, or where he is, as announcements of sailings have been 
                discontinued in the papers, and he would not be allowed to cable his own departure. 
                There is, therefore, nothing to be done at present but to wait until his arrival. 
            </p>
            <p>
                <title>Our book</title> will be out about the middle of April. Of course I shall send you a copy as soon as it comes. 
                I sent you a copy of <title>Harriet’s Anthology</title>, which is just out a week or so ago. 
                Of course it is not exactly <pb/>the selection I would have made myself in all instances. 
                I would never have left out your “Green Symphony”, for instance, which I think is, on the whole, finer than the “Blue”; 
                still, I must admit that I think it is a very creditable volume and shows that the poetical renaissance, 
                which we claim to exist, is a fact and not a fancy.  
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be amused to hear that <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite</persName> has had a fight with 
                <persName>Edgett</persName> and has left the “Transcript”. The reviews of <title>his Anthology</title> have been uniformly bad, 
                and I am afraid his unbusinesslike methods have made them mad in there, but they did not kick him out; 
                he kicked himself out in a fit of spleen, thinking himself more valuable than he really is. 
                You will probably be glad to know of this, but I am sincerely sorry, for I believe the alternative will be 
                <persName key="nathan_dole">Nathan Haskell Dole</persName>, which will be most unfortunate. They are neither of them bright, 
                but Dole is a malicious dolt, whereas Braithwaite is merely ignorant, and he certainly is kindly. 
            </p>
            <p>
                “The Transcript” had a review of Harriet’s Anthology by <persName key="kate_buss">Kate Buss</persName>, which I will send 
                you, and you will see how inadequately this sort of work will be done on the “Transcript”, if Braithwaite doesn’t do it. 
                Also, this little notice was on the back page, not on the book page at all. Now this is one of the most important books 
                that has come out lately, and to treat it this way shows a narrow-mindedness which is a disgrace to a paper like the 
                “Transcript”. At least Braithwaite insisted upon space.   
            </p>
            <p>
                I am sorry that you felt obliged to jump on him so hard in the “<title key="poetryReview">Poetry Review</title>”, because I think it is 
                just this sort of thing which has forced him out, and in all these considerations, it is a question of what is going to be the 
                result of any action. If jumping out of the frying <pb/> pan means jumping into the fire, you had better stay in the frying pan. 
                Anyway, I send you two clippings from the “Transcript”, which speak for themselves, but which will show you that Edgett read your review. 
                I am inclined to think that this, and the many hostile reviews which his new Anthology has received, is responsible for their attitude 
                towards him. I have no brief to hold for his work, as you know, but I think Edgett and Dole, as a combination, would be very much worse. 
                Also, I am sorry for Braithwaite, and it looks to me now as though he would starve. 
                Ignorance I can forgive; malicious underhandedness, I cannot.  
            </p>
            <p>
                My trip out West was eminently successful, as far as it went. I spoke in the <orgName>Medical School</orgName> in <placeName key="stLouis">St. Louis</placeName>, 
                under the auspices of the <orgName>Washington University Alumni Association</orgName>, and the hall was so crowded that they had to put 
                in seventy-five extra chairs. The enthusiasm was tremendous. I met <persName key="orrick_johns">Orrick Johns</persName> while I was there, 
                and he assumed disposed to be friendly and enthusiastic to all of us and did not at all take the tone which <persName>Williams</persName> took in the Autumn.  
            </p>
            <p>
                <persName key="kreymborg">Kreymborg</persName> is reading his poems to the sound of a “mandalute” – whatever that may be – 
                but I do not think that sort of freak stuff is likely to work very long. Kreymborg is a clever fellow, and if he 
                did not have some admixture of the charlatan in his composition, I think he would be an interesting fellow. 
                But the older I get, the more I value sincerity, and the less I care twopence for any one who has not got it. 
                I have his advertisement somewhere; if I can find it, I will send it to you. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I also send you a copy of a review of <title key="magazineVerse">Braithwaite’s Anthology</title><pb/> by <persName>Aiken</persName> in “<title key="dial">The Dial</title>”. 
                I think this is much better than his critical work usually is. It is more restrained and less bumptious; in fact, I quite like this review. 
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be amused to learn that <persName key="maurice_browne">Maurice Browne</persName> failed the day before I arrived in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName>, 
                so I only gave my lecture for Harriet, and gave up the others, as I did not want to run the risk myself, and there had been no time 
                to advertise them properly. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I think that Harriet has run her poetry talks into the ground. Having one every Sunday by so many poets, 
                most of whom cannot read aloud at all, I think it had rather weakened people’s interest, although my hall was so 
                crowded that they slopped over into the adjoining room. I believe that conditions here are getting more normal. 
                I think that the “boom” is decidedly over. <persName key="vachel_lindsay">Vachel Lindsay</persName> tells me that nobody wants him 
                any more, and it seems to me that as people are getting more educated, they are beginning to distinguish between the really serious 
                artists and those with the scholarly intent, and the half-baked ones. Also the close proximity of war is taking people’s 
                attention off the freaks. The result may be a less apparent demand for the works of the modern poets, 
                but I believe the real ones stand more chance of being appreciated than they ever have before. 
                In other words, the conditions, I hope, will settle down more to that of England than it has been for some time. 
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be glad to hear that “<title key="swordBladesAndPoppySeed">Sword Blades</title>” has gone into a third edition, 
                so that I think we are moving.  
            </p>
            <p>
                <persName key="william_bradley">William Aspinwall Bradley</persName> is here, and spoke so pleasantly of <pb/> you the other night. 
                He said he enjoyed that evening you passed together very much, and he wishes you were here, and I echoed him with all my heart.   
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be amused to hear that they have kicked me out of the Presidency of the <orgName>Poetry Club</orgName>, and 
                <persName key="josephine_peabody">Josephine</persName> has practically come out as my avowed enemy. 
                She still tries to hide it under a cloak of friendship, but I am on guard. I shall not go to the Poetry Society again, 
                and I am thankful that I am out of it. It is getting perfectly impossible, and they are asking the Harvard boys 
                for every meeting. Bradley, who went last time, told me that those old women kow-towed to the young men in a 
                perfectly ridiculous way which made him quite sick. He says he shall not go again, either. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I am off to <placeName key="buffalo">Buffalo</placeName> tonight for a lecture tomorrow, or rather a reading, and I 
                am to go to <placeName key="brynMawr">Bryn Mawr</placeName> in May.  Also, I hope to see <persName key="wm_patterson">Mr. Patterson</persName> 
                when I am passing through <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> in May. I have had several letters from him, but very little 
                can be done that way.
            </p>
            <p>
                This is a terribly long letter, and does my best to make up for the good talk I wish we could have. 
                I do wish you would come back and settle in <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> for good, but I suppose that would be 
                too good to be true. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Please remember me most kindly to your wife, if you can be remembered to a person whom you have never seen, and believe me  
            </p>
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>,
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
