<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="../../ALLP_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                    key="john_fletcher">John Gould Fletcher</persName>, <date when="1917-02-06">06 February 1917</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="">
                    <!-- Insert editor (whoever wrote the footnotes) here -->
                </editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="as">Anthony Shoplik</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ppm">Prakruti Maniar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="">
                        <!-- insert name -->
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="">
                    <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
                </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno>https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:425963709$92i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>This letter is 6 pages long (seq. 92-97). It is typed on good quality typing paper 
                            (neither notebook paper nor Lowell’s nice cardstock, but somewhere in between). 
                            The words “John Gould Fletcher” are written in pencil across the top of the first page.  </p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following:
                    <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to keyword-ography -->
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1917-02-06">February 6, 1917</date></dateline>
                <salute>Dear <persName key="john_fletcher">J.G.F.</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>
                I have a good many letters of yours to answer and that delightful book “<title><foreign>Légendes de Noel</foreign></title>" to thank you for. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Perhaps I can do something with “<title>The Napoleon Star</title>” some day. Just now I am off on a rather different tack.  
            </p>
            <p>
                Your book is here, “<title key="underTheGuns">Under the Guns</title>”, and I like it very much indeed. 
                Some of it, of course, is already familiar; much of it is perfectly new. 
                Your “<title>White Butterflies</title>” is excellent as I told you in accepting it for the <title>Imagist Anthology</title>. 
                I like “<title>Armies</title>” very much and “<title>The Return</title>”. I think perhaps I am rather particularly attracted by 
                “<title>Street Corner</title>” and “<title>The Bayonets</title>” is very good. Your “<title>Washington</title>” is interesting, but not, 
                I think, quite so good as your “<title>Lincoln</title>”, but still very good, and your picture of cranes lifting barrels up and down is excellent. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I think if I can get <orgName key="houghton_mifflin">Houghton-Mifflin</orgName> to accept it, it would be quite easy to make an arrangement for the 
                <title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagist Anthology</title> to come out a few weeks ahead of it, thus allowing it to contain both your “Lincoln” and your “Armies”. 
                But I am a little bit doubtful about Houghton-Mifflin as <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Ferris Greenslet</persName> is not there and <persName key="roger_scaife">Scaife</persName> 
                is a bit difficult to manage. He is very anxious to see the poems, and as I am going to take them in myself on 
                Wednesday, I think I can read aloud to him certain ones and perhaps induce him to take more interest 
                than he otherwise would. At any rate you can be sure I shall do my best. 
            </p>
            <p>
                If they do accept the book, I do not think there will be <pb/> very much time for any magazines to print the poems, 
                as they undoubtedly will want to publish it this Spring, and I imagine you will prefer to have it appear as a book, 
                than to wait and have it published later when possibly its peculiar fitness is past, merely for the sake 
                of having some of these poems in the magazines. I shall not do anything about sending them around until I have Scaife’s answer. 
                If his answer is in the negative, I will do what I can about placing them, but it is not so easy, as you know. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I have just had a poem refused by <orgName key="scribner">Scribner</orgName> this week. “<title key="sevenArts">The Seven Arts</title>” is not so sympathetic to our point of 
                view as I wish it was. It has already refused my long <title>Nelson poem</title>, which I think is probably the best thing 
                I have done, an opinion which is shared by the “<title key="northAmericanReview">North American Review</title>” who have reversed 
                their policy of years against printing long poems, and accepted this one after a day’s consideration, 
                although it will take up fifteen of their pages. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I think your book stands more chance now that we are so near war ourselves. At any rate you may be quite sure that I shall do my best to get them to accept it. 
            </p>
            <p>
                If they do accept it, I will try to place the “<title>Washington</title>” with <persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sedgwick</persName>, 
                but I can be almost certain that he will refuse to touch anything that has a time limit attached to it. I will also try him 
                in case they do not take the book, but you know how little effect I have on him, and Ferris Greenslet, as I have said, 
                is on his way to <placeName key="europe">Europe</placeName>. He sailed on the <placeName key="finland">Finland</placeName> and was <pb/>due 
                to reach <placeName key="england">England</placeName> this morning, and if you have a copy of the book there, I strongly 
                advise you to show it to him and clinch the matter on this spot, regardless of anything I may have done over here. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I was delighted with that two-column review of the Imagist Poets. I think we are decidedly looking up, 
                and I have not a doubt but that some day we shall have a reputation in England. 
            </p>
            <p>
                The <title key="pallMallGazette">Pall Mall Gazette</title> has already announced that I ought to have a good many admirers now. 
                I think chiefly on account of my Yankee poems, which is the sort of thing they always like.
            </p>
            <p>
                Did you see the rather long and good article, although <persName>the man</persName> is naturally disposed to be unsympathetic 
                with my work, of “<title key="menWomenGhosts">Men, Women and Ghosts</title>” in “<title key="newAge">The New Age</title>”? All these 
                things seem to prove that we are getting on. 
            </p>
            <p>
                <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> writes me that in “<title key="observer">The Observer</title>” of the <date when="1917-01-21">21st of January</date> 
                in a long two-columned article on “<title>Cambridge History of English Literature</title>”, the writer spoke about “<persName>Mr. Shaw</persName>, <persName>Mr. Wells</persName> and the Imagist Poets” 
                as representing the modern tendency to ignore tradition. Flint says: “Of course that is silly, but the collocation is symptomatic.” 
            </p>
            <p>
                You will be interested to hear that the <orgName key="macmillan">MacMillans</orgName> have ordered a third printing of 
                “Men, Women and Ghosts” and that I have signed a contract for my new book which is to be called 
                “<title key="tendencies">Tendencies in Modern American Poetry</title>”. 
            </p>
            <p>
                My lectures were very well attended. I had between three and four hundred people at each one and they were 
                immensely enthusiastic. <pb/>
            </p>
            <p>
                I also went down and spoke at <orgName key="princeton">Princeton University</orgName>, where I had ninety boys, 
                although the literary club I spoke before only numbered fifty, and almost all the English Department. 
                <persName>The President of the Club</persName> wrote me afterwards that I had converted the Faculty to a man which, if true, is certainly starting. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I wish you had been with me in <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> for I made some interesting experiments with a 
                <persNam key="wm_patterson">Mr. Patterson</persNam>, who is in the English Department at <orgName key="columbiaUniversity">Columbia University</orgName> 
                and has just written <title key="proseRhythms">a book on Prose Rhythms</title> in which he affirmed that vers libre came under the head of prose. 
                I met him at <persName key="gertrude_atherton"><sic>Mr.</sic> Atherton</persName>’s and after some discussion he said that he would be delighted to change all of 
                his opinions if I could prove to him that he was wrong. I passed a whole afternoon with him, 
                working with his sound photographic machine and leaving records for him to work on when I was not there with the result that 
                he announced what I believe to be true; that cadence in vers libre is somewhat analogous to phrasing in music. 
                I also discovered in preparing myself beforehand for this seance that cadences are made up of time limits, 
                but the time limits do not have to be exactly the same to each cadence. In other words, they are each of the 
                same portion but there may be uneven numbers of them to a cadence. 
            </p>
            <p>
                What we shall get, I do not know, and as I had to leave <placeName key="nyc">New York</placeName> after this first meeting, 
                of course we shall not get on so fast as though I were there. I trust Mr. Patterson will make some definite discoveries in 
                time to have me incorporate them in my book which, of course, will not appear until next autumn. <pb/> 
            </p>
            <p>
                When you suggest that you would rather be published by Macmillan, you suggest what I fear is an absolute impossibility. 
                <persName key="george_brett">Mr. Brett</persName> has lost a lot of money I think on poets. 
                <persName>Masters</persName>’s two last books are not selling at all, and I do not think he is very happy on the subject of 
                American poetry. He is exceedingly nice to me, but I think his interest is largely because I write prose, too. 
                But then, this last book has sold very well. <persName key="ec_marsh">Mr. Marsh</persName> told me that before 
                Christmas with the exception of “<title>Spoon River</title>” and Tagore’s books, it was the best selling poetry that they had. 
                As I look back on it, I feel sure that Mr. Brett would not have taken me in the beginning if I had not been a sister of <persName key="percival_lowell" key="lawrence_lowell">my 
                two brothers</persName>. Also, he would not have taken me if I had not been willing to pay for my own books. 
                I think he could probably be induced to publish your new book if you had paid for it, but he does not publish a 
                great many books that way and hates to have it known that he publishes any. I do not think there is the slightest use 
                in even suggesting it to him as a venture of his own. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I am returning you the money order<!--transaction, as of encoding date, no consensus on how to tag it-->. It was very sweet of you to send it, but those books were intended as a Christmas present, 
                so I beg you will get the <orgName key="englishPostOffice">English Post Office</orgName> to refund you. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I will write you again after I have got some more from Scaife. The Imagist Anthology is going to press at once. 
            </p>
            <p>
                <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda</persName> writes me that she will let me know what you and Flint think of “<title>Lacquer Prints</title>”, 
                but I have had no word from her and I have waited two weeks. She herself has passed them. I know very well that you have passed 
                them too, because you advised me to send them. In a letter I have from <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> this morning, he does not mention the matter. <pb/>
                I doubt whether Hilda even intended to ask <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>, as he is so far away. 
                At any rate, in the present state of our shipping, I can no longer delay sending in the book or we shall 
                not be out in April. Therefore, I am taking it in as it is. 
            
            </p>
            <p>Goodbye for the moment, <persName key="john_fletcher">dear boy</persName>,; I will write again shortly. </p>
            
            <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>,
            
            <postscript>Enclosure</postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
