<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1915-07-06">6 July 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="erb">Elizabeth Boarini</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="tm">Taylor Mansheim</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$97i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is two pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written in pencil
                        at the top.</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>6 July 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-07-06">July 6, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p>We will, as I said before, make a little bow to you in the preface of the <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">next Anthology</title>.
                    But do not go on blaming <orgName key="hougton_mifflin">Houghton Mifflin</orgName> for what was none of their business. Publishers can
                not control authors’ prefaces; all publishers can do is to take or leave a book. So you must throw
                whatever blame you have on us, and remember that in mentioning <title key="poetry" level="j">“Poetry”</title> in the preface of the
                new volume, we shall do so spontaneously and <foreign xml:lang="it">con amore</foreign> and not in the least because you ask it,
                for I think your deserts great and your contention wrong.</p>
                <p>As to your review of us and bringing in <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName>, you say in this letter that you still consider
                him a member of the Imagist group and, therefore, that it was natural you should mention him;
                but you seem to forget that our title was “Some Imagist Poets,” meaning that we only
                represented a portion of the group. We never laid claim to being the whole group, but I do wish
                that in the eyes of so many of you Ezra’s shadow did not lie with <pb n="02">such sharp edges over us all.
                Greatly as I admire Ezra’s work, I think other members of the group are as deserving as he and
                as important. The slenderness of Ezra’s output alone, and it is getting slenderer and slenderer of
                late years, is sure to affect his central position. I know his theory about overproduction very well,
                and of course, in the main, he is right; but so very slight a production as his cannot fail to be
                remarked upon as showing a lack of vigour, or inspiration, or large fecundity. Praise him as
                much as you like in reviewing his own things, but do, for Heaven’s sake, let our things stand on
                their own merits without reference to Ezra.</p>
                <p>You never mentioned to me in your letter what was to me the most important thing in my
                    letter: namely, whether it is in <date when="1915-08">August</date> or <date when="1915-09">September</date> that you are going to give me my group, and
                    open the ball with them. I think it is probably <date when="1915-09">September</date>, and September will suit me perfectly
                well. May I count on that?</p>
                <p>I hope you have not been drowned out as we have. I have never seen such rain as we have
                been having here.</p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
