<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-09-16"
                    >September 16, 1914</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$24i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p> Letter consists of 3 pages of typerwriter text. Includes the words "Monroe" and "Poerty" 
                            in handwiring at top of the front page above the opener. Text at the top at of page three is crooked
                            showing a typewriter aligmnment malfunction. Misalignment is corrected by the line beginning with "permit the 
                            news stands"</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brooline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>16 September, 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <div type="letter">
            <body>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1914-09-16">Sept. 16, 1914</dateline></date>
                    <salute>My dear<persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p>I send you the teaspoonful of "<title key="nationalismInArt" level="a">Nationalism in Art</title>" which you vouchsafed me. Your 
                   printer is fast becoming the incarnation of the devil, to my mind, and only the fact that you once 
                   told me that he was a friend of yours prevents me from lifting my voice and making the welkin 
                   ring with my curses. I have corrected this proof which I now return.</p>
                <p>May I suggest that “polyethnic” is the correct spelling, not “polyethuic?” A note at the 
                   bottom of this proof says that you have already looked it over. Will it be very mean to say that 
                   your not having observed that up-side-down letter is one of the reasons why I have a predilection 
                   for doing my own proofs? That is why I wired you to send me the remaining tablespoonful.</p>
                <p>You do not mind my poking fun at you, do you? I know how beastly proof reading is, 
                   and you ought to know by this time how greatly I admire the work you are doing on this <titile key="poetry" level="j">magazine</titile>, 
                   and I send you another at 
                <pb n="02">you might like me to give you <<gap><desc>unknown text</desc></gap>.</p>
                <p>Thanks for your remarks about "<title key="littleReview" levle="j">The Little Review</title>." I am supporting it for all I am worth 
                   by contributions of poems and prose, and I agree with you that it is better than the dull 
                   professionalism, but I wish she had your power of making her magazine a first class one.</p>
                <p>I hope you have got the advertisement from <title key="macmillan">Macmillans</title> for my book. I put that in on 
                   purpose. I wish there were anything I could do to help you, for whatever happens "<title key="poetry" level="j">poetry</title>” must 
                   not stop. If I were on the editorial staff I should have a poster printed every month and put in the 
                   book shop windows and on all the news stands. I should also try to organize an artificial demand 
                   in all the cities, at the book shops, every month, for the magazine. Sometime on the plan by 
                   which you “paper” a theatre. If you like, I will undertake to get various people to ask at the <orgName key="oldCornerBookstore">Old 
                   Corner Book Store</orgName> for six copies every month of your magazine. I will try to get it done by 
                   different people so as to have it appear that each person is anxious for a number. This shall not
                   be subscriptions, but purchases.</p> 
                <p><persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sӗdgwick</persName> tells me that he does not per
                <pb n="03">mit the news stands booksellers to return 
                   any unsold copies of the "<title key="atlantic" level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>" to him. By that basis he knows every month just
                   what he has really sold. I am not sure that it would work with so special a magazine as “Poetry.” 
                   I doubt whether the demand, yet, would be big enough to justify the booksellers or news men in 
                   purchasing any numbers out right, but you will know your sales about that better than I do.</p>
                <p>I really feel awfully about "<title key="Allies" level="a">The Allies</title>," I wish you could have seen your way to 
                   publishing it on my responsibility, even against your own judgment I know it would rouse people
                   into liking it and disliking it, which is, after all, what you want in a magazine, and its originality 
                   is undoubted. But if you still think you do not want it, at least I trust you will take this "<title key="balladOfFootmen" level="a">Ballad of
                   Footmen</title>.”</p>
                <p>My book will be out next week I think. Don’t you want to review it fairly quickly, as that 
                   will help me considerably? You do not answer about <persName key="robert_frost">Frost’s</persName> <titel key="northOfBoston" level="m">book</titel>.</p>
                <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> said she had a delightful time with you.</p>
    </text>
</TEI>

