<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1915-01-19"
               > Jan. 19, 1915</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="mb"> Mary Becker</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --></persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="fo"> Felix Oke </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$62i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc> <p> This letter is one pagelong. It is typed on stationerythat says “Sevenels Brookline.” On the leftupper corner is penciled in two diagonal lines (right bottom going up to the left) “Jan 20 1915 Ans. longhand H.[cut word]</p> 
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            &personography;
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type=”sent”>
               <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
               <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
               <date>1915-01-19</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type=”received”>
               <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type=”letter”>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1915-01-19">Jan. 19, 1915.</dateline></date>
               <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
           <p>Your letter was a truly disconcerting one; I do not know what to do about it. It is not so much the presence of <placeName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</placeName> in <title key="poetry" level="j">March</title> which would make it inadvisable for you to put any of my poems in that number, but the fact that I understood you to say that <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> article on me was going in in March; and I do not think any of my poems had better appear in the same number with that article.</p> 
<p>Now as to <title key="poetry" level="j">April</title> – of course, it is a little bit late, for <persName key="ferris_greenslet">Greenslet</persName> told me yesterday that he expected to get the book out toward the end of March. But books often get delayed and if you choose to risk publishing the poems in April, I do not think there would be any objection.</p> 
<p>May I point out to you that some of these poems you have had a year, and it is a little hard to have one’s poems hung up for a year, as you know. I think it would be better to have my group in in <title key="poetry" level="j">May or June,</title> as you planned, rather than have it come out simultaneously with the <title key="anthologyDesImagistes" level="m">Anthology.</title> If you want to print the two poems that you have which are included in the Anthology in April, well and good; I should be delighted. If, on the other hand, you wish to send them back to me and have me substitute two others for them, I can do that too, although naturally that would not be so satisfactory to me.</p>
<p>Of course, I should like best to have you print them in April, and have me substitute two others to make the group as long as it was before for, say, June. If you will let me know exactly what you would like to do as soon as possible, I should be very glad. I cannot change the poems in the Anthology, as I told you, on account of their being passed upon by the others, and the book goes to press immediately.</p>
<p>I do not believe there is the slightest objection to <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> things going in with Ezra’s, or you could put her in April. I understood <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> to tell me in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> that you had accepted her flower poems, but there seems to be some mistake about that; and certainly <title key="poetry" level="a">“The Pool”</title> appearing in April, even if the book came out a week or so before, would not matter with her any more than it would with me. Anyway, please let me know as soon as possible, so that I can send you substitute poems.</p>
</p>
            <closer>Afectionately yours,</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
