<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-09-15"
                    > September 15, 1914</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$10i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p> Letter consisits of 12 pages of typer writer text (6 pages front and back). Includes the words "Monroe" and "Poerty" 
                            in handwiring at top right of the front page above the date. Each page has various ink sumudges.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>15 September, 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <div type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener><dateline><date when="1914-09-15">September 15, 1914</dateline></date>
                <salute>My dear<persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I am so glad that "<titme key="nationalismInArt">Nationalism in Art</titme>," is going into the <date when="1914-10"<title key="poetry" level="j">October number</title></date> I am perfectly
               willing to have you leave out the last paragraph of my review of <persName key= "gf_norton">Miss Norton</persName> book if you <!-- is this correct?-->
               want to. I did want to get a slap at those silly dedications, but if you think better to leave it out, 
               do as you wish. Please sign it with my initials, and please sign “Nationalism in Art” with my full 
               name.</p>
            <p>I am awfully sorry you do not get "<title key="allies" level="a">The Allies</title>.” <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> says it grows on you with 
               every reading, so I hope it will on you. I meant to typify the citizen army of the <rs key="ww1" type="theme">Allies</rs>, how it 
               was made up of all the men who follow the various arts of peace, and how they were all fighting, 
               each for different reasons, and how the sum total of every man’s desire was peace. It was written 
               at a time when the Allies were known to be marching toward the Germans in <placeName key="belgium">Belgium</placeName>, but we 
               did not know where they were, and I thought of them as a long, 
            <pb n="02">slow, crawling worm, winding 
               along the Belgian <gap><desc>word missing</desc></gap> and made up of the units I have described. I think if you will 
               read it aloud to yourself, and listen to the beat of it, you will agree with me that it has something 
               of the ruggedness and savagery of war, and that it portrays in a modern manner why we want 
               peace. I tried to avoid the usual “Lord God of Battles,” style of thing. I know it is very new, and 
               very original, but I do not think I have ever written anything which has been so much liked. All 
               our poet friends in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> were most enthusiastic about it, and a man, a great lover of poetry, to 
               whom I read it on the steamer, burst into tears hearing it. He told me that even if I had never 
               written anything but that poem, my reputation would be made. As he is a man who fights rather 
               shy of modern technique, it seemed to me that my sentiment must have “got over.” Of course, if 
               you do not like it, do not print it, but I hope you will feel better about it on a second reading, 
               because I am willing to stake a good deal on its being a good thing.</p>
            <p>(I am sitting here in sunlight, and in order to shield my eyes from the glare I have held up 
                your letter between me and the sun, with the 
            <pb n="03">result that I beg you to take two sheets of your good
               note paper, and hold them up against the bright sunshine. Such glorious colour is really a 
               delight.)</p>
            <p>I wish I could have come out to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago </placeName>with my friend, <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName>, who has been 
                abroad with me all summer, and who has just gone to Chicago to see her <persName key="lorna_amussen">daughter</persName>. I asked her to 
               telephone you and inquire about “Nationalism in Art,” as I had not heard from you when she left.</p>
            <p>I want to ask you what you think of "<title key="littleReview">The Little Review</title>." I am afraid it strikes me as 
               rather amateurish and effervescent, but the Editor <!--who is this? -->, is so fearfully enthusiastic about me, that I 
               have given her some things of mine. However, I am afraid her magazine does not stand much 
               chance of making any real place for itself.</p>
            <p>You ask me about the quarrel between <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> and the rest of us. It is not a quarrel no, it is a 
               scism [sic]. It is a very long story, and I do not know quite how to tell you all of it be letter.</p>
            <p>Do you remember Ezra was very anxious to run 
            <pb n="04"> the "<title key="mercureDeFrance">Mercure de France</title>?" He came to 
                me at once as soon as I got to <plaeName key="london">London</plaeName>, and it then transpired that he expected to become editor of 
               said “Review” with a salary. I was to guarantee all the money, and put in what I pleased, and he 
               was to run the magazine his way. We talked over the cost of expenses, and we both thought that 
               <measure type="currency" num="5,000">$5,000</measure>. A year was the least that such a magazine could be run on. As I have not $5,000. a year 
               that I can afford to put into it, I based my refusal upon that fact, and it was most unfortunate that 
               Ezra apparently did not believe it. Like many people of no incomes, Ezra does not know the 
               difference between thousands and millions, and think that any one who knows where to look for 
               next week’s dinners is a millionaire, and therefore lost his temper with me completely, although 
               he never told me why, and he accused me of being unwilling to give any money toward art. </p>
            <p>In thinking over what I could do to help the poets less fortunate than myself, and also to 
               help myself in somewhat the same manner that a Review would do, it seemed to me that to re-
               publish the "<title key="some_imagist_poets">Imagiste Anthology</title>" with the same group  
            <pb n="05">of people, year after year, for a period of 
               five years, would enable us, by constant iteration, to make some impression upon the reading 
               public. And I thought it would be interesting for people to see the work of the same group of 
               poets brought out year after year, and it is a method which the editors of "<title key="georgianPoetry">Georgian Poetry</title>" have 
               found most satisfactory. I mentioned this first to the <persName key="hilda_doolittle" key="richard_aldington">Aldingtons</persName> because I saw them first after I 
               conceived the idea. I suggested that the last little book was too monotonous and too 
               undemocratic, in that certain poets were allowed much more space than others, and I suggested
               that in the “New Anthology” we should allow approximately the same space to each poet, and 
               that we should get a publisher of reputable standing, and I offered, in case we could not get any 
               publisher to take the risk of the volume itself, to pay for its publication.</p>
            <p>The Aldingtons were exceedingly enthusiastic with the idea, as have been the other poets 
               we have asked to join us. Only Ezra was annoyed. He accused me of trying to make myself 
               editor instead of him, 
            <pb n="06">and finally tried a little blackmail by telling me that he would only join us 
               on one condition that I would obligate myself to give <measure type="currency" num="200">$200.</measure> a year to some indigent poet. I told 
               him that the $200. a year might be managed should anyone in stress of circumstances need such
               a sum, but that I absolutely refused to be intimidated into buying anything, or to buy his poems at
               the expense of my self-respect. I also told him that I would not have suggested “The Anthology” 
               had I know that he would not like the idea, and that it was intended to benefit him, quite as 
               much as the rest of us.</p>
            <p>He was perfectly furious for some time, and sent for the Aldingtons, and told them they 
               must choose between him and me, which was awful for them, as he is a very old friend, and has
               done much for them, and I was only a new friend. They behaved with the utmost honour in the 
               matter. They told Ezra it was not a question of me at all, but a question of the principle, that they 
               felt it only fair to let the poets choose their own contributions and to give each poet an equal 
               space. He then tried to bribe them, by asking them to get up an Anthology with him, and leave 
               me out. This they absolutely refused to do.</p>
            <p>We had many communications on the subject in 
            <pb n="07"> which <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence</persName>, and <perName key="ford_hueffer">Ford Maddox Heuffer</perName> 
               joined us, and we all agreed that Ezra could not expect to run us all his own 
               way forever, and that is [sic] he chose to separate himself from us, we would be obliged,
               although most regretfully, to let him.<persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> is coming in, and a few of the poets in the last
               volume who have not been producing much in the interval, have been struck out.</p>
            <p>“The New Anthology” will consist of seven of us, viz: The Aldingtons, Flint, Fletcher, 
               Ford Maddox Heuffer, D.H. Lawrence, and myself, and the harmony and kindly feeling which 
               we have all displayed toward each other, has been very marked. In order to save Ezra’s feelings 
               as much as possible, we have written a preface, in which we have explained that Ezra has left us 
               from artistic reasons, owing to a slight difference in the interpretation of the word “Imagistes”. 
               We have changed the name of the anthology, in order to let him bring out another of his own 
               under that tile, should he so desire. Our Anthology is to be “Some Imagiste Poets.”</p>
            <p>I think Ezra is regretting his action a little, for he became very nice about it toward the 
                end, and offered not to bring out his volume if it  
            <pb n="08">would interfere with ours, but we told him that
               we had no idea that it would. As a matter of fact, he has no one for his volume except himself
               and a man named <persName key="john_rodker">Rodker</persName>, unless he rakes up somebody in the interval.</p>
            <p>The truth is, Ezra has ducked and draked his reputation with his last work. His poetry is 
               too indecent to be poetical, and even when it is not indecent, it is too often merely vituperative. 
               Please do not tell anyone that I said to, but I think he is in a very bad way as far as his work is 
               concerned. <persName key="re_prothero">Mr. Prothero</persName>, the editor of "<title key="quarterly_review" levle="j">The Quarterly</title>," who has just accepted from him some of 
               the <persName key="ernest_fenollosa">Fenellosa</persName> <title keu="chineseWrittenCharacter">manuscript</title>, told me that the trouble with Ezra was that he had nothing to say, and I
               am afraid that is really true." <orgName key="blast" level="j">Blast</orgName>" will give you a good idea of what Ezra has been obliged to 
               descend to in order to keep his name before the public, and he admitted in a speech at an 
               Imagiste dinner, that it was nothing but advertising.</p>
            <p>He looks very ill, and has a bad cough, and I am afraid that he is tuberculous. It has even 
               been hinted that this may have attacked his brain. 
            <pb n="09">No one knows anything about it, and this is 
               merely surmise. The fact remains that where his work is concerned he is failing every day, and 
               except for "<title key="poetry">Poetry</title>" and "<title key="egoist">The Egoist</title>" there are no magazines that will take his poetry, if I except 
                an occasional contribution to "<title key="poetryDrama">Poetry and Drama,</title> and he has only sold two prose articles this 
               year. One, which was mostly Fenellosa, appeared in the “Quarterly,’ and an article on 
               "<rs key="vorticism" type="theme"> Vorticism </rs>" in the current "<orgName key="fortnightly">Fortnightly</orgName>." He had a chance in his articles on French authors in 
               "<title key="newAge"The New Age</title>," a year ago, but the work was so superficial and slapdash that it did him harm 
               rather than good.</p>
            <p>Ezra always thought of life as a grand game of bluff. He never has learned the wisdom of 
                <persName key="abraham_lincoln">Lincoln’s</persName> famous adage about “Not being able to fool all the people all the time.” Advertising is 
               all very well, but one must have some goods to deliver, and the goods must be up to the 
               advertising of them. Now that Ezra has ceased to be a youthful phenomenon he must take his 
               place in the steady march by which young men of talent gain to a real reputation, and he finds 
               himself falling back at every step,   
            <pb n="10">and this naturally makes him exceedingly bitter. He is very 
               brilliant, he does not work though, and his work lacks the quality of soul, which, I am more and 
               more fain to believe, no great work can ever be without. At any rate, that is the situation about 
               the Imagistes. It is not a quarrel, in one sense it never was. I have spared no efforts to keep them
               all on good terms with each other, even offering to leave “The Anthology” myself, if it would 
               heal the breach. Ezra and his wife dined with me a few days before I left, and we had a very 
               pleasant and perfectly amicable evening, and it would not surprise me if he came into one of our 
               Anthologies later on, but of course, I have not suggested this possibility to him.</p>
            <p>The great thing which my summer has done for me is bringing me the intimacy of the 
               Aldingtons. They are a perfectly charming young couple, and I think <persName key="hilda_doolittle">Hilda’s</persName> last work an 
               advance on her other, don’t you? I am very glad indeed that you accepted the poems she sent. 
               You, with the exception of "<title key="seaIris" level="a:">Sea Iris</title>" in returning which I cannot help thinking you made a 
                mistake. I enclose a subscription blank for my old governess in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, who is </pb>  
            <pb n="11"> very much interested in seeing your book<!-- ? -->.</p>
            <p>Don’t be discouraged that the subscriptions are not increasing. A magazine devoted to 
               poetry can hardly expect to increase its subscription list hand over fist. Poetry is looking up, but I 
               do not suppose it will ever be really popular, and I think you are doing a great deal to change 
               public opinion and raise the standard in this country.</p>
            <p>I wish you could get a larger book stall. It is quite impossible to buy “Poetry” at any book 
               shop or stall, either here or in England. If they have any copies, they are sure to be left overs of 
               other months, and the only place where you can be sure of buying a current number is the <orgName key="poetryBookshop">Poetry 
               Bookshop </orgName> in London. Cannot you make some arrangement with the International News 
               Company<!-- should this be tagged? --> to carry it on their railway book stalls, and would it not be a good method to have 
               some prose articles merely as a selling device?</p>
            <p>I shall be in <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> before many months are over, I hope, and shall try to bring you 
                some poems to add to the four you took in <date when="1914-05">May</date>, and make a
            <pb n="12">group of my poems somewhere near spring.</p>
            <p>By the way, have you seen that "<title key="coalPicker"level="a">The Coal Picker</title>" has been copied in various 
               newspapers, both East and West? I am afraid you will be awfully lonely when your little home is 
               broken up, but you will be so busy, and that must be some satisfaction. Is there any truth in the 
               fact which Ezra told me, that you are no longer Art Editor of "<orgName key="chicagoTribue">The Tribune</orgName>?" Do you want me to 
               review <persName key="robert_frost">Frost’s </persName>book, the author of <titel key="northOfBoston">Boston</titel>, for you?</p>
            <closer>Very sincerely yours,</closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
