<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-09-10"
                    >September 10, 1914 </date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$5i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p> Letter consists of four paages of typewriter text. Second page is blank, but cuould be the back of the first page.
                            Fist page has no typed letter head, but includes the words "Monroe" and "Poerty" in handwiring at top right of the page
                            above the date. The final page includes the letterhead "Amy Lowell, Heath Street, Brookline Mass.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>10 September 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><date when="1914-09-10">September 10, 1914</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear<persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I enclose a check for <measure type="currency" num="60">$60</measure>. to pay for my advertisement in your <title key="poetry" level="j">magazine</title>. It brought me
               one answer which did not materialize, so that it hardly seems worth while to pursue advertising.
               I wish you would tell me if you ever received that paper on " <title key="nationalismInArt" level="a">Internationalism in Art</title>"
               which I sent you the last week in <date when="1914-06">June</date>. I not only sent it, but telegraphed, and wrote to you from
               <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, asking you if it had ever been received. I therefore ought at least to know whether you
               received the manuscript, or whether it was lost in the mails. Truly, Harriet, this is a bit
               unbusinesslike, for whether you received the manuscript or not, it seems very possible that you
               received either my telegram from <placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName> before I sailed, or my letter from <placeName key="london">London</placeName> in regard
               to it, and I do think you should have answered. </p>
            <p>It is a little discouraging to wait so long before you publish my prose things. You ask me to <gap><desc>Unknown number of lines missing</desc></gap>
                    <!-- <pb n="02"> [blank second page (possibly just the back of the first page). Missing line[s?] at the top of 
               the third page] --> </p>
            <pb n="03"><p>of eight months before they get into print. The point of the article was to that it come out
               fairly near to <persnName key="louis_untermeyer">Untermeyer’s</persnName> and <persName key="james_alvord">Alvord’s</persName> articles on the same subject in "<title key="poetryDrama">Poetry and Drama</title>,”
               and so furnish an answer and refutation to their premises. But you wait, and publish it when the
               people have forgotten all about the other things, and circumstances have entirely changed.
               I do not mean to find fault, but of course after waiting two months for a reply about the
               article, I am naturally a little upset. Also, do you not think in your advertisement in the
               <date when="1914-09">Septmber</date> number of "<title key="littelReview" level="j">The Little Review</title>" you might have included my "<title key="forsaken">Forsaken</title>" in the
               number of poems in the caption, “have you read?” It seems to me that it was worthy of being in
               included, considering that you included poems by <persName key="carl_sandburg">Sandburg</persName> and <persName key="orrick_johns">Johns</persName>. However that may be, a
               child may gird at its mother, and it does not make any difference in long run, and "<title key="poaetry" level="j"> Poetry</title>" is to a
               certain extent my mother, and I feel great loyalty and affection for it, and, it is needless to say, to
               you. I </p>
            <pb n="04"><p>I enclose a poem I wrote on the war, while I was in London. I do not include it in the
               war contest poems, because I know that it has no chance whatever of getting a prize, as no one 
               else is writing in this metre in English, I am quite certain that you would know instantly who
               wrote it, and I feel certain that your vaunted Democracy is not so democratic as to give me a
               prize if you thought I did not need it, when other more deserving people would lose thereby. This
               is not democracy, but it is what most people call democracy, and I fearit is your kind. Therefore
               I spare you the horrid necessity of a choice.</p>
            <p>This poem has been received enthusiastically by everyone to whom I heard read it, both
               in England and since I came home. I know it to be a good thing. I wish you would publish it in
               your November number with the other war poems, appending a note that the poem was not
               offered as one of the competing poems for the war prize.</p>
            <p>I did not pay the sums you asked me to, to <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra Pound</persName>, and to <persName key="james_stephens">James Stephens</persName>. James
               Stephens 
            <pb n="05"> was in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, and it was quite impossible to reach him, as difficult as it would be for
               you, and everybody advised me against the attempt of trying to get money over to <placeName key="france">France</placeName> from
               England. I told Ezra of your letter, and wished to give him the money at once, but he said he had
               already written to you to send it to him by Postal Order, and he was afraid there might be some
               mistake and he might be paid twice, so he preferred to wait until your remittance reached him. I
               am sorry not to have been of more use to you in this matter.</p>
            <p>I am afraid the war will do a great deal of harm to poetry on the other side of the Ocean.
               A great many of the men there are planning to emigrate to <placeName key="america">America</placeName> when the war is over.
               Several of the periodicals there have stopped. Now, if ever, is emphatically your chance.</p>
            <p>Please let me hear from you as soon as possible. about the article. By the way, have you
                heard from Richard Aldington about the new "<title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">Imagistes Anthology</title>" which we are bringing out,
               and which we are to bring out every year for five years? Ezra has left us, or we have left him for
               the moment. All the rest of us are in it, and it is only Ezra’s intense desire to always run
               everything entirely</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

