<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1915-05-03">5 May 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp">Julia Paella</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="tm">Taylor Mansheim</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$83i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is two pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written in pencil
                        at the top.</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>5 May 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-05-03">May 3, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>My dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p>Your letter has come and, although I think <measure type="currency" num="70">seventy dollars</measure> rather little for the number of
                    poems you have, I suppose I must accede to it. But I should like to make a protest, not only on
                    my own account but on account of your other contributors, which is that you should pay your
                    regular rate per page, whatever that may be, no matter how many pages a person is given. What
                    is the advantage for any poet to have a number of poems, if he loses money by it? Most of these
                    young poets need every penny they can get, and they get very little. You accept their poems and
                    hold them up sometimes for over a year, making it impossible for them to send them anywhere
                    else; and yet you do not pay them until the poems are published. I do think that is a great
                    mistake. As far as I am concerned, you get it back in the advertising, for I always insist upon the
                    publishers advertising everything in your pages. We have got our <title key="newPoetrySeries" level="s">New Poetry Series</title> in your
                    magazine <pb n="02">now, and I shall make <orgName key="macmillan">Macmillan</orgName> put in <title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">“Six French Poets”</title> <date when="1915">this Autumn</date>. I do think it
                    is a mistake, Harriet, and I wish you would consider it, that is all. I repeat I think your pro rata
                    page should be pro rata, no matter how many pages one person has.</p>
                 <p>Couldn’t you make it <date when="1915-08">August</date>, instead of <date when="1915-09">September</date>? September seems awfully far away,
                     but if you cannot make it August, I will accept September, and be thankful.</p>
                 <p>By the way, I have read <title key="spoonRiver">“Spoon River”</title> from cover to cover. I quite agree with you, it is
                    one of the most remarkable books ever published in this country. As a novel, it is, as far as I
                    know, unsurpassed. I shall be very interested to see what <persName key="el_masters">Mr. Masters</persName> will attempt next. His
                    knowledge of humanity is extraordinarily wide and clear, and these little, headed-up poems give
                    an impression of reality which I do not remember ever having felt so vividly before.</p>
                 <p>I am sorry <placeName key="mclurg">McClurg</placeName> would only take twelve copies. I don’t see why he cares how many
                    he takes, so long as he only pays for what he sells. Do stir people up to buy some copies, if you
                    can.</p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>