<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe"> Harriet Monroe </persName>, <date when="1916-02-03"
                    >February 02 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp"> Julia Paella </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$130i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p>This letter is two pages long. On the first page, “Poetry (Monroe)” is written in pencil 
                            at the top. The second page has, typed, H.M. with the corresponding page number in the top 
                            left corner, and the date (2/3/16) in the top right corner. On both pages, 
                            there is faint text on the page at the top. The text is large and mirrored on the opposite 
                            side of the page, It reads, “BERKSHIRE LINEN”</p> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>
                 
                </p>  
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><!-- Doesn't said a place --></settlement>
                    <date> February 03 1916</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1916-02-03">February 03, 1916</date>.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet:</persName></salute></opener>
                <p> I feel that I owe you an apology for suspecting you of deleting <persName key="agnes_lee">Mrs. Freer&apos;s</persName> article of 
                    complimentary remarks about me. Naturally, after Mrs. Freer&apos;s perfectly clear message, I supposed that you had left out a great 
                    deal that was important. As a matter of fact, on reading through her manuscript, which came this morning, I find that you only left out things 
                    which could in no way add to the value of the review, and which, had I been editing the manuscript, I should have left out myself. Mrs. 
                    Freer is evidently unused to criticism, as her review is merely a recapitulation of what could be found in the book; but since she wrote 
                    it that way, I do not see what else you could do. I was very grateful to you for putting it in so promptly, and I am returning it at once. 
                    I trust that you will understand that, had it not been for Mrs. Freer&apos;s sending me so clear and strong a message, I should never have 
                    suspected you of leaving anything important out of the review. I imagine that what happened was that Mrs. Freer did not care very much for 
                    her own review when she saw it in print, and probably did not quite remember what the original was, but imagined it would have been better 
                    than what was printed. I am very glad you send it to me.</p>
                <p> I also want to thank you very much for saying that you will change my list of poems in the Anthology 
                <pb="n2">
                    to suit me. I really cannot tell 
                    you how glad <del rend="strikethrough">I glad</del> I shall be if you change your mind in regard to &quot;polyphonic prose&quot; and 
                    allow <title key="leadSoldiers" level="a">&quot;Lead Soldiers&quot;</title> to appear in the Anthology. It would a very great kindness to 
                    me if you could see your way to doing this.</p>
                <p> You do not mention <title key="turnpike">&quot;Off the Turnpike,&quot;</title> but I trust that, as silence gives consent, it means that you are 
                    going to accept it. </p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>



