<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe"> Harriet Monroe </persName>, <date when="1915-10-04"
                    >October 04 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp"> Julia Paella </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$112i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p>This letter is three pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written in pencil at the top. 
                        The pages are rough on the edges as if torn out of a notebook. The third page also has, typed, H.M. in the top left corner, 
                        and the date (10/4/15) in the top right corner, as well as a -2- in the middle. There are also two black dots on each page that 
                        look like they could be from a hole punch.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>    <!--theme poetry prizes; Helen Haire Levenson Prize--></p>  
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><!-- Doesn't said a place --></settlement>
                    <date>October 04 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-10-04">October 04, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet:</persName></salute></opener>
                <p>Your letter of <date when="1915-10-01">October 1st</date> must have crossed with mine saying that I was withdrawing from the Levenson Prize. 
                    I do not want to withdraw a bit, but I know there is no hope of your giving me the prize; and I think it would be very foolish for me to get it, 
                    only I confess I should like the prestige sometime. I do not see quite how that can become got if I keep withdrawing. However, I do withdraw, of 
                    course; and, as I said in my last letter, I should be very glad if you would give me an honorable mention for something if you feel like doing so.</p>
                <p>As to your suggestion that I review the book on <persName key="maurice_maeterlinck">Maurice Maeterlinck</persName>, 
                    I am afraid I must refuse since you want it for the December number. I have had to work so fearfully hard over 
                    this <title key="sixFrenchPoets">&quote;Six French Poets&quote;</title> of mine, and the translations of the poems cited in the text have kept me at it
                    so continuously all <date when="1915">summer</date>, that I have not been able to do as much creative work as I should like. I have a lot of 
                    ideas all piled up in my head which only lack 
                <pb="n2">
                    the time for me to give expression to, and I think I must give them a chance. I have still another two or three weeks&apos; work 
                    on the &quote;French Poets,&quote; finishing up the proof reading; and after that I mean to take a month’s complete 
                    vacation and go off somewhere for a little rest. I have been almost steadily on the job since I returned from <placeName key="europe">Europe</placeName> 
                    a <date when="1914">year ago</date>, so I am afraid I could not promise to do your book before <date when="1915-12">December;</date> 
                    and as you want it at once, I rather think I had better refuse outright. I am awfully sorry that I should  fail you at this juncture and, if you care to put 
                    it off and punish it in one of the early Spring numbers, I could probably do it for you; but I doubt  whether you would find it that convenient. </p>
                <p>You have been awfully good to <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>. He has written me of all you  have done for him. Do not reproach 
                    yourself for anything left undone, for I am sure there has been nothing. His lack of <foreign xml:lang="fr"><u>savoir faire</u></foreign> often leads 
                    him into <foreign xml:lang="fr"><u>brusqueries</u></foreign> which make him seem less contented that he really is; and I know that he is 
                    really very grateful for your kindness.</p>
                <p> <add place="bottom">My work on &quote;ix French Poets&quote; has delayed </add>
                <pb="n3"> 
                    my article on <title key="poetry" level= "j">your magazine;</title> but you may be sure that I shall write it as soon as
                    I can after my vacation and try to force it on <title key="newRepublic" level="j">“The New Republic.”</title></p>
                
            
                <closer>Very sincerely yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
