<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-09-17"
                    >September 17, 1914 </date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="xeh">Xiamara Hohman</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$27i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p>Letter consists of 3 pages of typerwriter text. Includes the words "Monroe" and "Poerty" 
                           in handwiring at top of the front page above the opener. Date line appears twice at the top at of the first
                           page as a likely result of a typewriter malfunction.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>17 September, 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><date when="1914-09-17">September 17, 1914</dateline></date>
                    <salute>My Dear<persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
            <p>I am afraid you think me perfectly horrid not to take <persName kwy="henry_fuller">Mr. Fuller’s</persName> suggestions, but you tell 
               me I am conceited enough to think I am as good an authority on English Grammar as any one in 
               the world. One writer cannot know what flavour the other writers [sic] words ought to have. To 
               use “one another” and “thus far” would immediately turn the sentences into an academic and 
               preceiux form of language, the stilted kind which we are all trying very hard to get away from. 
               Mr. Fuller would never make an error of taste in his own writings, which are most dignified and 
               beautiful and in excellent proportion, but I do not admit that he, or any one else, is a good critic 
               of other people’s prose.</p>
            <p>You could have far more justly pounced upon the word “apter” which I think does not 
               exist. I, myself, think the secret of good writing is to be willing to do things of that kind when the 
               flavour requires it. At any rate, it is a liberty which I shall always take, even if I am, although, I 
               trust, sparingly, condemned for it.</p>
            <p><persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> writes me that she had a very pleasant talk with you over the telephone, and 
               that you asked her to come and see you. I hope that that will come off, for I know you would like 
               each other very much.</p> 
            <p>Please forgive my obstinacy, but after one has passed the nursery stage, one has a certain 
               self reliance, and I am not of the kind that cares a button for authority.</p>
            <p>I may be annoying as a contributor, but you must admit I am splendid at getting you 
               subscriptions.</p>
                <closer>Always very sincerely,</closer>     
            <postscript>  
                <p><lable>P.S.</lable> For your greater comfort let me say that I did not mean “one another,” but “each the other,” 
               namely that <gap><desc>[illegible text]</desc></gap> inhibits the one with which it has to do, which would of course be the 
               chemical action from which the simile is taken, not that each characteristic eliminates all the rest.</p> 
               <p><lable>P.P.S.</lable> I do wish you had not been afraid to print that review of mine on <persName key="charles_Towne">Charles Hanson Towne’s</persName> 
                book<!-- do we know what book this is? -->. One of <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite’s</persName> minions has just given him a great send-off in the <title key="transcript" level="j">Transcript</title>, and it 
               does seem a shame that no dissenting voice should be heard.</p>    
            </postscript>             
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

