<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1915-07-29">29 July 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="erb">Elizabeth Boarini</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="tm">Taylor Mansheim</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$103i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is three pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written in pencil
                        at the top.</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>29 July 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-07-29">July 29, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
                I am going to ask you a great favour. I have succeeded in selling <title key="imagesOldAndNew">a book</title> of <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard’s</persName> to a
                <orgName key="fourSeas">little firm</orgName> here in <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName>, <persName key="edmund_brown">Brown</persName>, to wit, who wishes to bring it out as one of a series they are
                publishing. They expect to issue the volume in <date when="1915-11">November</date>, but the book contains a poem —
                which I believe you have accepted, but have not yet published — called <title key="imagesPoem">“Images.”</title> Will you be
                an angel and print it between now and November, so that I can conclude the sale of the volume
                with Brown?
                Richard is awfully poor, as you know, and I would be a great thing for him to have a
                volume printed, and he naturally will not wish a poem of his which he thinks highly, not to be
                printed in it. He simply sent me the manuscript of the book, telling me who owned what poems
                and asking me if I could get it accepted by an American publisher. That is why I am doing the
                business for him. I shall be awfully obliged to you if you will do this for me, and of course I can
                promise <pb n="02">you that the usual acknowledgement will appear.
                Richard writes me that he has asked you to write a series of articles on American poetry
                for <title key="egoist" level="j">“The Egoist.”</title> I do hope you will do it, as far too little is known about American work on the
                other side of the ocean.
                To my mind, <title key="newRepublic" level="j">“The New Republic”</title> gets duller and duller. Perhaps that might be
                paraphrased into more and more political and less and less anything else. They have just
                accepted <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher’s</persName> <title key="clipperShips">“Clipper Ships;”</title> but if they keep it as long as they have two poems of mine
                which have not yet appeared, it won’t do him much good, poor boy!
                By the way, <title key="theCentury">“The Century”</title> has just accepted a polyphonic poem of mine. It amuses me
                to think of anything so radical in so conservative a stronghold. Yes, Harriet, there is no doubt
                about it: you have had an immense effect upon the other magazines in this country, let alone the
                effect you have had upon the writers themselves. I am laying all this up to hurl at the head of the
                public in my article on you.
                I hope you are not as hot as I am. Thank Goodness, I am going to the country this week. <pb n="03">I
                have been kept here by <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> not being very well. But now she is going West, and I am
                going to <placeName key="dublinNewHampshire">Dublin</placeName>. My address there is simply: Dublin, New Hampshire.
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
