<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="hariet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-07-20"
                    >July 20, 1914</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI"> <!-- this is a PDF --> </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> <!-- Insert physical description here, including description of letterhead, header addresses, etc. --> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="london">London</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>20 July, 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
            <opener><dateline><date when="1914-07-20">July 20, 1914</dateline></date>
                <salute>Dear<persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>,</salute></opener>
            <p>I wonder whether you ever got my article on "<title key="nationalismInArt" level="a">Nationalism in Art,</title>" which I sent you just 
               before I sailed, on the <date when= "1914-06-23">23rd of June</date>. I also wired you from home, before I started, to know if you
               had got it, but you never answered, and a letter from <persName key="ac_henderson">Mrs. Henderson</persName>, which I got about a week
               ago, doesn’t mention it. A change in secretaries may have made a leakage somewhere, for my
               old one ended by forgetting everything.</p>
            <p>If you have not go it I wish you would wire <persName key="alice_watts">Miss Alice Watts</persName>, 166 Coolidge Street,
               <placeName key="brookline">brookline, Mass</placeName>. To send it to you at once. She is my present secretary and seems really
               sensible.</p>
            <p>I got the <date when= "1914-06">July</date> "<title key="poetry" level="j">Poetry</title>" today, (how interesting <persName key="vachel_lindsay">Lindsay’s</persName> things are!) and was sorry to see
               that "<title key="coalPicker" level="a">The Coal Picker</title>" was not in it, for I thought you said you would put it in immediately to
               unshock all those people who did not like "<title key="forsaken" level="a">The Forsaken</title>." And, as Lindsay appeared in the 
               <date when="1914-04">April number</date> with me, and again this one, it does not seem to be too soon. Perhaps, however, you
               will be so good as to put it into <date when="1914-08">August</date>. I also enclose the review of <persName key="gf_norton"></persName>"<title key="sisterWind" level="a">The Sister of the Wind</title>"
               which I promised you.</p>
            <p>I have a lot to say to you about the situation here, but it is a little difficult to write it. I
               don’t want to tell tales out of school, but it does seem as though you ought to know how things
               stand. I find our little group more of less disintegrated and broken up. Violent jealousy has
               broken out, whether because of the “<title key="anthologyDesImagistes" level="m">Imagiste Anthology</title>” and its reviews, I cannot say. Poor old
               <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> has got himself into a most silly movement of which "<title key="blast" level="a">Blast</title>" is the organ. I will send you a
               copy tomorrow. He is annoyed with me because I will not finance a review for him to run. My
               feeling is that his slanging of the public, and his indecent poems poems, have flattened out his
               reputation, even <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer</persName> tells me that Ezra is very unhappy because he is so unsuccessful. The
               opinion of everyone is that he has nothing more to say. This would tally with your remarks to
               me about the last batch of his poems. Poor old Ezra, I am awfully sorry for him, but he is like a
               prickly pear to touch. My impression is that Hueffer is also in a gloomy way. I went to a lecture
               which he gave at which there were just nine people present, counting out his wife, the man who
               introduced him, and myself (who had to go because I dined with them.) He is on the verge of
               nervous prostration, poor fellow. <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>, they tell me, is writig very badly now, and that
               corroborates what you told me about the last batch of things he sent you. The <persName key="richard_aldington""hilda_doolittle">Aldingtons</persName> seem
               to be the sanest and best working of the set. Except <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName>, who is doing some good work. The
               craze for advertisement has swept Ezra off his feet. His Imagiste movment is petering out
               because of the lack of vigor in his poets, and the complete indifference of the publick. Onely
               one hundreds copies of the “Imagiste“ anthology have been sold in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>! Much less than in
               <placeName key="usa">America</placeName>. It seems now as though it were simply a flair of young men with nothing more in
               them. Barring Fletcher who still promises, and possibly the Aldingtons, she in her beautiful,
               delicate tenuousness, and he rather as a good, adequate prose writer, I think there does not
               seem to much to [sic]. The jealousy and the mercenary point of view, disgust me, rather. And I am
               thankful that I live in America where the poets seem to be generous and large minded, even if
               not up to this group technically. With Ezra it is the poisonof non-success brought about largely
               by his own foolish methods, which have done it. Another funny thing is that the reviews here
               are in such a bad way. That is the two which pretend to publish modern poetry, "<title key="egoist" level="j">The Egoist</title>"
               and "<title key="poetryDrama" level="j">Poetry and Drama</title>." “The Egoist” is not sold at the newsstands of the largest news agency
               on account of its articles on sex, and “Poetry and Drama” is trying to get more funds, as it is 
               practically bankrupt. I must say the outlook of the poor poets is not bright and there is no such
               large and interested a public for poetry here as there is in America. Within a decade, I feel sure
               that America will have all the best poets writing in English.</p>
            <p>I have had good luck, for “Poetry and Drama” have taken four of my poems and “The
               Egoist” eight.</p>
            <p>I am writing to my cousin, <persname key="fred_lowell">Fred Lowell</persname>, to send you that other hundred on the first of
               August. And please, dear lady, put that paper on “Nationalism” and “The Coal Picker” in as soon
               as possible.</p>
                <closer>Very sincerely,</closer>     
                    <signed><persName key="Amy Lowell">Amy Lowell</persName></signed>
           <postscript>
                <p>Of course this letter is private. I have met <persName key="allen_upward">Allen Upward</persName> and his is quite unlike what one would
                    suppose. I think he has a screw loose about his island</p></postscript>   
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

