<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe"> Harriet Monroe </persName>, <date when="1915-12-23"
                    >December 23 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp"> Julia Paella </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$118i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> <p>This letter is two pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written
                        in pencil at the top. The second page also has, typed, H.M. in the top left corner, and the date (12/23/15) 
                        in the top right corner.</p> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>
                    <!--theme medical ("the nose")-->
                </p>  
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><!-- Doesn't said a place --></settlement>
                    <date>Dicember 23 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-12-23">December 23, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet:</persName></salute></opener>
                <p> Thank you very much for your nice letter. I am very glad indeed that <persName key="agnes_lee">Mrs. Freer</persName> is doing my book. 
                    I know very well what an excellent person she is for the task.</p>
                <p> I had a letter from <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName>  <date when="1915-12-22">yesterday</date>, in which he told me that he had sent you 
                    another copy of the review of <title key="sixFrenchPoets" level="m">&quote;Six French Poets&quote;</title> which he had enclosed to me, and had asked you, 
                    if you could not use it, to send it on to some other paper. It was a funny coincidence that <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> 
                    had written to me that <date when="1915-12-22">very morning</date>, saying that she was at a loss to get anybody who could review it to her satisfaction, 
                    and could I suggest anyone to her. As I knew you had already arranged for Mrs. Freer, and that the review was doubtless written, if not printed, 
                    I wired you this morning, and enclosed Flint&apos;s review to Margaret Anderson this afternoon. I trust that my actions will meet with your approval.</p>
                <p>I do want to get on to that Poetry supper. I don&apos;t know when I wanted to do anything so much. I have never ceased to regret that I was not at the 
                    last one, and your suggestion that I can make a speech is almost irresistible. But I do not think there is the slightest prospect that I shall 
                    be well enough to travel out to you by the 23rd. I am going to see the doctor again next week, and if there is any chance that he thinks the nose 
                    can wait a while, I will let you know; but I have been having a very bad time with it for some years, and now it seems to have culminated in a condition 
                <pb="n2">
                    closely akin to asphyxiation, and I guess the sooner it is attended to the better. It is awfully good of you to want me, and I did hope 
                    to get to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> in <date when="1916-01">January,</date> but now it looks to me as 
                    if <date when="1916-03">March</date> were a more likely time. However, if I can leave it open, that would at least give me the feeling that 
                    there was hope.</p>
                <p> I have written a defence of you in answer to <persName key="conrad_aiken">Aiken&apos;s</persName> article in 
                    the <title key="poetryJournal" level="j">&quote;Poetry Journal&quote;</title> in the same paper. As Aiken published his abuse there, it 
                    seems the proper place to reply to him. I trust you will like it. It is supposed to appear in the next number, but as the numbers are generally
                    three months late, there seems no reason to suppose you will see it before Spring, or the public either for that matter, when they will have 
                    forgotten all about Aiken. But it cannot be helped.</p>
                <p>A very Merry Christmas to you, Harriet, and the best of New Years!</p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
