<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe"> Harriet Monroe </persName>, <date when="1916-01-26"
                    >January 26 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp"> Julia Paella </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$118i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p>This letter is three pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry (Monroe)” are written
                            in pencil at the top. The second and third pages also have, typed, H.M. with the corresponding 
                            page number in the top left corner, and the date (1/26/16) in the top right corner. On the last page, 
                            there is faint text on the page near the bottom. The text is large and mirrored on the opposite 
                            side of the page, perhaps written on the other side? It reads, “BERKSHIRE LINEN U.S.A.”</p> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>
                    <!--theme Poetry dinner, Other's anthology boycott-->
                </p>  
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement>></settlement>
                    <date> January 26 1916</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1916-01-26">January 26, 1916</date>.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet:</persName></salute></opener>
                <p> I cannot tell you how miserable I was, not being able to go out to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago.</placeName> 
                    <persName key="helen_lathrop">Mrs. Lathrop&aphos;s</persName> very kind invitation came too late for me to avail myself of it. I am enclosing 
                    a letter, which I should be very much obliged to you if you would give her.</p>
                <p> <persName key="ada_russell">Mrs. Russell</persName> writes that you asked her to the dinner, and I am in hopes that she 
                    will tell me all about it.I am enclosing my cheque for <measure type="currency" num="2.50">$2.50</measure> for her plate, 
                    and only regret that it was not more and that I did not have a plate, too. I wrote Mrs. Russell a long screed of questions 
                    to ask you, because you have been so busy lately, you Bad Thing, you have not answered anything I have been asking, and I 
                    naturally am extremely anxious to know how you are going to represent me in your Anthology. I count a good deal on that 
                    Anthology. I think it is going to be a good thing. <persName key="john_fletcher">Fletcher</persName> and I have removed 
                    ourselves from the <title key="othersAnthology" level="m">&quote;Others&quote; Anthology,</title> as we did not like their 
                    methods, and we did not want people to think they were Imagists. I think <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName>
                    has also taken himself out of it. I do not believe it stands any show to speak of, except as a freak. But that makes your 
                    Anthology all the more important to the poets and the public, for this will show the  sincere work that is being done, 
                    rather than the more shoddy kind.</p>
                <p>I imagine you are only going to put into it those poems which have appeared in <title key="poetry" level="j">“Poetry.”</title>
                    I really do  want very much to know which of mine you have chosen. </p>
                <pb="n2">
                <p> I also asked Mrs. Russell to see you and <persName key="mary_aldis">Mrs. Aldis</persName>, and find out if there was 
                    any chance of my giving any talk or talks in Chicago later in <date when="1916">the year</date>, 
                    say in <date when="1916-03">March</date> or <date when="1916-04">April.</date> I have been giving a great many lectures 
                    here and several in <placeName key="nyc">New York,</placeName> and they have been very successful, and I am extremely 
                    anxious to widen  my scope and include Chicago. Chicago has always been so nice to me that I do not see why they should 
                    not greet my talks as well as New York and <placeName key="boston">Boston</placeName> have.  I suppose Mrs. Russell will 
                    have seen you by this time, and will have told you in what the lectures consist. Some of them are talks 
                    about the &quot;new poetry&quote; with illustrations. In others cases, I have simply been asked to read my own poems. But I 
                    won&apos;t go into detail now, until I see what Mrs. Russell has said to you. </p>   
                <p> Meanwhile, here is the poem that I intended to read at your dinner. It is another one of that same series of 
                    which <title key="reaping" level="a">&quote;Reaping,&quote;</title> which you and 
                    <persName key="el_masters">Mr. Masters</persName> like so much, was the first. I want you to publish it. Personally, 
                    I think it is the best of that Yankee lot. It is fairly long, I know, but no longer than 
                    <persName key="ford_hueffer">Hueffer&apos;s</persName> <title key="heaven" level="a">&quote;Heaven,&quote;</title> and 
                    I think you ought to have it. You always print me two or three times a year, and this, it seems to me, would make a nice 
                    Spring contribution. It will appear in my next volume, which is coming out <date when="1916">next Autumn</date>, so you 
                    have quite a little leeway before you need publish it; but of course, as I have not bee in  your magazine since <date when="1915-09">last September,</date> 
                    I would kind of like to be in about <date when="1916-04">April</date>, if you can manage it.</p>
                    <p>My defense of you appears in next month&apos;s <title key="poetryJournal" level="j">&quote;Poetry Journal,&quote;</title> and 
                <pb="n3">   
                   I will send you a copy.</p>
                <p> You have not answered me about <persName key="fs_flint">Flint&apos;s</persName> poems, but I suppose you are printing them 
                    that we can use them in the Anthology to be published in April. Do be a Good Girl, and answer this sometime:</p>
                <p>I trust your dinner was a great success, and if you will only give another next year, I will take up my abode in Chicago 
                    weeks previously, in order to be there. </p>
                    
                
                <closer>Affectionately,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>

