<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1913-07-28"
                    >July 28, 1913</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rb">Rayne Broach</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref="vod">Tori O'Dea</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI"> <!-- this is a PDF --> </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> <!-- Insert physical description here, including description of letterhead, header addresses, etc. --> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="london">London</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>28 July 1913</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
            <opener><dateline><date when="1913-07-28">July 28, 1913</dateline></date>
                <salute>My dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Miss Monroe</persName>-</salute></opener>
            <p>Thank you very much for the copy of "<title key="poetry" level="j">Poetry</title>" which came last week. I was much pleased at the
               appearance of those two things of mine <!--do we know what these are?-->. How interesting the <persName key="fs_flint">Flint</persName> things were<!-- do we know what things? -->, don’t you think so?
            <p>I also have to thank you for [the] letter of introduction to <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra Pound</persName>. I don’t know whether you
               have heard from him, yet; or, if you have, whether he has told you of all of his efforts [on] my behalf. I
               sent him your note, and after some correspondence, he came here to dinner. We had a most delightful
               evening, and it ended in his taking one of my poems to print in a group of "<orgName key="imagists">Imagistes</orgName>" in the <date when="1913-09">mid-August</date>mid-August
               number of "<title key="egoist" level="j">The New Free Woman</title>,” and in his advising me to send another to "<title key="englishReview" level="j">The English Review </title>,”
               saying that if they would not print it, he would. He has also arranged for me to meet <persName key="wb_yeats">Yeats</persName> this week,
               and is also to take me to tea at the <title key="ford_hueffer">Ford Maddox Hueffer’s</title>. That he has done more than justice to your
               letter of introduction, you see, and what especially pleases me is his evident interest in my work. Mr.
               Pound is no flatterer, but his reticent praise is good to hear, and his occasional criticisms very much to
               the point. He is reading me the ms. of his new book some day this week. He tells me that he and you
               have never met. That is a pity, for he would have added to your gallery of personalities. Figure to
               yourself a young man, arrayed as “poet,” and yet making the costume agreeable by his personal charm.
               Figure again a sweep of conversation and youthful enthusiasm, which keeps him talking, and talking
               delightfully, as many hours as you choose. The violence of his writings giving way to show a very thin-
               skinned and sensitive personality. Opening out like a flower in a sympathetic circle, and I should imagine
               shutting up like a clam in an alien atmosphere. A most delightful companion, and in personal
               conversation, not in the least didactic, rather dreading the attitude, in fact. That he will outgrow some of
               his theories, I feel sure. His taste is too fine to confine itself within the walls of any school, even his own.
               He is so young that all sorts of developments may be expected, I think the chip-on-the-shoulder attitude
               will disappear in time, it ought to.</p>
            <p>Altogether you see [what] a pleasant road your letter has opened to me.</p>
            <p>Of course this letter is confidential and not for publication. I have got, and looked over, all the
               new books on poetry, and they are nothing. I told Mr. Pound about my review on <persName key="dh_lawrence">Lawrence’s</persName> Poems,
               and that it was diametrically opposed to his. He laughed and said he would print it in his paper. But I
               have not got it with me. I also went to see <orgName key="poetryBookshop">The Poetry Bookshop</orgName>, and a little, four or five line, description
               of it might go well in your magazine, what do you think?</p> 
            <p>I hope your summer is not so hot as it was when I left home, and that you are well. I leave for
               <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> next week, where Mr. Pound is, I believe, to give me one or two more introductions.</p>
            <p>Thanks to you, therefore, I am meeting just the people I wanted to see, and Believe me, with renewed gratitude,</p>
            <closer>Very sincerely yours.    
            <signed><persName key="Amy Lowell">Amy Lowell</persName></signed></closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

