<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1915-06-23">23 June 1915</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="erb">Elizabeth Boarini</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="tm">Taylor Mansheim</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$91i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc><p>This letter is six pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry Monroe” are written in pencil at the top.</p></physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following: <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --> </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline</placeName></settlement>
                    <date>23 June 1915</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1915-06-23">June 23, 1915.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet</persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p><persName key="ferris_greenslet">Mr/ Greenslet</persName> has told me of your letter to him of <date when="1915-06-19">June 19th</date>. I do not know what he
                answered himself, but I think I can straighten out the matter by writing to you.</p>
               <p>Let me hastily say that Mr. Greenslet had nothing whatever to do with the preface. The
                book was handed to him for publication with the preface all written, and he accepted it, preface
                and all. No one of us six were responsible for that preface. It was tinkered by all six of us, and no
                one of us would be at liberty to change it without the concurrence of all the others.</p>
               <p>Now I think, my Dear Girl, you are laboring under a misapprehension in the attitude you
                   take in requesting that <title key="poetry" level = "j">“Poetry”</title> should be mentioned in the bibliography at the end of our book.
                You are taking the attitude that “Poetry” is a book in itself. Now I never understood that you so
                understood it. You call it a magazine of verse; it comes out serially like a magazine; and in
                <pb n="02">treating it as a magazine, rather than as a book, no slight was intended to you. We were merely
                following the usual method in such cases. If 30 pages out of 77 were first printed in your paper,
                that still leaves 47 unaccounted for. Of those 47, a good many appeared in <title key="poetryDrama" level="j">“Poetry and Drama”</title>,
                <title key="egoist" level="j">“The Egoist,”</title> and <title key="smartSet" level="j">“The Smart Set.”</title> In those cases, therefore, the copyrights were held by them.
                No one of them has made any kick.</p>
               <p>It is, of course, true that you were the great herald of Imagism in this country, but our
                preface was not supposed to contain a history of Imagism; and we only made the remark about
                the first Anthology which we did, to explain why we were publishing under a separate title. I
                thought it abominable the way <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> left out all acknowledgement of “Poetry” in his first
                Anthology; but in acknowledging out debt to “Poetry” in the usual way, I felt that we had done
                all that was necessary in that particular place, and I think that, treating your book as a magazine,
                we did all that was customary.</p>
               <p>I have never heard of a magazine refusing permission to authors, or a group of authors, to
               <pb n="03">reprint any of their poems which had appeared in its pages. It is a commonplace of the business.
                Many magazines merely go so far as to say that in buying and copywriting the poem, they are
                only buying the magazine rights. This is the attitude which <title key="atlantic" level="j">“The Atlantic”</title> takes, and even the
                magazines that do not announce that fact always act upon it.</p>
               <p>You know how greatly I admire the work you have done in “Poetry.” Out of my own
                head, and with no suggestion from you, I have offered to write an article upon it, and you know I
                shall keep my word. And if I do not succeed in getting it published in <title key="newRepublic" leve="j">“The New Republic”</title> or
                elsewhere, it will not be for want of trying. But I feel that you are mistaken in feeling slighted in
                the preface of the Anthology, or in the bibliography. I feel it would be wiser for “Poetry” to
                assume merely the position desired by all other magazines, and seek its advertising where it
                legitimately belongs. To desire special recognition in a place where it would have sounded
                <pb n="04">dragged in, or in a bibliography which was carefully stated to be of books, in contradiction to
                magazines, would be amateurish, I think. If <title key="some_imagist_poets" level="m">“Some Imagist Poets”</title> should reach a second edition,
                I trust you will not feel offended if I, who although not the editor, am responsible for the printing
                of the book, begged you not to desire us to change the preface, as to do so, when six people must
                agree to it, is almost an impossibility.</p>
               <p>I beg you, dear Harriet, to believe in our sincere appreciation of “Poetry” and our
                admiration of you as its editor, and leave me to do you all possible justice in the article which I
                write this <date when="1915">Autumn</date>. If you still feel strongly upon the subject, rather than give you a wrong
                impression as to our gratitude, will you allow me to insert a paragraph to that effect in the new
                Anthology, which will appear next <date when="1916">Spring</date>, rather than to laboriously change the plates of this
                one? The latter I will certainly do. In fact, I think I should have done it anyway, but I shall be
                very much obliged to you, if you will not insist upon any change in this one, simply because of
                mechanical difficulties, of distance from the other authors and electrotype plates, to mak<pb n="05">ing a
                change.</p>
               <p>Now it is my turn to kick. It seems to me that in your review you were a little unkind to
                us. You laid a great deal of stress upon the fact that we did not acknowledge our debt to you.
                You referred constantly to the people who are not in the Anthology. Would it have been disloyal
                to Ezra, and would not it have been graceful to me, had you confined your remarks to the things
                which were in the book and ont referred to so many of the things which were not? It seems to me
                that my constant loyalty to you, my sincere interest in this magazine, and my desire to always
                identify myself with it as much as possible, might have led you to assume the dignified attitude
                of silence, which we have taken in regard to our schism with Ezra. If I chose to come out with
                the whole story, Ezra would not be left in a very pleasant position. I am willing to be absolutely
                silent and not accuse him in any way; but I do not like being covertly accused, particularly by
                those whom I consider (sic) my friends, and who I think <pb n="06">owe me the same loyalty which I always
                show to them. How loyal I am to you, Harriet, you will never know. I wrote and remonstrated
                with <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard</persName> for his method of reviewing your book and, although I am not my brother’s keeper,
                I have done my best. Don’t you want to cease referring to the break between Ezra and the rest of
                us? If I am willing to be silent, you, as Ezra’s friend, should be thankful.</p>
               <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
                <postscript><label>P.S.</label> Ferris Greenslet tells me that a magazine editor only buys the magazine copyright to to
                poems he publishes, not the book copyright, unless it is specifically so stated in the contract. He
                says that it has been tried in court over and over again, and this is always the decision.</postscript>
                    
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
