<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe"> Harriet Monroe </persName>, <date when="1916-02-17"
                    >February 17 1916</date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="jp"> Julia Paella </persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="cddvn"> Consuelo Diaz de Valdes Navarrete</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$132i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc> 
                        <p>This letter is three pages long. On the first page, the words “Poetry (Monroe)” are written 
                            in pencil at the top. The other pages have, typed, H.M. with the corresponding page number 
                            in the top left corner, and the date (2/17/16) in the top right corner. On the third page, 
                            there is faint text on the page near the top. The text is large and mirrored on the opposite 
                            side of the page, perhaps written on the other side? It reads, “BERKSHIRE LINEN U.S.A.”.</p> 
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>
                   
                </p>  
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type=”sent”>
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><!-- Doesn't said a place --></settlement>
                    <date> February 17 1916</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type=”received”>
                    <persName>Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type=”letter”>
                <opener><dateline><date when="1916-02-17">February 17, 1916</date>.</dateline></date>
                    <salute>Dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet:</persName></salute></opener>
                <p> Your letter has just come. In regard to the Anthology, I supposed of course that you were only taking poems that had appeared 
                    in <title key="poetry" level="j">your magazine,</title> and I was therefore only chooding 
                    from among the things of mine which you have published. As to your taking <title key="patterns" level="a">&quot;Patterns,&quot;</title> 
                    I am quite willing, and I am sure <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson</persName> will be; but it has already been extensively 
                    quoted, and we are putting it in our <title key="some_imagist_poets" level=",">Imagist Anthology.</title> I suppose you would not consider 
                    <title key="bombardment" level="a">the &quot;Bombardment.&quot;</title> That was in last year&apos;s Imagist Anthology, and also 
                    in <persName key="ws_braithwaite">Braithwaite&apos;s</persName> <title key="<!-- unclear what book this is--> " level="m" >book.</title>  As a matter of fact, I think it is 
                    rather a good thing from the point of view of the public, to keep dinning one poem at them, for then they get used to it and it gets into 
                    the current coin of the language. So if you wish to include &quot;Patterns&quot; and at the same time will be so kind as to put
                    in <title key="redSlippers" level="a">&quote;Red Slippers,&quot;</title> as I should like to show some of my &quot;polyphonic,&quot; I 
                    shall be quite satisfied.</p>
                <p> Of course, I do not want you to not like the things you put in of  mine, any more than I want not to like them myself. I realized why 
                    you put in “Apology” and “A Blockhead,” but it seemed to me that “Apology” alone was enough; but if you particularly 
                    want <title key="aBlockhead" level="a">&quot;A Blockhead,&quot;</title> I have no objection; so that nos 
                    my contribution to the Anthology will consist of: &quot;Patterns,&quot; &quot;Red Slippers,&quot;<title key="coalPicker" level="a">&quot;The Coal Picker,&quot;</title>
                    <title key="apology" level="a">&quot;Apology,&quot;</title> <title key="painterOnSilk" level="a">&quot;The Painter on Silk,&quot;</title> 
                    <title key="bungler" level="a">&quot;The Bungler,&quot;</title> <title key="aGift" level="a">&quot;A Gift,&quot;</title>
                    <title key="aliens" level="a">&quot;Aliens,&quot;</title> <title key="" level="a">&quot;The Back Bay Fens&quot;</title> (this in your list appears
                    as &quot;Fenway Park,&quot; but I find that &quot;Fenway Park&quot; is a base-ball park, so please change it to &quot;The Back Bay Fens&quot;), 
                    <title key="mayEveningInCentralPark" level="a">&quot;May Evening in Central Park,&quot;</title> <title key="solitaire" level="a">&quot;Solitaire,&quot;</title> 
                    <title key="aLady" level="a">&quot;A Lady,&quot;</title> and <title key="venusTrasiens" level="a">&quot;Venus Transiens,&quot;</title> &ndash;with or 
                    without &quot;A Blockhead,&quot; as you see fit. </p>
                <p> Now about <title key="turnpike" level="a">&quot;Off the Turnpike.&quot;</title> Your suggestion to shorten it does not meet with my approval. 
                    I am afraid the poem must stand as it is. 
                <pb="n2">   
                    <persName key="mary_aldis">Mrs. Aldis</persName> is to give it as a play (together with another poem of the same series 
                    called <title key="grocery">&quot;The Grocery,&quot;</title> which has just been accepted by <title key="masses" level="j">the &quot;Masses&quot;</title>) 
                    sometime <date when="1916">this Spring.</date> Now here is the difficult &ndash; I do not see why you should pay me bargain rates. You have 
                    the same number of pages in the issue, anway. Why, because you have to pay the rate of those pages to one person, should you 
                    pay any less than if you had to pay ten? It really seems to me that you might pay me the regulation rates. And here is another 
                    thing: hitherto I have always appeared twice a year in &quot;Poetry,&quot; and that seems to me about right, It certainly does not err on
                    the side of too frequent an appearance. Now you have not had anything of mine in the magazines since <date when="1915-09">September</date>, and 
                    if you keep me waiting until <date when="1916">July</date> or <date when="1916">August,</date> it is practically a year. Also I think it would be 
                    to your advantage to have the poem on Mrs. Aldis&apos;s programmes put down as having appeared in your paper, as &quot;The Grocery&quot; will 
                    be put down as having appeared in the &quot;Masses.&quot; <persName key="louis_untermeyer">Louis Untermeyer</persName> writes me that the 
                    editors of the &quot;Masses&quot; like the poem so much that they are keeping other manuscripts waiting, in order to publish it 
                    immediately, an that it is possible that they may publish it next month; and that is in a paper where I am only just beginning to appear, 
                    whereas you, who have always published me, want to hold me back six months before putting me in.</p>
                <p> As I told you, I am going to <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> on the <date when="1916-03-19">19th of March.</date> I hope I shall see 
                    you at <orgName key="littleTheatre">the Little Theatre</orgName> that night, but I shall telephone you when I strike the town,
                    because of course the lecture is incidental &ndash; what I really want to do is to talk over these things with you. We may keep the question of 
                    &quot;Off the Turnpike&quot; to be discussed  
               <pb="n3"> 
                   <!-- the word discussed is cut between pages. Page number 2 has written "dis-" while page number 3 has written "cussed" -->
                    cussed when I see you. As for the Anthology, I shall be quite satisfied with the arrangement made above, if that suits you, and from your 
                    letter I think it will. So go ahead and do it on that basis. </p>
                <p> I never meant to accuse you of underhandedness in regard to <persName key="agnes_lee">Mrs. Freer&apos;s</persName> article. After 
                    reading my defence of you in the <title key="poetryJournal">&quot;Poetry Journal&quot;</title> (which, by the way, you do not mention, 
                    and I suppose you do not like it), you will see that I have said that you were scrupulously honest as an editor. I did not consider that in 
                    using the blue pencil on my article, as I thought you had done, you were dishonest, merely editorial; but I have already apologized for that, 
                    and you may be quite sure that, however annoyed we get at each other in the course of business (and I think in a mild way that is inevitable), 
                    I know you to be as truthful and honest as the Rock of Ages, one of the most so of anybody I have ever seen, and I cordially admire all you 
                    have done, and are doing, for the cause of poetry, even if at the same time I do not think you quite rate me at my true valuation. 
                    There is honesty for you!</p>
                <closer>Affectionately,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


