<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>, <date when="1914-11-05"> 05 November 1914 </date></title>
                <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
                <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
                <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
                    Chicago</sponsor>
                <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="lma">Liam Anderson</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="blw">Brianna Wright</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="blw">Brianna Wright</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""> <!-- insert name --> </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when=""> <!-- Add date when published to website here --> </date> <!-- date of publication unclear at time of encoding -blw -->
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                        <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                        <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                        <idno type="URI">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427331885$47i</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>This letter is three pages long. It is not typed on Amy Lowell’s stationery.  The word “Poetry” is penciled in at the top of the first page.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>This letter contains references to the following: The <rs key="poundFeud" type="theme">Pound feud</rs> <!-- Insert tagged subject keywords here; will link to theme-ography --></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                &personography;
            </particDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
            </textClass>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName>Amy Lowell</persName>
                    <settlement><placeName key="brookline">Brookline, MA</placeName></settlement>
                    <date when="1914-11-05">05 November 1914</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet Monroe</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener><dateline><date when="1914-10-17">Oct. 17, 1914</date></dateline><salute>My dear <persName key="harriet_monroe">Harriet <add place="above" type="insertion" rend="pencil">Monroe</add><!--The addition was not in the original transcription - blw--></persName>:</salute></opener>
                <p>The Literary Editor of <title key="bostonAmerican" level="j">&quot;The Boston American&quot;</title> has occasionally permitted me to write reviews. They are anonymous which is the one drawback from my point of view as when one wishes to praise a friend one wishes to have all the world know how highly one thinks of her. But <persName>Mr. Williams</persName><!-- Currently unsure of who Mr. Williams is, tagged without a key for the time being -blw --> has only one signed article in his paper and that is his own. Now it occurs to me that he may permit me to write a review of <title key="youAndI" level="m">your book</title> for him. Ever since I got your letter yesterday morning I have been trying to get hold of him by telephone and he has always been out. But I think I shall be able to round him up before very long and I trust that he will not turn down my suggestion.</p>
                <p>The paper has a large circulation and I think it ought to be a good place. At any rate it is the only paper except <persName key="margaret_anderson">Margaret Anderson&apos;s</persName> <title key="littleReview" level="j">&quot;Little Review&quot;</title> which I write for and I think it will be better for me not to do it in a <placeName key="chicago">Chicago</placeName> paper owing <pb n="2">to being in the family, as it were, and so this seems distinctly the best arrangement. </pb>
                <p>I am very much afraid that <persName key="ezra_pound">Ezra</persName> may try his best to injure me owing to his fury at that unfortunate advertisement. It would therefore be a great kindness to me if you could review <title key="swordBladesAndPoppySeeds" level="m">my book</title> somewhat at length as all his friends in <placeName key="england">England</placeName> see <title key="poetry" level="j">&quot;Poetry&quot;</title> and a few nice words will do a great deal toward allaying the impression which he is trying to give. Not only do his letters to me show his state of mind but <persName key="richard_aldington">Richard Aldington</persName> writes me that he is being very nasty.</p>
                <p>Funnily enough I do not feel angry with him, merely very sad and rather disillusioned. I thought him a different man. But I do not want to obviate as much as possible the effects of his venomous pen and his still more venomous tongue on my poor little book. I am unpopular enough and misunderstood enough by the poets of other schools without having this one turn and rend me.</p>
                <p>In contradistinction the fine loyalty and generosity of <orgName key="the_aldingtons">the Aldingtons</orgName> stands out like a shining torch.</p>
                <p>It is ridiculous for I certainly never in[sentence cut off] his feelings and I wish I had <pb n="3">never suggested <title key="some_imagiste_poets" level="m">the anthology</title> as I certainly never would have done so had I supposed he would not come into it. However that cannot be helped now, only I beg you to give me a helping hand through this exceedingly hard moment.</p>
                <p>The <date when="1914-11">November</date> number has not come, I am most anxious to see it.</p>
                <closer>Affectionately yours,</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
