<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?> <!-- standalone statement declares that this document will link to other ones i.e. the site index content -->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc [
<!ENTITY personography SYSTEM "ALLP/siteIndex/allpPersonography.xml">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from <persName key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</persName> to <persName
                  key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sedgwick</persName>, <date when="1914-09-29">29
                  September 1914</date></title>
            <author key="amy_lowell">Amy Lowell</author>
            <editor ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</editor>
            <sponsor>Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola University
               Chicago</sponsor>
            <principal ref="mb">Melissa Bradshaw</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription proofed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance provided by</resp>
               <persName ref="">
                  <!-- insert name -->
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Amy Lowell Letters Project</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="">
               <!-- Add date when published to website here -->
            </date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the Houghton Library Repository.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>Harvard College Library</institution>
                  <repository>Houghton Library Repository</repository>
                  <collection>Amy Lowell Correspondence</collection>
                  <idno type="URI"
                     >https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:427718954$5i</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <p>Three pages on stationery that reads: “MISS A. LOWELL / HEATH STREET /
                     BROOKLINE, MASS” in upper left corner. Typewritten in black ink, editorial
                     corrections marked in fountain pen. Text written in pencil at top of first page
                     reads “ “Atlantic” (Sedgwick).” Also in pencil is the word “fireworks” written
                     above “this poem” in the first line. Ink smudges appear on the last page after
                     the text; unsigned.</p>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This letter contains references to the following:</p>
            <p><rs key="ww1" type="theme">WWI</rs>, <rs key="freeVerse" type="theme">free verse
                  (vers libre)</rs>, <rs key="polyProse" type="theme">polyphonic prose</rs></p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc> &personography; </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <!-- document-level keywords applied here -->
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <placeName key="brookline">Brookline, Mass.</placeName>
               <dateline><date when="1914-09-29">Sept. 29, 1914</date></dateline></opener>
            <salute>My dear<persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery</persName>:</salute>
            <anchor xml:id="n1"/>
            <p>I am venturing to send you <title key="allies" level="a">this poem</title><anchor
                  xml:id="n2"/> because I believe in it myself, and I am in hopes that, even through
               a form<anchor xml:id="n3"/> which I believe you do not care for, you may see its
               serious intent. My idea was to represent the citizen army which <placeName
                  key="france">France</placeName> and <placeName key="england">England</placeName>
               have put into the field; an army made up of men of all occupations and all kinds,
               each one fighting for the peace of the world which he knows and sees to be desirable,
               for liberty to do and work. And the sum total of all these desires making that
               necessary security which we call “peace,” as opposed to the devastating militarism of
               <placeName key="germany">Germany</placeName>. At the time when I wrote <title
               key="allies" level="a">this poem</title>, as you will see by the date<anchor
               xml:id="n4"/>, we did not know where the allied armies were, at least we in
               <placeName key="England">England</placeName> did not know. We only knew that they
               were marching to meet the Germans. It is under this figure that I have portrayed
               them. The words are crude, often violent. They are intended to represent the
               unsentimental anger of men who quit all they desire and regard as valuable, in the
               midst of achieve<pb/>ment, to fight a wild animal. The poet’s remarks may appear to you as
               flippant. They are intended to be merely the careless high spirits of such a
               character, thinly cloaking an urgent and serious purpose.</p>
            <p>The metre is the one in which <persName key="paul_fort">Paul Fort</persName><anchor
                  xml:id="n5"/> has been working for so long in <placeName>France</placeName>. It
               has the quality of ruggedness which is so useful for this sort of poem. It should be
               read exactly as if it were prose, and the unexpected rhymes, and the occasional
               repetition, somewhat in the manner of a refrain, are what give it its character.</p>
            <p>I read this poem to <persName key="charles_fiske">Charlie Fiske</persName><anchor
                  xml:id="n6"/> coming home on the steamer. You would hardly suppose him to be
               sympathetic to anything so different from the ordinary rhyme. In fact, before he
               asked me if I would read it to him, he prefaced his remark by saying that he did not
               care for the modern method. But while I was reading <title key="allies" level="a"
                  >this poem</title> he burst into tears and told me that he thought if I had never
               written anything else my reputation would be made by this.</p>
            <p>I hope you will feel the same way about it, because I am very anxious to have it appear in the pages of <title
                  key="atlantic" level="j">“The Atlantic.”</title> It is too serious for a pictorial
               paper like <title key="century" level="j">“The Century”</title> or <title
                  key="scribners" level="j">“Scribners,”</title><pb/> and <title key="poetry" level="j"
                  >“Poetry”</title> and <title key="littleReview" level="j">“The Little
                  Review”</title> have not a large enough circulation. Of course I know you will do
               as you think best. I only hope that you may find something in the poem which you
               consider worth while. </p>
            <p>It is too bad you have had such a nasty time. I believe that I am to have the
               pleasure of dining with you on Sunday next. I do hope the cool weather will bring
               back your strength.</p>
            <closer><salute>Sincerely yours,</salute></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <!-- Need to tag items in footnotes -->
            <note target="#n1" resp="mb"><persName key="ellery_sedgwick">Ellery Sedgwick</persName>
               (1872-1960), editor of the <title key="atlantic" level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
               from 1908-1938. Sedgwick, married to a childhood friend of Lowell, was one of her
               first literary connections. Her first published poem, “A Fixed Idea,” appeared in the
               Atlantic in 1910. </note>
            <note target="#n2" resp="mb"><title key="allies" level="a">“The Allies,”</title> from
                  <title key="menWomenGhosts" level="m">Men, Women and Ghosts</title> (Macmillan,
               1916). The poem was first published in <title key="littleReview" type="j">The Little
                  Review</title>, January, 1915. </note>
            <note target="#n3" resp="mb">The poem is written in what Lowell called Polyphonic Prose,
               poetry without enjambment that appears on the page looking like prose. </note>
            <note target="#n4" resp="mb">The poem’s subtitle, August 14, 1914, marks the German
               Empire’s invasion of Belgium/France. </note>
            <note target="#n5" resp="mb">Paul Fort (1872-1960). French poet associated with the
               Symbolist movement. Founder and editor of the literary reviews Livre d’Art and Vers
               et Prose. He published more than thirty volumes of ballads, written using a
               combination of French alexandrines and unmetered, unrhymed passages printed a prose. </note>
            <note target="n#6" resp="mb">This is presumably Boston-area lawyer Charles H. Fiske,
               Jr.</note>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
